<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="2"><pb facs="#f001"/>
                <p>what would be <lb/> the right name to put on the title-page of<lb/> an
                    excellent book; but this I feel, that the <lb/>names of all fine authors are
                    fictitious ones,<lb/> far more so than that of Junius; simply stand-<lb/>ing,
                    as they do, for the mystical, ever-eluding<lb/> spirit of all beauty, which
                    ubiquitously pos-<lb/>sesses men of genius. Purely imaginative as<lb/> this
                    fancy may appear, it nevertheless seems to<lb/> receive some warranty from the
                    fact, that on<lb/> a personal interview no great author has ever<lb/> come up
                    to the idea of his reader. But that<lb/> dust of which our bodies are composed,
                    how <lb/> can it fitly express the nobler intelligences<lb/> among us? With
                    reverence be it spoken, that<lb/> not even in the case of one deemed more than<lb/>
                    man, not even in our Saviour, did his visible<lb/> frame betoken anything of
                    the augustness of <lb/>the nature within. Else, how could those<lb/> Jewish
                    eyewitnesses fail to see heaven in his glance!</p>
                <p> It is curious, how a man may travel along a<lb/> country road, and yet miss the
                    grandest, or<lb/> sweetest of prospects by reason of an inter-<lb/>vening
                    hedge, so like all other hedges, as in<lb/> no way to hint of the wide
                    landscape beyond.<lb/> So has it been with me concerning the en-<lb/>chanting
                    landscape in the soul of this Haw-<lb/>thorne, this most excellent Man of
                    Mosses.<cb/> His "Old Manse" has been written now four<lb/> years, but I never
                    read it till a day or two<lb/> since. I had seen it in the book-stores--heard<lb/>
                    of it often--even had it recommended to me<lb/> by a tasteful friend, as a
                    rare, quiet book, per-<lb/>haps too deserving of popularity to be popu-<lb/>lar.
                    But there are so many books called "ex-<lb/>cellent," and so much</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="3">
                </div></body></text>