<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="4"><pb facs="#f003"/>
                <p>am off for the barn."</p>
                <p>Stretched on that new mown clover, the<lb/> hill-side breeze blowing over me
                    through the<lb/> wide barn door, and soothed by the hum of the<lb/> bees in
                    the meadows around, how magically<lb/> stole over me this Mossy Man! And how<lb/>
                    amply, how bountifully, did he redeem that<lb/> delicious promise to his guests
                    in the Old<lb/> Manse, of whom it is written--"Others could<lb/> give them
                    pleasure, or amusement, or instruc-<lb/>tion--these could be picked up
                    anywhere--but<lb/> it was for me to give them rest.<lb/> Rest, in a life of
                    trouble! What better could be done<lb/> for weary and world-worn spirits? What<lb/>
                    better could be done for anybody, who came<lb/> within our magic circle, than
                    to throw the spell<lb/> of a magic spirit over him?" So all that day,<lb/>
                    half-buried in the new clover, I watched this<lb/> Hawthorne's "Assyrian dawn,
                    and Paphian<lb/> sunset and moonrise, from the summit of our Eastern Hill."</p>
                <p>The soft ravishments of the man spun me<lb/> round about in a web of dreams, and
                    when<lb/> the book was closed, when the spell was over,<lb/> this wizard
                    "dismissed me with but misty re-<lb/>miniscences, as if I had been dreaming of
                    him."</p>
                <p>What a wild moonlight of contemplative<lb/> humor bathes that Old Manse!--the
                    rich and<lb/> rare distilment of a spicy and slowly-oozing<lb/> heart. No
                    rollicking rudeness, no gross fun<cb/> fed on fat dinners, and bred in the lees<lb/>
                    of wine,--but a humor so spiritually gentle, so<lb/> high, so deep, and yet</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="5">
                </div></body></text>