<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="6"><pb facs="#f005"/>
                <p>bones.<lb/> This possibility of mad destruction only made<lb/> his domestic
                    kindness the more beautiful and<lb/> touching. It was so sweet of him, being
                    en-<lb/>dowed with such power, to dwell, day after<lb/> day, and one long,
                    lonesome night after an-<lb/>other, on the dusky hearth, only now and then<lb/>
                    betraying his wild nature, by thrusting his red<lb/> tongue out of the
                    chimney-top! True, he had<lb/> done much mischief in the world, and was<lb/>
                    pretty certain to do more, but his warm heart<lb/> atoned for all. He was
                    kindly to the race of<lb/> man."</p>
                <p>But he has still other apples, not quite so<lb/> ruddy, though full as ripe;--
                    apples, that have<lb/> been left to wither on the tree, after the plea-<lb/>sant
                    autumn gathering is past. The sketch of<lb/> "The Old Apple Dealer" is
                    conceived in the<lb/> subtlest spirit of sadness; he whose "sub-<lb/>dued and
                    nerveless boyhood prefigured his<lb/> abortive prime, which, likewise,
                    contained<lb/> within itself the prophecy and image of his<lb/> lean and
                    torpid age." Such touches as are in<lb/> this piece can not proceed from any
                    common<lb/> heart. They argue such a depth of tender-<lb/>ness, such a
                    boundless sympathy with all<lb/> forms of being, such an omnipresent love, that<lb/>
                    we must needs say that this Hawthorne is<lb/> here almost alone in his
                    generation, --at least,<lb/> in the artistic manifestation of these things.<lb/>
                    Still more. Such touches as these, -- and<lb/> many, very many similar ones,
                    all through his<lb/> chapters--furnish clues, whereby we enter a<lb/></p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="7">
                </div></body></text>