<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="7"><pb facs="#f006"/>
                <p>little way into the intricate, profound heart<lb/> where they originated. And we
                    see, that<lb/> suffering, some time or other and in some shape<lb/> or
                    other,-- this only can enable any man to<lb/> depict it in others. All over
                    him, Hawthorne's<lb/> melancholy rests like an Indian Summer,<lb/> which,
                    though bathing a whole country in one<lb/> softness, still reveals the
                    distinctive hue of<lb/> every towering hill, and each far-winding vale.</p>
                <p>But it is the least part of genius that attracts<lb/> admiration. Where
                    Hawthorne is known, he<lb/> seems to be deemed a pleasant writer, with a<lb/>
                    pleasant style, --a sequestered, harmless man,<lb/> from whom any deep and
                    weighty thing would<lb/> hardly be anticipated--a man who means no<lb/>
                    meanings. But there is no man, in whom<lb/> humor and love, like mountain
                    peaks, soar to<lb/> such a rapt height, as to receive the irradiations<lb/> of
                    the upper skies; --there is no man in<lb/> whom humor and love are developed in
                    that<lb/> high form called genius; no such man can<lb/> exist without also
                    possessing, as the indis-<lb/>pensable complement of these, a great, deep<lb/>
                    intellect, which drops down into the universe<lb/> like a plummet. Or, love and
                    humor are only<lb/> the eyes, through which such an intellect<lb/> views this
                    world. The great beauty in such a<lb/> mind is but the product of its strength.<lb/>
                    What, to all readers, can be more charming<lb/> than the piece entitled
                    "Monsieur du Miroir;"<lb/> and to a reader at all capable of fully fathom-<lb/>ing
                    it, what, at the same time, can possess<lb/> more mystical depth of
                    meaning?--yes, there<lb/> he sits, and looks at me,--this "shape of mys-<lb/>tery,"
                    this "identical Monsieur du Miroir."<lb/></p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="8">
                </div></body></text>