<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="15"><pb facs="#f014"/>
                <head>HAWTHORNE AND HIS MOSSES.</head>
                <head><hi rend="small-caps align(center)">by a virginian spending july in vermont</hi>
                    .</head>
                <head>[<hi rend="italics">Concluded from the last number.</hi>]</head>
                <p>Now, I do not say that Nathaniel of Salem is <lb/> a greater than William of
                    Avon, or as great.<lb/> But the difference between the two men is by<lb/> no
                    means immeasurable. Not a very great<lb/> deal more, and Nathaniel were verily
                    William.</p>
                <p>This, too, I mean, that if Shakspeare has <lb/>not been equalled, give the world
                    time, and <lb/>he is sure to be surpassed, in one hemisphere or<lb/>the other.
                    Nor will it at all do to say, that the <lb/>world is getting grey and grizzled
                    now, and<lb/> has lost that fresh charm which she wore of <lb/>old, and by
                    virtue of which the great poets of <lb/>past times made themselves what we
                    esteem<lb/> them to be. Not so. The world is as young<lb/> to-day, as when it
                    was created; and this Ver-<lb/>mont morning dew is as wet to my feet, as <lb/>Eden's
                    dew to Adam's. Nor has Nature been<lb/> all over ransacked by our progenitors,
                    so that<lb/> no new charms and mysteries remain for this<lb/> latter
                    generation to find. Far from it. The <lb/>trillionth part has not yet been
                    said; and all<lb/> that has been said, but multiplies the avenues <lb/>to what
                    remains to be said. It is not so much<lb/> paucity as superabundance of
                    material that <lb/>seems to incapacitate modern authors. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="16">
                </div></body></text>