<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="18"><pb facs="#f017"/>
                <p>given, in certain cases) even <lb/>from some Englishmen, than from their own <lb/>countrymen.
                    There are hardly five critics in<lb/> America; and several of them are asleep.
                    As<lb/> for patronage, it is the American author who <lb/>now patronizes his
                    country, and not his country<lb/> him. And if at times some among them appeal <lb/>to
                    the people for more recognition, it is not <lb/>always with selfish motives,
                    but patriotic ones.</p>
                <p>It is true, that but few of them as yet have <lb/>evinced that decided
                    originality which merits<lb/> great praise. But that graceful writer, who <lb/>perhaps
                    of all Americans has received the most<lb/> plaudits from his own country for
                    his produc-<lb/>tions,--that very popular and amiable writer,<lb/> however
                    good, and self-reliant in many things,<lb/> perhaps owes his chief reputation
                    to the self-<lb/>acknowledged imitation of a foreign model, and <lb/>to the
                    studied avoidance of all topics but<lb/> smooth ones. But it is better to fail
                    in origin-<lb/>ality, than to succeed in imitation. He who <lb/>has never
                    failed somewhere, that man cannot<lb/> be great. Failure is the true test of
                    greatness<lb/>. And if it be said, that continual success is a <lb/>proof that
                    a man wisely knows his powers,--<lb/>it is only to be added, that, in that
                    case, he <lb/>knows them to be small. Let us believe it, <lb/>then, once for
                    all, that there is no hope for us <lb/>in these smooth pleasing writers that
                    know<lb/> their powers. Without malice, but to speak<lb/> the plain fact, they
                    but furnish an appendix <lb/>to Goldsmith, and other English authors. And <lb/>we
                    want no American Goldsmiths; nay, we <lb/>want no American Miltons. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                </div></body></text>