<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf"><pb facs="#f018"/>
                <p>It were the vilest <lb/> thing you could say of a true American author, <lb/>
                    that he were an American Tompkins. Call him <lb/>an American and have done, for
                    you cannot say<lb/> a nobler thing of him. But it is not meant <lb/>that all
                    American writers should studiously<lb/>cleave to nationality in their writings;
                    only <lb/> this, no American writer should write like <lb/>an Englishman, or a
                    Frenchman; let him write <lb/>like a man, for then he will be sure to write <lb/>
                    like an American. Let us away with this <lb/>leaven of literary flunkeyism
                    towards England. <lb/>If either must play the flunkey in this thing, <lb/> let
                    England do it, not us. While we are <lb/>rapidly preparing for that political
                    supremacy <lb/>among the nations, which prophetically awaits <lb/>as at the
                    close of the present century, in a <lb/> literary point of view, we are
                    deplorably <lb/> unprepared for it; and we seem studious to <lb/> remain so.
                    Hitherto, reasons might have ex-<lb/>isted why this should be; but no good
                    reason <lb/>exists now. And all that is requisite to <lb/>amendment in this
                    matter, is simply this: that <lb/>while fully acknowledging all excellence
                    every-<lb/>where, we should refrain from unduly lauding <lb/>foreign writers
                    and, at the same time, duly <lb/>recognize the meritorious writers that are our <lb/>own;--those
                    writers who breathe that un-<lb/>shackled, democratic spirit of Christianity in
                    all<lb/> things, which now takes the practical lead in<lb/> this world, though
                    at the same</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="20">
                </div></body></text>