<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="20"><pb facs="#f019"/>
                <p>time led by <lb/>ourselves--us Americans. Let us boldly con-<lb/>temn all
                    imitation, though it comes to us <lb/>graceful and fragrant as the morning; and <lb/>foster
                    all originality, <lb/>though, at first, it be crabbed and ugly as our own pine
                    knots. <lb/>And if any of our authors fail, or seem to fail, <lb/>then, in the
                    words of my Carolina cousin, let <lb/>us clap him on the shoulder, and back him <lb/>against
                    all Europe for his second round. The <lb/>truth is, that in one point of view,
                    this matter <lb/>of a national literature has come to such a pass <lb/>with
                    us, that in some sense we must turn bul-<cb/>lies, else the day is lost, or
                    superiority so far <lb/>beyond us, that we can hardly say it will ever <lb/>be
                    ours.</p>
                <p>And now, my countrymen, as an excellent <lb/>author, of your own flesh and
                    blood,--an un-<lb/>imitating, and, perhaps, in his way, an inimi-<lb/>table
                    man--whom better can I commend to <lb/>you, in the first place, than Nathaniel
                    Haw-<lb/>thorne. He is one of the new, and far better <lb/>generation of your
                    writers. The smell of <lb/>your beeches and hemlocks is upon him; your o<lb/>wn
                    broad praries are in his soul; and if you <lb/>travel away inland into his deep
                    and noble <lb/>nature, you will hear the far roar of his <lb/>Niagara. Give
                    not over to future generations <lb/>the glad duty of acknowledging him for what <lb/>he
                    is. Take that joy to your self, in your own <lb/>generation; and so shall he
                    feel those grateful <lb/>impulses in him, that may possibly prompt <lb/>him to
                    the full flower of some still greater <lb/>achievement in your eyes.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="21">
                </div></body></text>