<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf" n="22"><pb facs="#f021"/>
                <p>subse-<lb/>quently fancying to himself some ideal image <lb/>of the man and his
                    mind. And if you rightly <lb/>look for it, you will almost always find that <lb/>the
                    author himself has somewhere furnished <lb/>you with his own picture. <lb/>For
                    poets (whether <lb/>in prose or verse), being painters of <lb/>nature, are
                    like their brethren of the pencil, the true <lb/>portrait-painters, who, in the
                    multitude of like-<lb/>nesses to be sketched, do not invariably omit <lb/>their
                    own; and in all high instances, they paint <lb/>them without any vanity, though
                    at times <lb/>with a lurking something, that would take <lb/>several pages to
                    properly define.</p>
                <p>I submit it, then, to those best acquainted <lb/>with the man personally,
                    whether the follow-<lb/>ing is not Nathaniel Hawthorne;--and to him-<lb/>self,
                    whether something involved in it does not <lb/>express the temper of his
                    mind,--that lasting <lb/>temper of all true, candid men--a seeker, not <lb/>a
                    finder yet:-- <lb/>
                </p>
                <p>"A man now entered, in neglected attire, with <lb/>the aspect of a thinker, but
                    somewhat too rough-<lb/>hewn and brawny for a scholar. His face was <lb/>full
                    of sturdy vigor, with some finer and keener <lb/>attribute beneath; though
                    harsh at first, it was <lb/>tempered with the glow of a large, warm heart, <cb/>which
                    had force enough to heat his powerful intel-<lb/>lect through and through. He
                    advanced to the <lb/>Intelligencer, and looked at him with a glance of <lb/>such
                    stern sincerity, that perhaps few secrets were <lb/>beyond its scope.</p>
                <p>"'I seek for Truth,' said he."</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="align(center)">* * * * *</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Twenty-four hours have elapsed since <lb/>writing the foregoing. I have just
                    returned <lb/>from the hay-mow, charged more and more <lb/>with love and
                    admiration of Hawthorne. For <lb/>I have just been gleaning through the Mosses, <lb/>picking
                    up many things here and there that had <lb/>previously escaped me. And I found
                    that but <lb/>to glean after this man, </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                </div></body></text>