<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw"><body><div type="leaf"><pb facs="#f025"/>
                <p>Belshazzar when he banquetted his lords <lb/>in Babylon.</p>
                <p>But my chief business now, is to point out <lb/>a particular page in this piece,
                    having reference <lb/>to an honored guest, who under the name of <lb/>"The
                    Master Genius" but in the guise "of a <lb/>young man of poor attire, with no
                    insignia of <lb/>rank or acknowledged eminence," is intro-<lb/>duced to the
                    ,an of Fancy, who is the giver <lb/>of the feast. Now the page having reference <lb/>to
                    this "Master Genius," so happily expresses <lb/>much of what I yesterday wrote,
                    touching the <lb/>coming of the literary Shiloh of America, <lb/>that I cannot
                    but be charmed by the coincidence; <lb/>especially, when it shows such a parity
                    of ideas, <lb/>at least in this one point, between a man like <lb/>Hawthorne
                    and a man like me.</p>
                <p>And here, let me throw out another conceit <lb/>of mine touching this American
                    Shiloh, or <lb/>"Master Genius," as Hawthorne calls him. <lb/>May it not be,
                    that this commanding mind has <lb/>not been, is not, and never will be,
                    individually <lb/>developed in any one man? And would it, <lb/>indeed, appear
                    so unreasonable to suppose, <lb/>that this great fulness and overflowing may <lb/>be,
                    or may be destined to be, shared by a plu-<lb/>rality of men of genius? Surely,
                    to take the <cb/>very greatest example on record, Shakspeare <lb/>cannot be
                    regarded as in himself the concretion <lb/>of all the genius of his time; nor
                    as so im-<lb/>measurably beyond Marlow, Webster, Ford, <lb/>Beaumont, Jonson,
                    that those great men can <lb/>be said to share none of his power? For <lb/>one,
                    I conceive that there were dramatists in <lb/>Elizabeth's day, between whom and
                    Shak-<lb/>speare the distance was by no means great. <lb/>Let anyone, hitherto
                    little acquainted with <lb/>those neglected old authors, for the first time <lb/>read
                    them thoroughly, or even read Charles Lamb's <lb/>Specimens of them, and he
                    will</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                </div></body></text>