<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lw">
        <body>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f000"/>
                <head>HAWTHORNE AND HIS MOSSES.</head>
                <head><hi rend="small-caps">by a virginian spending july in vermont</hi>.</head>
                <p><hi rend="small-caps">A papered</hi> chamber in a fine old farm-house,<lb/> a
                    mile from any other dwelling, and dipped to <lb/> the eaves in
                    foliage--surrounded by moun-<lb/>tains, old woods, and Indian ponds,--this,
                    surely, is the place to write of Hawthorne.<lb/> Some charm is in this northern
                    air, for love<lb/> and duty seem both impelling to the task. A<lb/> man of a
                    deep and noble nature has seized me<lb/> in this seclusion. His wild,
                    witch-voice rings <lb/> through me; or, in softer cadences, I seem to hear it
                    in the songs of the hill-side birds <lb/> that sing in the larch trees at my
                    window.</p>
                <p>Would that all excellent books were found-<lb/>lings, without father or mother,
                    that so it<lb/> might be we could glorify them, without in-<lb/>cluding their
                    ostensible authors!<note>HM had used a full-stop in the MS.</note> Nor would<lb/>
                    any true man take exception to this; least of<lb/> all, he who writes, "When
                    the Artist rises high<lb/> enough to achieve the Beautiful, the symbol by<lb/>
                    which he makes it perceptible to mortal senses<lb/> becomes of little value in
                    his eyes, while his<lb/> spirit possesses itself in the enjoyment of the
                    reality."</p>
                <p>But more than this. I know not</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="2">
                <pb facs="#f001"/>
                <p>what would be <lb/> the right name to put on the title-page of<lb/> an
                    excellent book; but this I feel, that the <lb/>names of all fine authors are
                    fictitious ones,<lb/> far more so than that of Junius; simply stand-<lb/>ing,
                    as they do, for the mystical, ever-eluding<lb/> spirit of all beauty, which
                    ubiquitously pos-<lb/>sesses men of genius. Purely imaginative as<lb/> this
                    fancy may appear, it nevertheless seems to<lb/> receive some warranty from the
                    fact, that on<lb/> a personal interview no great author has ever<lb/> come up
                    to the idea of his reader. But that<lb/> dust of which our bodies are composed,
                    how <lb/> can it fitly express the nobler intelligences<lb/> among us? With
                    reverence be it spoken, that<lb/> not even in the case of one deemed more than<lb/>
                    man, not even in our Saviour, did his visible<lb/> frame betoken anything of
                    the augustness of <lb/>the nature within. Else, how could those<lb/> Jewish
                    eyewitnesses fail to see heaven in his glance!</p>
                <p> It is curious, how a man may travel along a<lb/> country road, and yet miss the
                    grandest, or<lb/> sweetest of prospects by reason of an inter-<lb/>vening
                    hedge, so like all other hedges, as in<lb/> no way to hint of the wide
                    landscape beyond.<lb/> So has it been with me concerning the en-<lb/>chanting
                    landscape in the soul of this Haw-<lb/>thorne, this most excellent Man of
                    Mosses.<cb/> His "Old Manse" has been written now four<lb/> years, but I never
                    read it till a day or two<lb/> since. I had seen it in the book-stores--heard<lb/>
                    of it often--even had it recommended to me<lb/> by a tasteful friend, as a
                    rare, quiet book, per-<lb/>haps too deserving of popularity to be popu-<lb/>lar.
                    But there are so many books called "ex-<lb/>cellent," and so much</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="3">
                <pb facs="#f002"/>
                <p>unpopular merit, that <lb/>amid the thick stir of other things, the hint of<lb/>
                    my tasteful friend was disregarded; and for<lb/> four years the Mosses on the
                    Old Manse never<lb/> refreshed me with their perennial green. It<lb/> may be,
                    however, that all this while the book,<lb/> likewise, was only improving in
                    flavor and<lb/> body. At any rate, it so chanced that this<lb/> long
                    procrastination eventuated in a happy re-<lb/>sult. At breakfast the other day,
                    a mountain<lb/> girl, a cousin of mine, who for the last two<lb/> weeks has
                    every morning helped me to straw-<lb/>berries and raspberries, which, like the
                    roses<lb/> and pearls in the fairy tale, seemed to fall into<lb/> the saucer
                    from those strawberry-beds, her<lb/> cheeks--this delightful creature, this
                    charming<lb/> Cherry says to me-- "I see you spend your<lb/> mornings in the
                    haymow; and yesterday I<lb/> found there 'Dwight's Travels in New En-<lb/>gland.'
                    Now I have something far better than<lb/> that, something more congenial to our
                    summer<lb/> on these hills. Take these raspberries, and<lb/> then I will give
                    you some moss." "Moss!"<lb/> said I. "Yes, and you must take it to the<lb/>
                    barn with you, and good-by to 'Dwight' ".</p>
                <p>With that she left me, and soon returned<lb/> with a volume, verdantly bound,
                    and garnished<lb/> with a curious frontispiece in green; nothing<lb/> less
                    than a fragment of real moss cunningly pressed to a fly-leaf. "Why this," said I<lb/>
                    spilling my raspberries, "this is the 'Mosses<lb/> from an Old Manse.'" "Yes"
                    said cousin<lb/> Cherry, "yes, it is that flowery Hawthorne."<lb/> "Hawthorne
                    and Mosses," said I ,"no more:<lb/> it is morning: it is July in the country:
                    and I</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="4">
                <pb facs="#f003"/>
                <p>am off for the barn."</p>
                <p>Stretched on that new mown clover, the<lb/> hill-side breeze blowing over me
                    through the<lb/> wide barn door, and soothed by the hum of the<lb/> bees in
                    the meadows around, how magically<lb/> stole over me this Mossy Man! And how<lb/>
                    amply, how bountifully, did he redeem that<lb/> delicious promise to his guests
                    in the Old<lb/> Manse, of whom it is written--"Others could<lb/> give them
                    pleasure, or amusement, or instruc-<lb/>tion--these could be picked up
                    anywhere--but<lb/> it was for me to give them rest.<lb/> Rest, in a life of
                    trouble! What better could be done<lb/> for weary and world-worn spirits? What<lb/>
                    better could be done for anybody, who came<lb/> within our magic circle, than
                    to throw the spell<lb/> of a magic spirit over him?" So all that day,<lb/>
                    half-buried in the new clover, I watched this<lb/> Hawthorne's "Assyrian dawn,
                    and Paphian<lb/> sunset and moonrise, from the summit of our Eastern Hill."</p>
                <p>The soft ravishments of the man spun me<lb/> round about in a web of dreams, and
                    when<lb/> the book was closed, when the spell was over,<lb/> this wizard
                    "dismissed me with but misty re-<lb/>miniscences, as if I had been dreaming of
                    him."</p>
                <p>What a wild moonlight of contemplative<lb/> humor bathes that Old Manse!--the
                    rich and<lb/> rare distilment of a spicy and slowly-oozing<lb/> heart. No
                    rollicking rudeness, no gross fun<cb/> fed on fat dinners, and bred in the lees<lb/>
                    of wine,--but a humor so spiritually gentle, so<lb/> high, so deep, and yet</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="5">
                <pb facs="#f004"/>
                <p>so richly relishable, that<lb/> it were hardly inappropriate in an angel. It<lb/>
                    is the very religion of mirth; for nothing so<lb/> human but it may be advanced
                    to that. The<lb/> orchard of the Old Manse seems the visible<lb/> type of the
                    fine mind that has described it.--<lb/> those twisted and contorted old trees,
                    "that<lb/> stretch out their crooked branches, and take such hold of the
                    imagination, that we remem-<lb/>ber them as humorists and odd-fellows."<lb/>
                    And then, as surrounded by these grotesque<lb/> forms, and hushed in the
                    noon-day repose of<lb/> this Hawthorne's spell, how aptly might the<lb/> still
                    fall of his ruddy thoughts into your soul<lb/> be symbolized by "the thump of a
                    great<lb/> apple, in the stillest afternoon, falling without<lb/> a breath of
                    wind, from the mere necessity of<lb/> perfect ripeness!" For no less ripe than<lb/>
                    ruddy are the apples of the thoughts and fancies<lb/> in this sweet Man of
                    Mosses.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="align(center)"> "Buds and Bird-voices"--</hi><lb/> What
                    a delicious thing is that! "Will the<lb/> world ever be so decayed, that Spring
                    may not<lb/> renew its greenness?" And the "Fire-<lb/>Worship." Was ever the
                    hearth so glorified<lb/> into an altar before? The mere title of that<lb/>
                    piece is better than any common work in fifty<lb/> folio volumes. How exquisite
                    is this:-- "Nor<lb/> did it lessen the charm of his soft, familiar<lb/>
                    courtesy and helpfulness, that the mighty<lb/> spirit, were opportunity offered
                    him, would<lb/> run riot through the peaceful house, wrap its<lb/> inmates in
                    his terrible embrace, and leave<lb/> nothing of them save their whitened</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="6">
                <pb facs="#f005"/>
                <p>bones.<lb/> This possibility of mad destruction only made<lb/> his domestic
                    kindness the more beautiful and<lb/> touching. It was so sweet of him, being
                    en-<lb/>dowed with such power, to dwell, day after<lb/> day, and one long,
                    lonesome night after an-<lb/>other, on the dusky hearth, only now and then<lb/>
                    betraying his wild nature, by thrusting his red<lb/> tongue out of the
                    chimney-top! True, he had<lb/> done much mischief in the world, and was<lb/>
                    pretty certain to do more, but his warm heart<lb/> atoned for all. He was
                    kindly to the race of<lb/> man."</p>
                <p>But he has still other apples, not quite so<lb/> ruddy, though full as ripe;--
                    apples, that have<lb/> been left to wither on the tree, after the plea-<lb/>sant
                    autumn gathering is past. The sketch of<lb/> "The Old Apple Dealer" is
                    conceived in the<lb/> subtlest spirit of sadness; he whose "sub-<lb/>dued and
                    nerveless boyhood prefigured his<lb/> abortive prime, which, likewise,
                    contained<lb/> within itself the prophecy and image of his<lb/> lean and
                    torpid age." Such touches as are in<lb/> this piece can not proceed from any
                    common<lb/> heart. They argue such a depth of tender-<lb/>ness, such a
                    boundless sympathy with all<lb/> forms of being, such an omnipresent love, that<lb/>
                    we must needs say that this Hawthorne is<lb/> here almost alone in his
                    generation, --at least,<lb/> in the artistic manifestation of these things.<lb/>
                    Still more. Such touches as these, -- and<lb/> many, very many similar ones,
                    all through his<lb/> chapters--furnish clues, whereby we enter a<lb/></p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="7">
                <pb facs="#f006"/>
                <p>little way into the intricate, profound heart<lb/> where they originated. And we
                    see, that<lb/> suffering, some time or other and in some shape<lb/> or
                    other,-- this only can enable any man to<lb/> depict it in others. All over
                    him, Hawthorne's<lb/> melancholy rests like an Indian Summer,<lb/> which,
                    though bathing a whole country in one<lb/> softness, still reveals the
                    distinctive hue of<lb/> every towering hill, and each far-winding vale.</p>
                <p>But it is the least part of genius that attracts<lb/> admiration. Where
                    Hawthorne is known, he<lb/> seems to be deemed a pleasant writer, with a<lb/>
                    pleasant style, --a sequestered, harmless man,<lb/> from whom any deep and
                    weighty thing would<lb/> hardly be anticipated--a man who means no<lb/>
                    meanings. But there is no man, in whom<lb/> humor and love, like mountain
                    peaks, soar to<lb/> such a rapt height, as to receive the irradiations<lb/> of
                    the upper skies; --there is no man in<lb/> whom humor and love are developed in
                    that<lb/> high form called genius; no such man can<lb/> exist without also
                    possessing, as the indis-<lb/>pensable complement of these, a great, deep<lb/>
                    intellect, which drops down into the universe<lb/> like a plummet. Or, love and
                    humor are only<lb/> the eyes, through which such an intellect<lb/> views this
                    world. The great beauty in such a<lb/> mind is but the product of its strength.<lb/>
                    What, to all readers, can be more charming<lb/> than the piece entitled
                    "Monsieur du Miroir;"<lb/> and to a reader at all capable of fully fathom-<lb/>ing
                    it, what, at the same time, can possess<lb/> more mystical depth of
                    meaning?--yes, there<lb/> he sits, and looks at me,--this "shape of mys-<lb/>tery,"
                    this "identical Monsieur du Miroir."<lb/></p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="8">
                <pb facs="#f007"/>
                <p>"Methinks I should tremble now, were his<lb/> wizard power of gliding through
                    all impedi-<lb/>ments in search of me, to place him suddenly<lb/> before my
                    eyes".</p>
                <p> How profound, nay appalling, is the moral<lb/> evolved by the Earth's
                    Holocaust; where--<lb/>beginning with the hollow follies and affect-<lb/>ations
                    of the world,--all vanities and empty<lb/> theories and forms are, one after
                    another, and<lb/> by an admirably graduated, growing compre-<lb/>hensiveness,
                    thrown into the allegorical fire,<lb/> till, at length, nothing is left but the
                    all-<lb/>engendering heart of man; which remaining<lb/> still unconsumed, the
                    great conflagration is<lb/> nought.</p>
                <p> Of a piece with this, is the "Intelligence<lb/> Office," a wondrous symbolizing
                    of the secret<lb/> workings in men's souls. There are other<lb/> sketches,
                    still more charged with ponderous<lb/> import.</p>
                <p>"The Christmas Banquet," and "The<lb/> Bosom Serpent" would be fine subjects for
                    a<lb/> curious and elaborate analysis, touching the<lb/> conjectural parts of
                    the mind that produced<lb/> them. For spite of all the Indian-summer<lb/>
                    sunlight on the hither side of Hawthorne's<lb/> soul, the other side--like the
                    dark half of the<lb/> physical sphere--is shrouded in a blackness,<lb/> ten
                    times black. But this darkness but gives<lb/> more effect to the ever-moving
                    dawn, that<lb/> forever advances through it, and circumnavi-<lb/>gates his
                    world. Whether Hawthorne has<lb/> simply availed himself of this mystical<lb/>
                    blackness as a means to the wondrous effects he<lb/> makes it to produce in his
                    lights and shades;<lb/> or whether there really lurks in him, perhaps<lb/>
                    unknown to himself, a touch of Puritanic<lb/> gloom,--this, I cannot</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="9">
                <pb facs="#f008"/>
                <p>altogether tell. Cer-<lb/>tain it is, however, that this great power of<lb/>
                    blackness in him derives its force from its ap-<lb/>peals to that Calvinistic
                    sense of Innate De-<lb/>pravity and Original Sin, from whose visita-<lb/>tions,
                    in some shape or other, no deeply think-<lb/>ing mind is always and wholly
                    free. For, in<lb/> certain moods, no man can weigh this world<lb/> without
                    throwing in something, somehow like<lb/> Original Sin, to strike the uneven
                    balance.<lb/> At all events, perhaps no writer has ever<lb/> wielded this
                    terrific thought with greater terror<lb/> than this same harmless Hawthorne.
                    Still<lb/> more: this black conceit pervades him through<cb/> and through. You
                    may be witched by his sun-<lb/>light,-- transported by the bright gildings in<lb/>
                    the skies he builds over you; but there is the<lb/> blackness of darkness
                    beyond; and even his<lb/> bright gildings but fringe and play upon the<lb/>
                    edges of thunder-clouds. In one word, the<lb/> world is mistaken in this
                    Nathaniel Haw-<lb/>thorne. He himself must often have smiled<lb/> at its
                    absurd misconception of him. He is<lb/> immeasurably deeper than the plummet of
                    the<lb/> mere critic. For it is not the brain that can<lb/> test such a man;
                    it is only the heart. You<lb/> cannot come to know greatness by inspecting<lb/>
                    it; there is no glimpse to be caught of it,<lb/> except by intuition; you need
                    not ring it, you<lb/> but touch it, and you find it is gold</p>
                <p> Now it is that blackness in Hawthorne, of<lb/> which I have spoken, that so
                    fixes and fasci-<lb/>nates me. It may be, nevertheless, that it is<lb/> too </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="10">
                <pb facs="#f009"/>
                <p>largely developed in him. Perhaps he<lb/> does not give us a ray of his light
                    for every<lb/> shade of his dark. But however this may be,<lb/> this blackness
                    it is that furnishes the infinite<lb/> obscure of his background,--that back-<lb/>ground,
                    against which Shakspeare plays his<lb/> grandest conceits, the things that have
                    made for<lb/> Shakspeare his loftiest, but most circumscribed<lb/> renown, as
                    the profoundest of thinkers. For<lb/> by philosophers Shakspeare is not adored
                    as the<lb/> great man of tragedy and comedy.-- "Off with<lb/> his head! so
                    much for Buckingham!" This<lb/> sort of rant, interlined by another hand,
                    brings<lb/> down the house,--those mistaken souls, who<lb/> dream of
                    Shakspeare as a mere man of<lb/> Richard-the-Third humps, and Macbeth dag-<lb/>gers.
                    But it is those deep far-away things in<lb/> him; those occasional
                    flashings-forth of the<lb/>intuitive Truth in him; those short, quick probings
                    at the very axis of reality;--these<lb/> are the things that make Shakspeare,
                    Shak-<lb/>speare. Through the mouths of the dark<lb/> characters of Hamlet,
                    Timon, Lear, and Iago,<lb/> he craftily says, or sometimes insinuates the<lb/>
                    things, which we feel to be so terrifically true,<lb/> that it were all but
                    madness for any good man,<lb/> in his own proper character, to utter, or even<lb/>
                    hint of them. Tormented into desperation,<lb/> Lear the frantic King tears off
                    the mask, and<lb/> speaks the same madness of vital truth. But,<lb/> as I
                    before said, it is the least part of genius<lb/> that attracts admiration. And
                    so, </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="11">
                <pb facs="#f010"/>
                <p> much of the<lb/> blind, unbridled admiration that has been heap-<lb/>ed upon
                    Shakspeare, has been lavished upon<lb/> the least part of him. And few of his
                    endless<lb/> commentators and critics seem to have re-<lb/>membered, or even
                    perceived, that the immedi-<lb/>ate products of a great mind are not so great,<lb/>
                    as that undeveloped, and sometimes undeve-<lb/>lopable yet dimly-discernable
                    greatness, to<lb/> which these immediate products are but the in-<lb/>fallible
                    indices. In Shakspeare's tomb lies in-<lb/>finitely more than Shakspeare ever
                    wrote.<lb/> And if I magnify Shakspeare, it is not so<lb/> much for what he
                    did do, as for what he did<lb/> not do, or refrained from doing. For in this<lb/>
                    world of lies, Truth is forced to fly like a<lb/> scared white doe in the
                    woodlands; and only<lb/> by cunning glimpses will she reveal herself, as<lb/>
                    in Shakspeare and other masters of the great<lb/> Art of Telling the
                    Truth,--even though it be<lb/> covertly, and by snatches.</p>
                <p>But if this view of the all-popular Shak-<lb/>speare be seldom taken by his
                    readers, and if<lb/> very few who extol him have ever read him<lb/> deeply,
                    or, perhaps, only have seen him on the<lb/> tricky stage, (which alone made,
                    and is still<lb/> making him his mere mob renown)--if few<lb/> men have time,
                    or patience, or palate, for the<lb/> spiritual truth as it is in that great
                    genius;--<lb/>it is, then, no matter of surprise that in a con-<lb/>temporaneous
                    age, Nathaniel Hawthorne is a<cb/> man as yet almost utterly mistaken among<lb/>
                    men. Here and there, in some quiet arm-<lb/> chair in the noisy town, or some
                    deep nook<lb/> among the noiseless mountains, he may be ap-<lb/>preciated for
                    something of what he is.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="12">
                <pb facs="#f011"/>

                <p>But <lb/>unlike Shakspeare, who was forced to the <lb/>contrary course by
                    circumstances, Hawthorne<lb/> (either from simple disinclination, or else <lb/>from
                    inaptitude) refrains from all the popular-<lb/>izing noise and show of broad
                    farce and <lb/>blood-besmeared tragedy; content with the<lb/> still, rich
                    utterances of a great intellect in re-<lb/>pose, and which sends few thoughts
                    into circu-<lb/>lation, except they be arterialized at his large<lb/> warm
                    lungs, and expanded in his honest heart.</p>
                <p>Nor need you fix upon that blackness in <lb/>him, if it suit you not. Nor,
                    indeed, will all<lb/> readers discern it; for it is, mostly, insinuated<lb/>
                    to those who may best understand it, and ac-<lb/>count for it; it is not
                    obtruded upon every one<lb/> alike.</p>
                <p> Some may start to read of Shakspeare and <lb/>Hawthorne on the same page. They
                    may say, <lb/>that if an illustration were needed, a lesser <lb/>light might
                    have sufficed to elucidate this Haw-<lb/>thorne, this small man of yesterday.
                    But I <lb/>am not willingly one of those who, as touching <lb/>Shakespeare at
                    least, exemplify the maxim of <lb/>Rochefoucault, that "we exalt the reputation <lb/>of
                    some, in order to depress that of others";-<lb/>who, to teach all noble-souled
                    aspirants that <lb/>there is no hope for them, pronounce Shak-<lb/>speare
                    absolutely unapproachable. But Shak-<lb/>speare has been approached. There are
                    minds <lb/>that have gone as far as Shakspeare into the <lb/>universe. And
                    hardly a mortal man, who, at <lb/>some time or other, has not felt as great <lb/>thoughts
                    in him as any you will find in Ham-<lb/>let. We must not inferentially malign
                    man-<lb/>kind</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="13">
                <pb facs="#f012"/>
                <p>for the sake of any one man, whoever he <lb/>may be. This is too cheap a
                    purchase of con-<lb/>tentment for conscious mediocrity to make. <lb/>Besides,
                    this absolute and unconditional adora-<lb/>tion of Shakspeare has grown to be a <lb/>part
                    of our Anglo Saxon superstitions. <lb/>The Thirty-Nine articles are now Forty. <lb/>Intolerance
                    has come to exist in this matter. <lb/>You must believe in Shakspeare's
                    unapproach-<lb/>ability, or quit the country. But what sort of <lb/>a belief
                    is this for an American, a man who is <lb/>bound to carry republican
                    progressiveness into <lb/>Literature as well as into Life? Believe me, <lb/>my
                    friends, that men, not very much inferior <lb/>to Shakspeare, are this day
                    being born on the <lb/>banks of the Ohio. And the day will come<lb/> when you
                    shall say, Who reads a book by an <lb/>Englishman that is a modern? The great<lb/>
                    mistake seems to be, that even with those <lb/>Americans who look forward to
                    the coming of <lb/>a great literary genius among us, they some-<lb/>how fancy
                    he will come in the costume of <lb/>Queen Elizabeth's day, be a writer of
                    dramas <lb/>founded upon old English history or the tales <lb/>of Boccaccio.
                    Whereas, great geniuses are <lb/>parts of the times, they themselves are the <lb/>times,
                    and possess a correspondent coloring. <lb/>It is of a piece with the Jews, who,
                    while their <lb/>Shiloh was meekly walking in their streets,<lb/> were still
                    praying for his magnificent coming; <lb/>looking for him in a chariot, who was
                    already <lb/>among them on an ass. Nor must we forget<lb/> that, in his own
                    life-time, Shakspeare was</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="14">
                <pb facs="#f013"/>
                <p>not <lb/>Shakspeare, but only Master William Shak-<lb/>speare of the shrewd,
                    thriving, business firm <lb/>of Condell, Shakspeare &amp; Co., proprietors of
                    the <lb/>Globe Theatre in London; and by a courtly <lb/>author, of the name of
                    Chettle, was looked at<lb/> as an "upstart crow," beautified "with other <lb/>birds'
                    feathers." For, mark it well, imitation <lb/>is often the first charge brought
                    against real <lb/>originality. Why this is so, there is not space <pb/>to set
                    forth here. You must have plenty of <lb/>sea-room to tell the Truth in;
                    especially <lb/>when it seems to have an aspect of newness, <lb/>as America
                    did in 1492, though it was then <lb/>just as old, and perhaps older than Asia,
                    only <lb/>those sagacious philosophers, the common <lb/>sailors, had never
                    seen it before, swearing it <lb/>was all water and moonshine there.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics align(center)">(To be concluded next week.)</hi>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="15">
                <pb facs="#f014"/>
                <head>HAWTHORNE AND HIS MOSSES.</head>
                <head><hi rend="small-caps align(center)">by a virginian spending july in vermont</hi>
                    .</head>
                <head>[<hi rend="italics">Concluded from the last number.</hi>]</head>
                <p>Now, I do not say that Nathaniel of Salem is <lb/> a greater than William of
                    Avon, or as great.<lb/> But the difference between the two men is by<lb/> no
                    means immeasurable. Not a very great<lb/> deal more, and Nathaniel were verily
                    William.</p>
                <p>This, too, I mean, that if Shakspeare has <lb/>not been equalled, give the world
                    time, and <lb/>he is sure to be surpassed, in one hemisphere or<lb/>the other.
                    Nor will it at all do to say, that the <lb/>world is getting grey and grizzled
                    now, and<lb/> has lost that fresh charm which she wore of <lb/>old, and by
                    virtue of which the great poets of <lb/>past times made themselves what we
                    esteem<lb/> them to be. Not so. The world is as young<lb/> to-day, as when it
                    was created; and this Ver-<lb/>mont morning dew is as wet to my feet, as <lb/>Eden's
                    dew to Adam's. Nor has Nature been<lb/> all over ransacked by our progenitors,
                    so that<lb/> no new charms and mysteries remain for this<lb/> latter
                    generation to find. Far from it. The <lb/>trillionth part has not yet been
                    said; and all<lb/> that has been said, but multiplies the avenues <lb/>to what
                    remains to be said. It is not so much<lb/> paucity as superabundance of
                    material that <lb/>seems to incapacitate modern authors. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="16">
                <pb facs="#f015"/>
                <p> praise <lb/>mediocrity even, in her own children, before <lb/>she praises (for
                    everywhere, merit demands <lb/>acknowledgment from every one) the best<lb/>
                    excellence in the children of any other land. <lb/>Let her own authors, I say,
                    have the pri-<lb/>ority of appreciation. I was much pleased <lb/>with a
                    hot-headed Carolina cousin of mine,<lb/> who once said,--"If there were no
                    other<lb/> American to stand by, in literature, why, then, <lb/>I would stand
                    by Pop Emmons and his "Fre-<lb/>doniad," and till a better epic came along, <lb/>swear
                    it was not very far behind the Iliad." <lb/>Take away the words, and in spirit
                    he was <lb/>sound.</p>
            </div>

            <div n="17" type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f016"/>
                <p>Let America then prize and cherish her <lb/> writers; yea, let her glorify them.
                    They are<lb/> not so many in number as to exhaust her<lb/> good-will. And
                    while she has good kith and<lb/> kin of her own, to take to her bosom, let her<lb/>
                    not lavish her embraces upon the household of<lb/> an alien. For believe it or
                    not, England, after<lb/> all, is, in many things an alien to us. China<lb/>
                    has more bonds of real love for us than she.<lb/> But even were there no strong
                    literary indivi-<lb/>dualities among us, as there are some dozens at<lb/>
                    least, nevertless, let America first <note>[Rest of the paragraph inserted from
                    f015]</note>praise <lb/>mediocrity even, in her own children, before <lb/>she
                    praises (for everywhere, merit demands <lb/>acknowledgment from every one) the
                    best<lb/> excellence in the children of any other land. <lb/>Let her own
                    authors, I say, have the pri-<lb/>ority of appreciation. I was much pleased <lb/>with
                    a hot-headed Carolina cousin of mine,<lb/> who once said,--"If there were no
                    other<lb/> American to stand by, in literature, why, then, <lb/>I would stand
                    by Pop Emmons and his "Fre-<lb/>doniad," and till a better epic came along, <lb/>swear
                    it was not very far behind the Iliad." <lb/>Take away the words, and in spirit
                    he was <lb/>sound.</p>
                <p>Not that American genius needs patronage<lb/> in order to expand. For that
                    explosive sort o<lb/>f stuff will expand though screwed up in a <lb/>vice, and
                    burst it, though it were triple steel.<lb/> It is for the nation's sake, and
                    not for her<lb/> authors' sake, that I would have America be<lb/> heedful of
                    the increasing greatness among her<pb/> writers. For how great the shame,<lb/>
                    if other nations should be before her, in crowning her<lb/> heroes of the pen!
                    But this is almost the case <lb/>now. American authors have received more<lb/>
                    just and discriminating praise (however loftily<lb/> and ridiculously</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="18">
                <pb facs="#f017"/>
                <p>given, in certain cases) even <lb/>from some Englishmen, than from their own <lb/>countrymen.
                    There are hardly five critics in<lb/> America; and several of them are asleep.
                    As<lb/> for patronage, it is the American author who <lb/>now patronizes his
                    country, and not his country<lb/> him. And if at times some among them appeal <lb/>to
                    the people for more recognition, it is not <lb/>always with selfish motives,
                    but patriotic ones.</p>
                <p>It is true, that but few of them as yet have <lb/>evinced that decided
                    originality which merits<lb/> great praise. But that graceful writer, who <lb/>perhaps
                    of all Americans has received the most<lb/> plaudits from his own country for
                    his produc-<lb/>tions,--that very popular and amiable writer,<lb/> however
                    good, and self-reliant in many things,<lb/> perhaps owes his chief reputation
                    to the self-<lb/>acknowledged imitation of a foreign model, and <lb/>to the
                    studied avoidance of all topics but<lb/> smooth ones. But it is better to fail
                    in origin-<lb/>ality, than to succeed in imitation. He who <lb/>has never
                    failed somewhere, that man cannot<lb/> be great. Failure is the true test of
                    greatness<lb/>. And if it be said, that continual success is a <lb/>proof that
                    a man wisely knows his powers,--<lb/>it is only to be added, that, in that
                    case, he <lb/>knows them to be small. Let us believe it, <lb/>then, once for
                    all, that there is no hope for us <lb/>in these smooth pleasing writers that
                    know<lb/> their powers. Without malice, but to speak<lb/> the plain fact, they
                    but furnish an appendix <lb/>to Goldsmith, and other English authors. And <lb/>we
                    want no American Goldsmiths; nay, we <lb/>want no American Miltons. </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f018"/>
                <p>It were the vilest <lb/> thing you could say of a true American author, <lb/>
                    that he were an American Tompkins. Call him <lb/>an American and have done, for
                    you cannot say<lb/> a nobler thing of him. But it is not meant <lb/>that all
                    American writers should studiously<lb/>cleave to nationality in their writings;
                    only <lb/> this, no American writer should write like <lb/>an Englishman, or a
                    Frenchman; let him write <lb/>like a man, for then he will be sure to write <lb/>
                    like an American. Let us away with this <lb/>leaven of literary flunkeyism
                    towards England. <lb/>If either must play the flunkey in this thing, <lb/> let
                    England do it, not us. While we are <lb/>rapidly preparing for that political
                    supremacy <lb/>among the nations, which prophetically awaits <lb/>as at the
                    close of the present century, in a <lb/> literary point of view, we are
                    deplorably <lb/> unprepared for it; and we seem studious to <lb/> remain so.
                    Hitherto, reasons might have ex-<lb/>isted why this should be; but no good
                    reason <lb/>exists now. And all that is requisite to <lb/>amendment in this
                    matter, is simply this: that <lb/>while fully acknowledging all excellence
                    every-<lb/>where, we should refrain from unduly lauding <lb/>foreign writers
                    and, at the same time, duly <lb/>recognize the meritorious writers that are our <lb/>own;--those
                    writers who breathe that un-<lb/>shackled, democratic spirit of Christianity in
                    all<lb/> things, which now takes the practical lead in<lb/> this world, though
                    at the same</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="20">
                <pb facs="#f019"/>
                <p>time led by <lb/>ourselves--us Americans. Let us boldly con-<lb/>temn all
                    imitation, though it comes to us <lb/>graceful and fragrant as the morning; and <lb/>foster
                    all originality, <lb/>though, at first, it be crabbed and ugly as our own pine
                    knots. <lb/>And if any of our authors fail, or seem to fail, <lb/>then, in the
                    words of my Carolina cousin, let <lb/>us clap him on the shoulder, and back him <lb/>against
                    all Europe for his second round. The <lb/>truth is, that in one point of view,
                    this matter <lb/>of a national literature has come to such a pass <lb/>with
                    us, that in some sense we must turn bul-<cb/>lies, else the day is lost, or
                    superiority so far <lb/>beyond us, that we can hardly say it will ever <lb/>be
                    ours.</p>
                <p>And now, my countrymen, as an excellent <lb/>author, of your own flesh and
                    blood,--an un-<lb/>imitating, and, perhaps, in his way, an inimi-<lb/>table
                    man--whom better can I commend to <lb/>you, in the first place, than Nathaniel
                    Haw-<lb/>thorne. He is one of the new, and far better <lb/>generation of your
                    writers. The smell of <lb/>your beeches and hemlocks is upon him; your o<lb/>wn
                    broad praries are in his soul; and if you <lb/>travel away inland into his deep
                    and noble <lb/>nature, you will hear the far roar of his <lb/>Niagara. Give
                    not over to future generations <lb/>the glad duty of acknowledging him for what <lb/>he
                    is. Take that joy to your self, in your own <lb/>generation; and so shall he
                    feel those grateful <lb/>impulses in him, that may possibly prompt <lb/>him to
                    the full flower of some still greater <lb/>achievement in your eyes.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="21">
                <pb facs="#f020"/>
                <p>And by confessing <lb/>him, you thereby confess others; you brace <lb/>the
                    whole brotherhood. For genius, all over <lb/>the world, stands hand in hand,
                    and one shock <lb/>of recognition runs the whole circle round.</p>
                <p>In treating of Hawthorne, or rather of Haw-<lb/>thorne in his writings (for I
                    never saw the <lb/>man; and in the chances of a quiet plantation <lb/>life,
                    remote from his haunts, perhaps never <lb/>shall); in treating of his works, I
                    say, I have <lb/>thus far omitted all mention of his "Twice <lb/>Told Tales",
                    and "Scarlet Letter." Both are <lb/>excellent; but full of such manifold,
                    strange <lb/>and diffusive beauties, that time would all but <lb/>fail me, to
                    point the half of them out. But <lb/>there are things in those two books,
                    which, <lb/>had they been written in England a century <lb/>ago, Nathaniel
                    Hawthorne had utterly dis-<lb/>placed many of the bright names we now <lb/>revere
                    on authority. But I am content to <lb/>leave Hawthorne to himself, and to the
                    infalli-<lb/>ble finding of posterity; and however great <lb/>may be the
                    praise I have bestowed upon him, <lb/>I feel, that in so doing, I have more
                    served and <lb/>honored myself, than him. For, at bottom, <lb/>great
                    excellence is praise enough to itself; but <lb/>the feeling of a sincere and
                    appreciative love <lb/>and admiration towards it, this is relieved by <lb/>utterance;
                    and warm, honest praise, ever <lb/>leaves a pleasant flavor in the mouth; and <lb/>it
                    is an honorable thing to confess to what is <lb/>honorable in others.</p>
                <p>But I cannot leave my subject yet. No man <lb/>can read a fine author, and
                    relish him to his <lb/>very bones while he reads, without</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="22">
                <pb facs="#f021"/>
                <p>subse-<lb/>quently fancying to himself some ideal image <lb/>of the man and his
                    mind. And if you rightly <lb/>look for it, you will almost always find that <lb/>the
                    author himself has somewhere furnished <lb/>you with his own picture. <lb/>For
                    poets (whether <lb/>in prose or verse), being painters of <lb/>nature, are
                    like their brethren of the pencil, the true <lb/>portrait-painters, who, in the
                    multitude of like-<lb/>nesses to be sketched, do not invariably omit <lb/>their
                    own; and in all high instances, they paint <lb/>them without any vanity, though
                    at times <lb/>with a lurking something, that would take <lb/>several pages to
                    properly define.</p>
                <p>I submit it, then, to those best acquainted <lb/>with the man personally,
                    whether the follow-<lb/>ing is not Nathaniel Hawthorne;--and to him-<lb/>self,
                    whether something involved in it does not <lb/>express the temper of his
                    mind,--that lasting <lb/>temper of all true, candid men--a seeker, not <lb/>a
                    finder yet:-- <lb/>
                </p>
                <p>"A man now entered, in neglected attire, with <lb/>the aspect of a thinker, but
                    somewhat too rough-<lb/>hewn and brawny for a scholar. His face was <lb/>full
                    of sturdy vigor, with some finer and keener <lb/>attribute beneath; though
                    harsh at first, it was <lb/>tempered with the glow of a large, warm heart, <cb/>which
                    had force enough to heat his powerful intel-<lb/>lect through and through. He
                    advanced to the <lb/>Intelligencer, and looked at him with a glance of <lb/>such
                    stern sincerity, that perhaps few secrets were <lb/>beyond its scope.</p>
                <p>"'I seek for Truth,' said he."</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="align(center)">* * * * *</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Twenty-four hours have elapsed since <lb/>writing the foregoing. I have just
                    returned <lb/>from the hay-mow, charged more and more <lb/>with love and
                    admiration of Hawthorne. For <lb/>I have just been gleaning through the Mosses, <lb/>picking
                    up many things here and there that had <lb/>previously escaped me. And I found
                    that but <lb/>to glean after this man, </p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f022"/>
                <p>is better than to be in <lb/>at the harvest of others. To be frank (though, <lb/>perhaps,
                    rather foolish) notwithstanding what <lb/>I wrote yesterday of these Mosses, I
                    had not <lb/>then culled them all; but had, nevertheless, <lb/>been
                    sufficiently sensible of the subtle essence <lb/>in them, as to write as I did.
                    To what infinite <lb/>height of loving wonder and admiration I may <lb/>yet be
                    borne, when by repeatedly banquetting <lb/>on these Mosses, I shall have
                    thoroughly in-<lb/>corporated their whole stuff into my being,--<lb/>that, I
                    can not tell. But already I feel that this Hawthorne <lb/>has dropped germinous
                    seeds into <lb/>my soul. He expands and deepens down, the <lb/>more I
                    contemplate him; and further and <lb/>further, shoots his strong New England
                    roots <lb/>into the hot soil of my Southern soul.</p>
                <p>By careful reference to the "Table of Con-<lb/>tents," I now find, that I have
                    gone through all <lb/>the sketches; but that when I yesterday wrote, <lb/>I
                    had not at all read two particular pieces, to <lb/>which I now desire to call
                    special attention,--<lb/>"A Select Party," and "Young Goodman <lb/>Brown."
                    Here, be it said to all those whom <lb/>this poor fugitive scrawl of mine may
                    tempt <lb/>to the perusal of the "Mosses," that they must <lb/>on no account
                    suffer themselves to be trifled <lb/>with, disappointed, or deceived by the
                    triviality <lb/>of many of the titles to these sketches. For<lb/> in more than
                    one instance, the title utterly be-<lb/>lies the piece. It is as if rustic
                    demijohns con-<lb/>taining the very best and costliest of Faler-<lb/>nian and
                    Tokay, were labelled "Cider,"<lb/> "Perry," and "Elderberry wine." The truth <lb/>seems
                    to be, that like many other geniuses, this <lb/>Man of Mosses takes great
                    delight in hood-<lb/>winking the world,--at least, with respect to <lb/>himself.
                    Personally, I doubt not, that he <lb/>rather prefers to be generally esteemed
                    but a <lb/>so-so sort of author; being willing to</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f023"/>
                <p>reserve <lb/>the thorough and acute appreciation of what he <lb/>is, to that
                    party most qualified to judge--that <lb/>is, to himself. Besides, at the bottom
                    of their <lb/>natures, men like Hawthorne, in many things, <lb/>deem the
                    plaudits of the public such strong <lb/>presumptive evidence of mediocrity in
                    the ob-<lb/>ject of them, that it would in some degree ren-<lb/>der them
                    doubtful of their own powers, did <lb/>they hear much and vociferous braying
                    con-<lb/>cerning them in the public pastures. True, I <lb/>have been braying
                    myself (if you please to be <lb/>witty enough, to have it so), but then I claim <lb/>to
                    be the first that has so brayed in this parti-<lb/>cular matter; and therefore,
                    while pleading <lb/>guilty to the charge still claim all the merit <lb/>due to
                    originality.</p>
                <p>But with whatever motive, playful or pro-<lb/>found, Nathaniel Hawthorne has
                    chosen to en-<lb/>title his pieces in the manner he has, it is cer-<lb/>tain,
                    that some of them are directly calculated <lb/>to deceive-- egregiously
                    deceive, the superfi-<lb/>cial skimmer of pages. To be downright and <lb/>candid
                    once more, let me cheerfully say, that <lb/>two of these titles did dolefully
                    dupe no less <lb/>an eager-eyed reader than myself; and that, <lb/>too, after
                    I had been impressed with a sense of <lb/>the great depth and breadth of this
                    American <lb/>man. "Who in the name of thunder" (as the <lb/>country- people
                    say in this neighborhood),<lb/> "who in the name of thunder, would antici-<lb/>pate
                    any marvel in a piece entitled 'Young<lb/> Goodman Brown?'" You would of course <lb/>suppose
                    that it was a simple little tale, intend-<lb/>ed as a supplement to "Goody Two
                    Shoes." <lb/>Whereas, it is deep as Dante; nor can you <lb/>finish it, without
                    addressing the author in his <lb/>own words--"It is yours to penetrate, in
                    every <lb/>bosom, the deep mystery of sin". And with<lb/></p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f024"/>
                <p>Young Goodman, too, in allegorical pursuit of <lb/>his Puritan wife, you cry out
                    in your anguish:</p>
                <p>"'Faith !' shouted Goodman Brown, in a voice <lb/>of agony and desperation; and
                    the echoes of the <lb/>forest mocked him, crying-- 'Faith! Faith!' as if <lb/>bewildered
                    wretches were seeking her all through <lb/>the wilderness."</p>
                <p>Now this same piece, entitled "Young Good-<lb/>man Brown," is one of the two
                    that I had not <lb/>all read yesterday; and I allude to it now, <lb/>because
                    it is, in itself, such a strong positive<lb/> illustration of that blackness in
                    Hawthorne, <lb/>which I had assumed from the mere occasional <lb/>shadows of
                    it, as revealed in several of the <lb/>other sketches. But had I previously
                    perused <lb/>"Young Goodman Brown," I should have been <lb/>at no pains to
                    draw the conclusion, which I <lb/>came to, at a time when I was ignorant that
                    the <lb/>book contained one such direct and unqualified <lb/>manifestation of
                    it.</p>
                <p>The other piece of the two referred to, is <lb/>entitled "A Select Party,"
                    which, in my first <lb/>simplicity upon originally taking hold of the <lb/>book,
                    I fancied must treat of some pumpkin-<lb/>pie party in old Salem, or some
                    chowder-<lb/>party on Cape Cod. Whereas, by all the gods <lb/>of Peedee! it is
                    the sweetest and sublimest <lb/>thing that has been written since Spencer <lb/>wrote.
                    Nay, there is nothing in Spencer that <lb/>surpasses it, perhaps nothing that
                    equals it. <lb/>And the test is this: read any canto in "The <lb/>Faery
                    Queen," and then read "A Select <lb/>Party," and decide which pleases you the
                    most,--<lb/>that is, if you are qualified to judge. Do not <lb/>be frightened
                    at this; for when Spencer was <lb/>alive, he was thought of very much as Haw-<lb/>thorne
                    is now,--was generally accounted just <lb/>such a "gentle" harmless man. It may
                    be, <lb/>that to common eyes, the sublimity of Haw-<lb/>thorne seems lost in
                    his sweetness,--as per-<lb/>haps in this same "Select Party" of his; for <lb/>whom
                    he has builded so august a dome of sun-<lb/>set clouds, and served them on
                    richer plate<lb/> than</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f025"/>
                <p>Belshazzar when he banquetted his lords <lb/>in Babylon.</p>
                <p>But my chief business now, is to point out <lb/>a particular page in this piece,
                    having reference <lb/>to an honored guest, who under the name of <lb/>"The
                    Master Genius" but in the guise "of a <lb/>young man of poor attire, with no
                    insignia of <lb/>rank or acknowledged eminence," is intro-<lb/>duced to the
                    ,an of Fancy, who is the giver <lb/>of the feast. Now the page having reference <lb/>to
                    this "Master Genius," so happily expresses <lb/>much of what I yesterday wrote,
                    touching the <lb/>coming of the literary Shiloh of America, <lb/>that I cannot
                    but be charmed by the coincidence; <lb/>especially, when it shows such a parity
                    of ideas, <lb/>at least in this one point, between a man like <lb/>Hawthorne
                    and a man like me.</p>
                <p>And here, let me throw out another conceit <lb/>of mine touching this American
                    Shiloh, or <lb/>"Master Genius," as Hawthorne calls him. <lb/>May it not be,
                    that this commanding mind has <lb/>not been, is not, and never will be,
                    individually <lb/>developed in any one man? And would it, <lb/>indeed, appear
                    so unreasonable to suppose, <lb/>that this great fulness and overflowing may <lb/>be,
                    or may be destined to be, shared by a plu-<lb/>rality of men of genius? Surely,
                    to take the <cb/>very greatest example on record, Shakspeare <lb/>cannot be
                    regarded as in himself the concretion <lb/>of all the genius of his time; nor
                    as so im-<lb/>measurably beyond Marlow, Webster, Ford, <lb/>Beaumont, Jonson,
                    that those great men can <lb/>be said to share none of his power? For <lb/>one,
                    I conceive that there were dramatists in <lb/>Elizabeth's day, between whom and
                    Shak-<lb/>speare the distance was by no means great. <lb/>Let anyone, hitherto
                    little acquainted with <lb/>those neglected old authors, for the first time <lb/>read
                    them thoroughly, or even read Charles Lamb's <lb/>Specimens of them, and he
                    will</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f026"/>
                <p>be <lb/>amazed at the wondrous ability of those Anaks <lb/>of men, and shocked
                    at this renewed example <lb/>of the fact, that Fortune has more to do with <lb/>fame
                    than merit,-- though, without merit, last-<lb/>ing fame there can be none.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, it would argue too ill of my <lb/>country were this maxim to hold
                    good con-<lb/>cerning Nathaniel Hawthorne, a man, who <lb/>already, in some
                    few minds, has shed "such a <lb/>light, as never illuminates the earth save
                    when <lb/>a great heart burns as the household fire of a <lb/>grand
                    intellect."</p>
                <p>The words are his,--in the "Select Party;"<lb/> and they are a magnificent
                    setting to a coinci-<lb/>dent sentiment of my own, but ramblingly ex-<lb/>pressed
                    yesterday, in reference to himself. <lb/>Gainsay it who will, as I now write, I
                    am <lb/>Posterity speaking by proxy--and after times <lb/>will make it more
                    than good, when I declare, <lb/>that the American, who up to the present day, <lb/>has
                    evinced, in literature, the largest brain <lb/>with the largest heart, that man
                    is Nathaniel <lb/>Hawthorne. Moreover, that whatever Na-<lb/>thaniel Hawthorne
                    may hereafter write, "The <lb/>Mosses from an Old Manse" will be ulti-<lb/>mately
                    accounted his master-piece. For there <lb/>is a sure, though a secret sign in
                    some works <lb/>which prove the culmination of the powers <lb/>(only the
                    developable ones, however) that <lb/>produced them. But I am by no means de-<lb/>sirous
                    of the glory of a prophet. I pray <lb/>Heaven that Hawthorne may <hi rend="italics">yet</hi> prove me an <lb/>impostor in this prediction.
                    Especially, as I <lb/>somehow cling to the strange fancy, that, in all <lb/>men,
                    hiddenly reside certain wondrous, occult <lb/>properties--as in some plants and
                    minerals--<lb/>which by some happy but very rare accident <lb/>(as bronze was
                    discovered by the melting of <lb/>the iron and brass in the burning of Corinth) <lb/>may
                    chance to be called forth here on earth; <lb/>not entirely waiting for their
                    better discovery <lb/>in the more congenial, blessed atmosphere of <lb/>
                    heaven.</p>
                <p>Once more--for it is hard to be finite upon <lb/>an infinite subject, and all
                    subjects are infinite.</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f027"/>
                <p>By some people, this entire scrawl of mine may <lb/>be esteemed altogether
                    unnecessary, inasmuch, <lb/>"as years ago" (they may say) "we found out <lb/>the
                    rich and rare stuff in this Hawthorne, <lb/>whom you now parade forth, as if
                    only <hi rend="italics">your-<lb/>self</hi> were the discoverer of this
                    Portuguese dia-<lb/>mond in our literature." But even granting <lb/>all this--
                    and adding to it, the assumption that <lb/>the books of Hawthorne have sold by
                    the five <lb/>thousand,--what does that signify? They <lb/>should be sold by
                    the hundred thousand; and <lb/>read by the million; and admired by every one <lb/>who
                    is capable of admiration.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>