<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
	<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>58 - The Fortitude of the North</title>
			
			
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher></publisher>
			<pubPlace></pubPlace>
			<date></date>
		<authority></authority>
		<availability><p></p></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p></p></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><p><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438002086778-x292rc2rybpdgqfr-9e17385f9e315bae5b1baebe47df0e5e%2F177.jpg"/><ref target="#ref_20957">The Fortitude of the North
under the Disaster of the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/event:29" type="event">Second Manassas</name></ref><note xml:id="ref_20957">Note 3: [Historical] General Robert E. Lee and the Army of Northern Virginia defeated General John Pope’s Union Army of Virginia in the Second Manassas. (Christina Lee)</note>

</p><p>They take no shame for dark defeat
  While prizing yet each victory won,
Who fight for the <ref target="#ref_20954">Right</ref><note xml:id="ref_20954">Note 2: [Critical][Intratextual] This poem, along with the previous poem ”Inscription" focuses on Right and Cause, part of “a constellation of values associated with Law in Melville’s mind” (Shurr 17). (Christina Lee)</note> through all retreat,
  Nor pause until their work is done.
The <ref target="#ref_20946">Cape-of-Storms</ref><note xml:id="ref_20946">Note 1: [Historical] There is disagreement about which Cape “Cape-of-Storms” refers to. Cohen suggests that “Cape-of-Storms” refers to Cape Horn since “[f]or Melville Cape Horn is often a symbol of anguish and trial” and he points to references in Melville’s letters, journal entries and White-Jacket (Cohen 206-207, 280); more recently, however, Monteiro argues that “Cape-of-Storms” refers to Cape of Good Hope, which was originally named Cape of Storms and points to references in Moby-Dick and White-Jacket (Monteiro 55). (Christina Lee)</note> is proof to every throe;
  Vainly against that foreland beat
Wild winds aloft and wilder waves below:
  The black cliffs gleam through rents in sleet
When the livid <ref target="#ref_19272">Antarctic</ref><note xml:id="ref_19272">The area surrounding Antarctica.

[reference, geography]</note> storm-clouds glow.</p></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>