<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
	<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>61 - Inscription for Marye's Heights</title>
			
			
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher></publisher>
			<pubPlace></pubPlace>
			<date></date>
		<authority></authority>
		<availability><p></p></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p></p></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><p><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438002233892-738ljg64cwi5dn29-adb43064d6470d49c290967f02eb363d%2F180.jpg"/><ref target="#ref_21286">Inscription</ref><note xml:id="ref_21286">NOTE: Upon request by Lieutenant Colonel Alexander Bliss, Melville submitted another Fredericksburg “Inscription” for publication in a volume for the benefit of the U.S. Sanitary Commission entitled Autograph Leaves of Our Country’s Authors (1864). Melville later sent a revised version to Bliss but it was too late to be included in the volume (NN Published Poems p. 321 for the revised poem and p. 866-67 for the corresponding note). Both Garner and Cohen suggest that the last stanza of “Chattanooga” was adapted from the “Inscription For the Dead at Fredericksburgh” (646). (Christina Lee)</note>
for Marye&amp;apos;s Heights, Fredericksburg

</p><p>To <ref target="#ref_21284">them</ref><note xml:id="ref_21284">NOTE: “them” refers to the Army of the Potomac led by General Ambrose E. Burnside. While General Lee and his army took the advantageous hilltop position on Marye’s Heights, “to attack, Burnside had to cross the Rappahannock River, drive through the town, and breast a stone wall in front of a sunken road at the base of Marye’s Heights” (Cohen 281). While Lee’s army suffered 5,300 losses, Burnside’s army suffered a staggering 12,600 casualties (“Marye’s Heights” civilwar.org). (Christina Lee).

https://www.civilwar.org/learn/maps/maryes-heights-december-13-1862</note> who crossed the flood
And climbed the hill, with eyes
  Upon the heavenly flag intent,
  And through the deathful tumult went
Even unto death: to them this Stone—
<ref target="#ref_21283">Erect</ref><note xml:id="ref_21283">NOTE: Cohen notes that “the word erect is the principal verb, but it also functions as an adjective modifying Stone and as such contrasts with overthrown” (281). (Christina Lee)</note>, where they were overthrown—
  Of more than victory the monument.</p></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>