<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
	<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>70 - Presentation to the Authorities</title>
			
			
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher></publisher>
			<pubPlace></pubPlace>
			<date></date>
		<authority></authority>
		<availability><p></p></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p></p></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><p><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438002611301-i61ew3tcact0529-b08d08430f95bc95a9a157be86e4a6fa%2F192.jpg"/><ref target="#ref_21207">Presentation</ref><note xml:id="ref_21207">This patriotic flag ceremony is mirrored by the presentation of Melville's poetic testimony. A historical event has not been found that corresponds with Melville's poetic representation.</note> to the <ref target="#ref_21194">Authorities</ref><note xml:id="ref_21194">Who these "Authorities" are is uncertain, though they represent "Country" and are sanctified by the word "altar." Captured Confederate flags were turned over to the War Department. The most immediate reference is to the Audience or readers of Melville's own poem. </note>,
by <ref target="#ref_21204">Privates</ref><note xml:id="ref_21204">The lowest rank in the military, signifying an enlisted or conscripted soldier as compared with an appointed officer. Melville might be punning here because at the end of the public ceremony, and the poem, when they are mustered out, they become real "privates" again.  Union privates were paid $13 per month until after the final raise of 20 June '64, when they got $16. "The Civil War Dictionary" by Mark M. Boatner. https://www.civilwarhome.com/Pay.html</note>, of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:997" type="artwork"><ref target="#ref_21181">Colors captured in Battles</ref><note xml:id="ref_21181">The front page of Harper's Weekly 12 November 1864 featured an illustration of  “General Custer Presenting Captured Battle-Flags at the War Department, Washington, October 23, 1864.” [aArt].  Melville's presentation is by a group of unnamed "Privates" rather than a named General. "There were various incentives for capturing and turning in Confederate flags to government authorities. Within some units the captor of a flag would be eligibile for a thirty-day leave, an award of the Medal of Honor, or both." Charles M. Nusbaum, "The Return of the War Department Captured Flags to the States, 1905-1906," Military Collector &amp; Historian (italics) 60:4 (Winter 2008), 262.
</note></name> ending in the
<ref target="#ref_21174">Surrender of Lee</ref><note xml:id="ref_21174">General Robert E. Lee surrendered to General Ulysses S. Grant at Appomattox Courthouse on April 9, 1865. </note>

</p><p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:999" type="artwork"><ref target="#ref_21202">These</ref><note xml:id="ref_21202">The poem itself enacts a ceremony -- "these," "here" -- suggesting that the poem is a form of flag itself, an alternative "Battle-Piece."</note> flags</name> of armies overthrown—
<ref target="#ref_21209"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:999" type="artwork">Flags fallen</name></ref><note xml:id="ref_21209">The War Department created an inventory in 1887 of 545 Confederate flags that were in its custody at that time. Until the fall of 1867, these flags were "deposited in  vacant attic room of a building on 17th Street in Washington, DC, which housed clerks from the Adjutant General's office."  Charles M. Nusbaum, "The Return of the War Department Captured Flags to the States, 1905-1906," Military Collector &amp; Historian (italics) 60:4 (Winter 2008), 262-3. The largest number of flags noted as taken from any single battle were the 38 taken from Sailor's Creek, VA (17 more than Gettysburg). Nusbaum, 271 [Historical] The two stressed syllables that begin the first two lines of the poem provide a metrical representation of the materiality of the flags being referenced. </note> beneath the sovereign <ref target="#ref_21183">one</ref><note xml:id="ref_21183">Ostensibly the Union Flag of the United States, but unspoken by the vanquished, and undefined by Melville, signified by the jarring of its initial off-rhyme with "overthrown" in the poem's opening couplet.[ [Ambiguity; Poetics, rhyme]</note>
In end foredoomed which closes war;
<ref target="#ref_21184">We</ref><note xml:id="ref_21184">A reference to the "Privates" and the "Captors" who lay down the flags before the "Authoritiies," and then proceed home to their private lives. Melville is assuming the narrative position of the collective common soldier here. </note> here, the captors, lay before
  The <ref target="#ref_21191">altar</ref><note xml:id="ref_21191">The sanctification of the Nation -- "Our Country" -- is connoted here, to with the narrator, speaking on behalf of other "Privates" has been "Revering ever her sacred call."  This religious rhetoric is secluded within the indented non-sequential couplet. [allusion, religious] unclear</note> which of right claims <ref target="#ref_21203">all</ref><note xml:id="ref_21203">The superlative "all" signifies the power and ultimate authority of the State to enlist ("claim") the obeisance of its citizens in its sanctified cause.</note>—
Our Country. And as <ref target="#ref_21201">freely</ref><note xml:id="ref_21201">The freedom in this poem consists not only in enlisting to serve in the war but also here  in the laying down of all fealty to Flags to resume virtuous lives of citizens from after the sacrifice of being soldiers.[Ambiguity]</note> we,
  Revering ever her sacred call,
Could lay our <ref target="#ref_21200">lives</ref><note xml:id="ref_21200">Note the equivalence between the laying down of the lives of the common soldiers and these flags of the enemy rebels. </note> down—though life be
<ref target="#ref_21193">Thrice</ref><note xml:id="ref_21193">What these three dimensions suggest Melville's multiple allegiances -- to the victorious survivors who remember both friends and foes who were killed. [Ambiguity]</note> loved and precious to the sense
Of such as reap the recompense
  Of life <ref target="#ref_21205">imperiled</ref><note xml:id="ref_21205">The triple stress in this word -- repeated at the beginning of the next line -- magnifies the stress and fear experienced by the survivors in war. [Poetics, meter]</note> for <ref target="#ref_21206">just cause</ref><note xml:id="ref_21206">The equal strong stress on both "just" and "cause" strikes the deeper moral stakes of the Civil War. This indented couplet is completed only in the final line, which can be read as expanding this emphasis into five continuously stressed syllables that adds the traumatic sacrifice of the soldiers to such a cause to generate the full fruit of the victory -- that the justice of the cause ultimately consists in the vindication of laws.[Poetics, meter]</note>—
Imperiled, and yet preserved;
While <ref target="#ref_21192">comrades</ref><note xml:id="ref_21192">These "comrades" include both the Union soldiers killed during the war, and the Confederates who died for their cause. [Ambiguity]</note>, whom Duty <ref target="#ref_21187">as strongly nerved</ref><note xml:id="ref_21187">strikes an equivalence between both Union and Confederate soldiers, as does "all as dear" in the next line. [Ambiguity]</note>,
Whose <ref target="#ref_21197">wives </ref><note xml:id="ref_21197">"Wives" and "homes" here connote the realm of the real domestic in contrast to the domestic nation that has just survived its crisis. </note>were <ref target="#ref_21189">all as dea</ref><note xml:id="ref_21189">strikes an equivalence between both Union and Confederate soldiers, as does "as strongly nerved" in the prior line. [Ambiguity]</note>r, <ref target="#ref_21190">lie low</ref><note xml:id="ref_21190">Compare with the the "Foemen at morn, but friends at eve— Fame or country leaWhile "lie low" semantically refers to dead "comrades" at the level of the sentence, on the dimension of rhyme and couplet, it refers also to the laying down of the battle flagsst their care" who also "lie low"  in "Shiloh." [Intratextality]
While "lie low" semantically refers to dead "comrades" at the level of the sentence, on the dimension of rhyme and couplet, it refers also to the laying down of the battle flags, an act that releases the "Privates" from their public roles as soldiers.</note>.
<ref target="#ref_21186">But <ref target="#ref_21208">these flags</ref><note xml:id="ref_21208">Replicates the first two words of the poem, suggesting that the furling of the poem itself to the end of this clause signifies the laying down of all forms of battle flags and martial law as civil order is restored. </note> given, glad we go
  To waiting homes with vindicated <ref target="#ref_21185">laws</ref><note xml:id="ref_21185">Rhymes with "cause" in line 11. This indented couplet is radically split by a quatrain that includes both these survivors and the Union and Confederate dead. Melville suggests the the ultimate "just cause" was "vindicated laws," and not merely the victory of one power. </note>.</ref><note xml:id="ref_21186">The poem ends not with a heroic couplet but rather with a demobilization of the surviving "Privates" after their final duty of ironically laying down the Confederate battle flags they had captured, a fact denoting their own in symbolic submission to the "Authorities." </note></p></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>