<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="reading">
        <body>

            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f000"/>
                <head>Hawthorne &amp; His Mosses,</head>
                <head>By a Virginian Spending July in Vermont</head>
                <p>A papered chamber in a fine<lb/> old farm-house -- a mile from any other
                    dwelling,<lb/> and dipped to the eaves in foliage -- surrounded by<lb/>
                    mountains, old woods, and Indian ponds, -- this, surely, is<lb/> the place to
                    write of Hawthorne. Some charm is in<lb/> this northern air, for love and duty
                    seem both impelling<lb/> to the task. A man of a deep &amp; noble nature has
                    seized<lb/> me in this seclusion. His wild, witch voice rings thro' me;<lb/>
                    or, in softer cadences, I seem to hear it in the songs of<lb/> the hill-side
                    birds, that sing in the larch trees at my<lb/> window.</p>
                <p>Would that all excellent books were foundlings,<lb/> without father or mother,
                    that so it might be, we<lb/> could glorify them, without including their
                    ostensible authors. Nor<lb/> would any true man take exception to this; --
                    least of all,<lb/> he who writes, -- <ref target="note_9f762d8685424b2e8380ea53d69940e4" type="editorial">"When the
                    Artist rises high enough to<lb/> achieve the Beautiful, the symbol by which he
                    makes it<lb/> perceptible to mortal senses becomes of little value in his<lb/>
                    eyes, while his spirit possesses itself in the enjoyment<lb/> of the reality."</ref><note xml:id="note_9f762d8685424b2e8380ea53d69940e4">HM did not mark this passage
                    in his copy of Mosses from an Old Manse. This is the final line from "The Artist
                    of the Beautiful, on which Melville left marginalia on four pages. Melville
                    mistakenly capitalized "artist" and switched tenses in copying the sentence --
                    "When the artist rose enough to achieve the Beautiful, the symbol by which he
                    made it perceptible to mortal senses became of little value in his eyes, while
                    his spirit possessed itself in the enjoyment of the reality" (p. 191 in HM's
                    1846 Wiley &amp; Putnam edition).</note></p>
                <p>But more than this. I know not</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf">
                <p>
                    <pb facs="#f003"/>
                </p>
                <p>am off for the barn".</p>
                <p>
                    <note type="compositorial">Alexander</note>Stretched on that new mown clover, <lb/>
                    the hill-side breeze blowing over me <lb/>
               <app>
                        <rdg wit="ms">thro'</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="lw">through</rdg>
                    </app> the wide barn door,
                    and soothed by the hum of the <lb/> bees in the meadows around, how magically <lb/>
                    stole over me this Mossy Man! And how amply, <lb/> how bountifully, did he
                    redeem that delicious <lb/> promise to his guests in the Old Manse, of whom <lb/>
                    it is written -- "Others could give them pleasure, <lb/> "or amusement, or
                    instruction -- these could be <lb/> "picked up anywhere -- but it was for me to <lb/>
                    "give them rest. Rest, in a life of trouble! What <lb/> "better could be done
                    for weary and <lb/> "world-worn spirits? what better could be done <lb/> "for
                    anybody, who came within our magic <lb/> "circle, than to throw the spell of a
                    magic spirit <lb/> "over him?" -- So all that day, half-buried in the <lb/>
                    new clover , I watched this Hawthorne's <lb/> "Assyrian dawn, and Paphian
                    sunset and moon-<lb/> rise, from the summit of our Eastern Hill."</p>
                <p>The soft ravishments of the man spun me round <lb/> about in a web of dreams,
                    and when the book was <lb/> closed, when the spell was over, this wizard <lb/>
                    "dismissed me with but misty reminiscences, as if <lb/> I had been dreaming of
                    him"</p>
                <p>What a mild moonlight of contemplative <lb/>humor bathes that Old Manse!-- the
                    rich and <lb/> rare distilment of a spicy and slowly-oozing heart.<lb/> No
                    rollicking rudeness, no gross fun fed on fat dinners, <lb/> and bred in the
                    lees of wine,-- but a humor <lb/> so spiritually gentle, so high, so deep, and
                    yet</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="14">
                <pb facs="#f013"/>
                <p>not Shakespeare, but only Master William Shakespeare <lb/> of the shrewd,
                    thriving,<note/> business firm of Condell, Shakespeare &amp; <corr change="#StE" facs="#f013_z007">Co.</corr>, proprietors <lb/> of the Globe
                    Theatre in London; <reg change="metatdata#StE" facs="#f013_z008">&amp; </reg>by
                    a courtly author, <lb/> of the name of Chettle, was hooted at, as an <quote change="#readingNH" facs="#f013_z004 #f013_z005 #f013_z006" source="Shakespeare Volume 1">"upstart <lb/> crow" beautified "with other
                    birds' feathers."</quote>
               <note facs="#f013_z004 #f013_z005 #f013_z006">The quote
                    from <hi rend="italic">Greene's Groats-worth of Witte</hi>, slightly misquoted
                    here, was marked on p. xv of volume I of Meville's <hi rend="italic">Dramatic
                    Works of William Shakespeare</hi>: "for there is an upstart crow, beautified
                    with our feathers, that, with his tiger's heart wrapped in a player's hide,
                    supposes he is as well able to bombast out a blank verse as the best of you...".
                    The NN edition claimed that the <hi rend="italic">Literary World</hi> retained
                    both "errors" in its printing, but in fact "Groats-worth" was entered in the
                    Stationers' Register 'upon the peril of Henry Chettle' on 20 September 1592, two
                    and a half weeks after Greene's death on 3 September. On the page that Melville
                    marked, Chettle is also mentioned as the publisher. As Chettle arranged for the
                    book to be published, some have claimed that he authored the book, so Melville's
                    claim is not quite an error. MEL therefore retains his original wording.</note>For,
                    mark it well, <lb/> imitation is often the first charge brought against real <lb/>
                    originality. Why this is so, there is not space to set forth here. You must <lb/>
                    have plenty of sea-room to tell the <lb/> Truth<note>HM modified "truth" to be
                    upper case</note> in; especially, when it seems to have an aspect <lb/> of
                    newness, as America did in 1492, <reg change="#StE" facs="#f013_z010">tho'</reg>
                    it was then <lb/> just as old, and perhaps older than Asia, only <lb/> those<note/>
                    sagacious philosophers, the common sailors, had never <lb/> seen it before;
                    swearing it was all water and moonshine <lb/> there. (to be concluded next
                    week)<note>Added by Duyckinck...</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>