<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<text>
		<body>
			<p>
				<pb facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002"/>
			</p>
			<p>unpopular merit, that amid the thick stir of other things, the hint of my tasteful friend was disregarded; and for four years the Mosses on the old Manse never refreshed me with their perennial green. <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_delete-but">But</del> It may be, <add facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_add-however">however,</add> that all this while, the book, like wine, was only improving in flavor and body. At any rate, it so chanced that this long procrastination eventuated in a happy result. At breakfast the other day, a mountain girl, a cousin of mine, who for the last two weeks has every morning helped me to strawberries and raspberries,--which, <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_delete-like">like</del> <add facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_add-the">the</add> roses and pearls in the fairy tale, seemed to fall into the saucer from those strawberry-beds her cheeks,--this delightful creature, this charming Cherry says to me-- "I see you spend your mornings in the hay-mow; and yesterday I found there 'Dwight's Travels in New England'. Now I have something far better than that,--something more congenial to our summer on these hills. Take these raspberries, and then I will give you some moss."-- "Moss!" said I.-- "Yes, and you must take it to the barn with you, and good-bye to 'Dwight' ".</p>
			<p>With that she left <add facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_add-me">me,</add> <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_delete-thetable">the table,</del> and soon returned with a volume, verdantly bound, and garnished with a curious frontispiece in green,--nothing less, than a fragment of real moss cunningly pressed to a flyleaf.-- "Why this," said I spilling my raspberries, "this is the 'Mosses from an Old Manse'." "Yes" said <add facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_add-cousinCherry">cousin Cherry</add> <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f002_delete-she">she</del>"yes, it is that flowery Hawthorne."--"Hawthorne and Mosses" said I "no more: it is morning: it is July in the country: and I</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>