<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<text>
		<body>
			<p>
				<pb facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003"/>
			</p>
			<p>am off for the barn".</p>
			<p>Stretched on that new mown clover, <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-with">with</del> the hill-side breeze blowing over me <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-from">from</del> through the wide barn door, and soothed by the hum of the bees in the meadows around, how magically stole over me this Mossy Man! And how amply, how bountifully, did he redeem that delicious promise to his guests in the Old Manse, of whom it is written-- "Others could give them pleasure, <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-and">and</del> <add>or</add> amusement, or instruction--these could be picked up anywhere--but it was for me to give them rest. Rest, in a life of trouble! What better could be done for <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-these">those</del> weary and world-worn spirits? what better could be done for anybody, who came within our magic circle, than to throw the spell of a magic spirit over him,"-- So all that day, <add facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_add-half-">half-</add>buried in the new clover <del facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-ofthehalf">of the half-buried</del>, I watched this Hawthorne's "Assyrian dawn, and Paphian sunset and moonrise, from the summit of our Eastern Hill."</p>
			<p>The soft ravishments of the man spun me round about in a web of dreams, and when the book was dosed, when the spell was over, this wizard "dismissed me with but misty reminiscences, as if I had been dreaming of him."</p>
			<p>What a mild moonlight of contemplative humor bathes that Old Manse!--the rich and rare distilment of a spicy and slowly-oozing heart. No rollicking <add facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_add-rudeness,">rudeness</add>, no gross fun fed on fat dinners, and bred in the lees of wine,--but a humor so spiritually gentle, so high, so deep, and yet</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>