<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>06 - The March into Virginia</title>
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body>
				<div xml:id="the-march-into-virginia">
					<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0030.jpg"/>
					<head type="main"><hi rend="italic">The March into Virginia,</hi></head>
					 <head type="sub-head"><hi rend="italic">Ending in the First Manassas.</hi></head>
					 <head type="sub-head">(<hi rend="smallcaps">July</hi>, 1861.)</head><lb/>
<lg>
<l><hi rend="smallcaps">Did</hi> all the lets and bars appear</l>
<l rend="2em">To every just or larger end,</l>
<l>Whence should come the trust and cheer?</l>
	<l rend="2em">Youth must its ignorant impulse lend—</l>
<l n="5">Age finds place in the rear.</l>
	<l rend="2em">All wars are boyish, and are fought by boys,</l>
<l>The champions and enthusiasts of the state:</l>
	<l rend="2em">Turbid ardors and vain joys</l>
	<l rend="4em">Not barrenly abate—</l>
<l n="10" rend="2em">Stimulants to the power mature,</l>
	<l rend="4em">Preparatives of fate.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Who here forecasteth the event?</l>
<l>What heart but spurns at precedent</l>
<l>And warnings of the wise,</l>
<l n="15">Contemned foreclosures of surprise? <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0031.jpg"/></l>
<l>The banners play, the bugles call,</l>
<l>The air is blue and prodigal.</l>
<l rend="2em">No berrying party, pleasure-wooed,</l>
<l>No picnic party in the May,</l>
<l n="20">Ever went less loth than they</l>
<l rend="2em">Into that leafy neighborhood.</l>
<l>In <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/event:40" type="event">Bacchic</name> glee they file toward Fate,</l>
<l><ref target="#ref_20560"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:310" type="person">Moloch</name>&apos;s uninitiate</ref><note xml:id="ref_20560">Traditionally, Moloch is a Canaanite god whose worshipers engaged in child sacrifice. In Milton's <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, he rules in Pandemonium: "First Moloch, horrid King besmear'd with blood / Of human sacrifice, and parents' tears" (as quoted in Cohen 213).</note>;</l>
<l>Expectancy, and glad surmise</l>
<l>Of battle&apos;s unknown mysteries.</l>
<l n="25">All they feel is this: &apos;tis glory,</l>
<l>A rapture sharp, though transitory,</l>
<l>Yet lasting in belaureled story.</l>
<l>So they gayly go to fight,</l>
<l>Chatting left and laughing right.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
	<l n="30">But some who this blithe mood present,</l>
	<l rend="2em">As on in lightsome files they fare,</l>
<l>Shall die experienced ere three days <ref target="#ref_20685">are</ref><note xml:id="ref_20685">In revisions to this stanza in the bound sheets of <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi> (Copy C), Melville wrote "be for 'are'" in pencil in the right margin as a possible revision of "are spent" to "be spent"; however, he made no clearer determination by actually deleting "are." The NN edition of <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi> does not emend (NN <hi rend="italic">Published Poems</hi> 627), and MEL makes note of the possible revision here and in its side-by-side display of copies A and C. For the page image from Copy C and its additional revision sites, see the revision narrative for the poem's last line.</note> spent—
</l>
	<l rend="2em">Perish, enlightened by the vollied glare;</l>
<l>Or shame survive, and, like to adamant,
</l>
	<l n="35" rend="2em"><ref target="#ref_20684">The throe of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/event:41" type="event">Second Manassas</name> share.</ref><note xml:id="ref_20684">
In the bound sheets copy of <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi> (Copy C), Melville made several revisions to the last line of "The March into Virginia," oscillating between options. The editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Published Poems</hi> offer a revision sequence that begins with Melville's underlining of the last line in pencil and inscribing a question mark in the right margin, with the author presumably indicating a problem area to be resolved. The editors go on to narrate the site's further revisions. MEL offers another revision scenario arguing that the underlining and marginal question mark may have come later, as the indication of a restoration of the original line and of Melville's indecision about which final reading he wanted. In the other revision steps at this revision site, MEL's and NN's revisions sequencings generally agree. The MEL sequencing is that Melville would have first struck through the original, printed line and inscribed beneath it a new line "Manassas' second throe and deadlier share". The line presents metrical problems because it adds a fifth beat to the original tetrameter, and even a sixth depending on how the possessive "Manassas'" is pronounced. At this time, Melville might have thought better of the possessive, struck through the entire penciled line, and underlined the original print line to indicate its restoration. Later, in darker pencil, Melville landed upon a third option: "Thy second shock, Manassas, share." Tinkering, he then struck out "second" and inscribed "after" above it to give "Thy after shock, Manassas, share." Though "after shook" (as in an earthquake) is a new and vibrant imnage, the loss of "second" does not distinguish the second more disastrous battle at Manassas, he might have added the marginal question mark to indicate his indecision about this optional line.
</note> <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v2/battle-pieces-ii-0033.jpg"/></l>
</lg>
				</div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>

<!--
NN Rev Narrative: "Then he explicitly lined through the printed line and penciled, then lined through, 'Manassas' second throe and deadlier share'; then he penciled, below, 'Thy second shock, Manassas, share', and finally he substituted 'after' for 'second'.(627)"
	<ref target="#ref_20981">foreclosures</ref><note xml:id="ref_20981">"Legally the word signifies the extinguishing of a right hat one previously had. (Shurr 310)
	"If Luther's day expand to Darwin's year, Shall that exclude the hope—foreclose the fear?"</note>
-->
