<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>08 - Ball's Bluff</title>
			
			
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="balls-bluff"><pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0036.jpg"/>
				<head><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/event:42" type="event">Ball&apos;s Bluff</name>.</hi><lb/>
                               <hi rend="italic">A Reverie.</hi><lb/>
                           (October, 1861.)<lb/>
                     __________________</head>
<lg>
	<l><hi rend="smallcaps">One</hi> noonday, at my window in the town,</l>
<l rend="2em"><ref target="#ref_20698">I saw a sight</ref><note xml:id="ref_20698">In Parker's biography on Melville, he notes that "Melville put himself out to witness some of the military activities, for Stanwix's letter relates an event of 10 June: 'Papa took me to the cattle Show grounds to see the soldiers drill, but we did not see them'" (2:474).</note>—saddest that eyes can see—</l>
	<l rend="2em"><ref target="#ref_20690">Young soldiers marching lustily</ref><note xml:id="ref_20690">We know that Melville had access to <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi> (Sealts No. 241). He had apparently gifted volume 5 (1861) of <hi rend="italic">Harper's Weekly</hi> to Malcolm (Sealts No. 182). This volume features a picture that would have caught Melville's attention: <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:987">The Seventh Regiment Marching Down Broadway to Embark for the War</ref>. The image of the soldiers marching is often cited in Civil War memoirs. In John Wyeth's 1878 memoir, he recalls the meeting on August 7, 1862, in which he enlisted to fight for the New England Guard: "At the call for members to sign the new roll, there was a general rush, each being anxious to get his name on the list first; between two and three hundred men enlisted. On the same day the battalion paraded the city, with Flagg's band" (5).</note></l>
<l rend="6em">Unto the wars,</l>
	<l><ref target="#ref_20692">With fifes, and flags in mottoed pageantry;</ref><note xml:id="ref_20692"> Memories of the pageantry in the early days of the War can be found in many journals and biographies of Civil War soldiers. In John Williams's <hi rend="italic"> Leaves from a Trooper's Diary</hi>, published in 1869, the author remembers when the "air was alive with the roll of drums, and the flag--now dearer than ever before, flutter in miniature from every window" (8).</note></l>
	<l n="5" rend="4em">While all the porches, walks, and doors</l>
	<l><ref target="#ref_20693">Were rich with ladies cheering royally</ref><note xml:id="ref_20693">In Lewis H. Steiner's diary, he relays his memory of General McClellan riding through Frederick, Maryland, in September, 1862. Steiner writes, "matrons held their babes towards him as their deliverer from the rule of a foreign army, and fair young ladies rushed to meet him on the streets, some even throwing their arms around his horse's neck" (24). Although women played roles in the Civil War that varied from caretaker to combatant, the vision of the woman cheering on the soldiers as they march to or from battle is pervasive. R. R. Hancock, Confederate soldier in the Second Tennessee Cavalry, recalls marching through La Grange, Tennessee, on Thursday, September 4, 1862. He writes, "the good ladies cheered us on our way with sweet music, both vocal and instrumental" (214).</note>.</l>
</lg>

				<lg><l>They moved like Juny morning on the wave,</l>
<l rend="2em">Their hearts were fresh as clover in its prime</l>
<l rend="2em">(It was the breezy summer time),</l>
					<l n="10" rend="6em">Life throbbed so strong,</l>
<l>How should they dream that Death in a rosy clime</l>
<l rend="4em">Would come to thin their shining throng?</l>
<l><ref target="#ref_20699">Youth feels immortal, like the gods sublime</ref>.<note xml:id="ref_20699">At this point in his life, Melville had already learned that the quest for glory is fraught with danger. He was most likely reminded of this lesson in August, 1860, as he sailed around Cape Horn on the <hi rend="italic"> Meteor</hi>and read his copy of George Chapman's translations Homer (Sealts Nos. 277 and 278).</note></l></lg>
				<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0037.jpg"/>
				<lg><l>Weeks passed; and at my window, leaving bed,</l>
					<l n="15" rend="2em">By night I mused, of easeful sleep bereft,</l>
<l rend="2em">On those brave boys (Ah War! thy theft);</l>
<l rend="6em">Some marching feet</l>
<l>Found pause at last by cliffs Potomac cleft;</l>
<l rend="4em">Wakeful I mused, while in the street</l>
<l n="20">Far footfalls died away till none were left.</l>
				</lg>
</div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>