<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>18 - Malvern Hill</title>
			<author>Herman Melville</author>
				<editor>Leslie McAbee</editor>
				<editor>Christopher Ohge</editor>
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="malvern-hill">
				<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0075.jpg"/>
				<head type="main"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/event:18" type="event"><ref target="#ref_21057">Malvern Hill</ref><note xml:id="ref_21057">According to Hennig Cohen, Melville visited Virginia battlefields in April 1864, including Malvern Hill, where he purchased “a souvenir brick made from the clay of Malvern Hill” (Cohen 232).</note></name>.</head>
<head type="sub-head">(July, 1862.)</head>

<lg>
<l><hi rend="smallcaps">Ye</hi> <ref target="#ref_21023">elms</ref><note xml:id="ref_21023">The form of “elm” comes from Old English (OED). Hennig Cohen suggests that a news story from July 7, 1862 published in the Grenada (Appeal), and catalogued in the <hi rend="italic">Rebellion Record</hi> (V, 266), may have been a source for Melville’s reference to elms at Malvern Hill: “‘The house at Malvern Hill is a quaint old structure of the last century, built of red brick and stands on a lofty hill a thousand yards from the James River. . . . A fine grove of ancient elms embowers the lawn in a grateful shade. . . .It seemed a bitter nature on the wickedness of man, this peaceful, serene, harmonious aspect of nature. . . .’" (qtd. in Cohen 231).</note> that wave on <ref target="#ref_21022"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:471" type="place">Malvern Hill</name></ref><note xml:id="ref_21022">In addition to the Civil War battlefield, Malvern Hill was also the site of one of the oldest plantations in Virginia, which burned in 1905. Reportedly, the original 17th-century landowners named the property Malvern Hill after English hills of the same name between Hereford and Worcestershire (Matrana, Marc, Lost Plantations of the South, 2009). Malvern Hill has a notable pre-Civil War military history. The land served as a patriot campsite during the Revolutionary War, hosting at one point the Marquis de Lafayette. It again was the site of a military camp during the war of 1812 (Matrana, Marc, Lost Plantations of the South, 2009). </note></l>
<l rend="2em">In prime of morn and May,</l>
<l>Recall ye how <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:178" type="person">McClellan</name>&apos;s men</l>
<l rend="4em">Here stood at <ref target="#ref_21026">bay</ref><note xml:id="ref_21026">Melville’s word choice evokes three denotations. The foremost definition refers to, according to Melville’s edition of Webster’s dictionary, “[a] state of expectation, watching or looking for; as, to a keep a man at bay” (Webster). A second definition of “bay” is in keeping with the poem's arboreal figurations and references, the elms and and cypress glades, as it refers to a “laurel-tree,” the branches of which were “anciently made” into  “an honorary garland or crown, bestowed as a prize for victory” (<hi rend="italic">Webster</hi>). A third meaning of “bay” refers to “[a]n arm of the sea, extending into the land, not of any definite form, but smaller than a gulf, and larger than a creek” (Webster, An American Dictionary of the English Language, 1846). Melville puns on “bay” to point to General McClellan’s position during the battle. Before and for the duration of the battle, McClellan boarded a gunboat, one of several that shelled Confederate positions (Gabriel, Michael. “Battle of Malvern Hill.” Encyclopedia Virginia).</note>?</l>
<l n="5">While deep within yon forest dim</l>
<l rend="em">Our rigid comrades lay—</l>
<l>Some with <ref target="#ref_21058">the cartridge in their mouth</ref><note xml:id="ref_21058">Hennig Cohen explains this image: “A paper cartridge containing powder and a lead ball was used for some muzzle-loading rifles. The paper was bitten open, the powder emptied into the bore, and the paper rammed in as wadding” (233).</note>,</l>
<l>Others with <ref target="#ref_21059">fixed arms</ref><note xml:id="ref_21059">Melville’s word play evokes the image of aimed guns but also the anatomical arms of soldiers “fixed” in death. Editors the 2009 Northwestern UP and Newberry Library’s (Published Poems) suggest that Melville may have drawn this graphic image from the Richmond Examiner’s description of the dead after the battle, which appeared in the Rebellion Record: “The different postures of the dead always strike a spectator as he passes over the battle-field. One lay on his back, with his arms stretched upward at length” (<hi rend="italic">Rebellion Record</hi>, 5:268, doc. 78) (NN <hi rend="italic">Published Poems</hi>, 639).</note> lifted South—</l>
<l rend="6em">Invoking so</l>
<l n="10">The <ref target="#ref_21025">cypress</ref><note xml:id="ref_21025">Melville’s 1846 edition of Webster’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> identifies the cypress tree as “[t]he emblem of mourning for the dead, cypress branches having been anciently used at funerals” (Webster, <hi rend="italic">An American Dictionary of the English Language</hi>, 1846).</note> glades? Ah wilds of woe!</l>
</lg>

<lg>
<l>The spires of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:441" type="place">Richmond</name>, late beheld</l>
<l rend="2em">Through rifts in musket-haze,</l>
<l>Were closed from view in clouds of dust</l>
<l rend="4em">On leaf-walled ways,</l>
<l n="15">Where streamed our wagons in caravan;</l>
<l rend="2em">And the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/event:22" type="event">Seven Nights and Days</name></l>
<l><pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0076.jpg"/> Of march and fast, retreat and fight,</l>
<l>Pinched our grimed faces to ghastly plight—</l>
<l rend="6em">Does the elm wood</l>
<l n="20">Recall the haggard beards of blood?</l></lg>

<lg>
<l><ref target="#ref_21028">The battle-smoked flag, with stars eclipsed,</ref><note xml:id="ref_21028">Like the dead described in the first stanza, Melville does not specify whether the flag is Confederate or Union, though the speaker appears to identify as a Confederate soldier. The fact that the flag never fell suggests a victorious outcome for the Confederates. The Union Army of the Potomac technically won the battle of Malvern Hill but failed to capture Richmond, Virginia. Thus, the Confederate Army of Northern Virginia could be considered victorious in defending Richmond at the end of the Seven Days Battles.</note></l>
<l rend="2em">We followed (it never fell!)—</l>
<l>In silence husbanded our strength—</l>
<l rend="4em">Received their yell;</l>
<l n="25">Till on this slope we patient turned</l>
<l rend="2em"><ref target="#ref_21056">With cannon ordered well</ref><note xml:id="ref_21056">Both the Federal Army of the Potomac and Lee’s Confederate Army of Virginia exchanged heavy artillery to weaken the opponent’s lines. Once Lee ordered the infantry to pursue 130-foot high Malvern Hill did the Union artillery barrage decide the Union’s victory in battle.</note>;</l>
<l><ref target="#ref_21021">Reverse we proved was not defeat</ref><note xml:id="ref_21021">Melville again creates ambiguity about which army the speaker identifies as "we," even as the speaker appears to identify as Confederate. On the one hand, the Union Army secured a technical victory at the battle of Malvern Hill, but the army retreated to a protected position on the James River after the battle (A Critical Companion to Herman Melville 115). On the other hand, the "Reverse" without "defeat" could also refer to the Confederate's defeat at Malvern Hill but overall success in defending Richmond, Virginia.</note>;</l>
<l>But ah, the sod what thousands meet!—</l>
<l rend="6em">Does Malvern Wood</l>
<l n="30">Bethink itself, and muse and brood?</l>
</lg>

<lg>
<l rend="6em">We elms of Malvern Hill</l>
<l rend="8em">Remember every thing;</l>
<l rend="6em">But sap the twig will fill:</l>
	<l rend="6em"><ref target="#ref_21060"><ref target="#ref_21019">Wag</ref><note xml:id="ref_21019">According to Melville’s 1846 Webster’s Dictionary, “wag” in verb form is defined as “1. [t]o be quick in ludicrous motion; to stir. 2. To go; to depart; to pack off. 3. To be moved one way and the other” (Webster, An American Dictionary of the English Language, 1846). According to the Oxford English Dictionary, the verb form of “wag” is from the “Middle English wagge-n, root of Old English wagian … to oscillate, shake."</note> the world how it will</ref><note xml:id="ref_21060">Hennig Cohen lists the possible sources for this phrase: “Cf. Shakespeare, (As You Like It), II, vii. 23: “‘ . . . Thus we may see,’ quoth he, ‘how the world wags . . .’” Also cf. the uncollected poem located by H. P. Vincent, “In a Nutshell” (line 4): 'Wag the world how it may.' The phrase is proverbial (Tilley W879)” (Cohen 233).</note>,</l>
<l n="35" rend="8em">Leaves must be green in Spring. <!--  <note xml:id="ref_21020">Ronald Giles reads the final stanza, in which the elms speak, as the trees' “rebuke” of human kind “for attempting to coerce an unnatural compassion,” of which the elms are not capable ("Malvern Hill," Explicator, 1987). Aaron Kramer places “Malvern Hill” in a constellation with other Battle-Pieces that address the theme of “nature’s uninterested continuity after a human catastrophe. He cites “Shiloh,” “The Stone Fleet,” “A Requiem for Soldiers Lost in Ocean Transports,” and “On a Natural Monument in a Field of Georgia” (Kramer, Melville’s Poetry: Toward the Enlarged Heart, 28).</note> --></l>
</lg>
</div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>