<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>25 - The House-Top</title>
			
			
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><div xmlns="" id="25--the-house-top"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1437998951724-uhgs89j5iea02j4i-72807660b141ebbd831013e0b7767599%2F96.jpg"/><ref target="#ref_21008">The House-Top</ref><note xml:id="ref_21008">Refers to the New York Draft Riots on 11 July, 1863. [Allusion, Historical] </note>. 

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">A Night Piece. 

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">(July, 1863.)

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">––––––––––––––

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">No sleep. The sultriness pervades the air
And binds the brain—a dense oppression, such
As tawny <ref target="#ref_21009">tigers</ref><note xml:id="ref_21009">"And down the dunes a thousand guns lie couched/ Unseen beside the flood/ Like tigers in some Orient jungle crouched,/ That wait and watch for blood." Henry Timrod, "Charleston," Charlestown, Mercury (13 December 1862) [Intertextuality];
"...beholding the tranquil beauty and brilliancy of the ocean's skin, one forgets the tiger heart that pants beneath" [Intratexuality, Moby-Dick]  (Cohen, 239) </note> feel in matted shades,
Vexing their blood and making apt for ravage.
Beneath the stars the roofy desert spreads
Vacant as <ref target="#ref_21010">Libya</ref><note xml:id="ref_21010">Shakespeare, Troilus and Cressida, I, iii, 327-8 [Allusion/Source, Literary] (Cohen 239)</note>. All is hushed near by.
Yet fitfully from far breaks a mixed surf
Of muffled sound, the Atheist roar of riot.
Yonder, where parching <ref target="#ref_21011">Sirius</ref><note xml:id="ref_21011">The Dog Star, or Canis Major, is the brightest star. [Allusion, Astronomical]; "From July 3 to August 11, according to tradition, Sirius rises with the sun, increasing its heat (known as 'Dog Days') (Cohen 240} from Greek word seiros "hot, scorching" [Etymology] </note> set in drought,
Balefully glares red Arson—there—and there.
The Town is taken by its rats—ship-rats
And rats of the wharves. All civil charms
And priestly spells which late held hearts in awe—
Fear-bound, subjected to a better sway
Than sway of self; these like a dream dissolve,
And man rebounds whole æons back in nature.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1437998956005-5m3fc6z3v1tnjyvi-72807660b141ebbd831013e0b7767599%2F97.jpg"/>Hail to the low dull rumble, dull and dead,
And ponderous drag that <ref target="#ref_21007">shakes</ref><note xml:id="ref_21007">Melville changes his word to "jars" in Houghton Copy C, p. 87. [Variant] Shurr notes how the lines in this second part "become heavy with a plodding and jarring alliteration." (39) [Poetics]</note> the wall.
Wise Draco comes, deep in the midnight roll
Of black artillery; he comes, though late;
<ref target="#ref_21012">In code corroborating Calvin&apos;s creed</ref><note xml:id="ref_21012">"The poem is alliterative to and extent unusual even for Melville. Alliteration is used to give the unity elsewhere provided by rhyme...in a section of the poem where alliteration is relatively sparse. (Cohen 241) [Poetics] </note>
And cynic tyrannies of honest kings;
He comes, nor parlies; and the Town, redeemed,
Gives thanks devout; nor, being thankful, heeds
The grimy slur on the Republic&apos;s faith implied,
Which holds that Man is naturally good,
And—more—is <ref target="#ref_21013">Nature&apos;s Roman, never to be scourged</ref><note xml:id="ref_21013">Acts 16:37-38 and 22:25-29 relate how Paul invoked his rht as a Roman citiczen to exemption from scourging. {Allusion, Biblical]; "Is ti lawful for you to scourge a man that is Roman? asks the intrepid Apostle, well knowing, as a Roman citizen, that it was not. And now, eighteen hundred years later, is it lawful to you, my countrymen, to scourge a man who is an American? [Intratextuality, Redburn, Chap. 34] (Cohen, 241) </note>.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>