<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>38 - The March to the Sea</title>
			
			
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><div xmlns="" id="38--the-march-to-the-sea"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001031868-dnzx8rhm9cprdx6r-fe88944bf0831b74cc15da93e489dfef%2F138.jpg"/><ref target="#ref_19216">The March to the Sea</ref><note xml:id="ref_19216">"March to the Sea" was published in Harper’s New Monthly Magazine 32 (February 1866), 366-7, one of four other poems in Battle-Pieces to be previously published in that journal anonymously." [Intratextuality] “The March to the Sea” was one of five Battle-Pieces poems published in Harper’s New Monthly Magazine. The other Battle-Pieces poems featured in Harper’s included “The Cumberland,” “Phillip,” “Chattanooga,” and “Gettysburg” (Robertson-Lorant 486).[variation]
[Critical] [Intertextuality] Hennig Cohen notes that Melville owned a copy of Major George Ward Nichols’ The Story of the Great March, which saw 20 printings before Melville published “The March to the Sea” in Harper’s Weekly. 
[Critical] Frank L. Day argues that Melville drew details for the poem from Brevet Major George Ward Nichols’s The Story of the Great March. One piece of evidence for his theory is the poem’s title, as “The March to the Sea” is the title of the first of three sections in Nichols’s book. 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>
(December, 1864)

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Not <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:484" type="place">Kenesaw</name> high-arching,
  Nor <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:485" type="place">Allatoona</name>&apos;s glen—
Though there the graves lie parching—
  Stayed <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:138" type="person">Sherman</name>&apos;s miles of men;
From charred <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:486" type="place">Atlanta</name> marching
  They launched the sword again.
        <ref target="#ref_21123">The columns streamed like rivers</ref><note xml:id="ref_21123">THE COLUMNS STREAMED LIKE RIVERS [Allusion—military] For the march from Atlanta to Savannah, Sherman split his infantry in two. Because cavalry protected each of the infantry lines, the Union soldiers formed four parallel columns (“Scorched Earth,” www.civilwar.org).
Leslie McAbee</note>
          Which in their course agree,
        And they streamed until their flashing
          Met the flashing of the sea:
            It was glorious glad marching,
            That marching to the sea.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><ref target="#ref_21136">They brushed the foe before them
  (Shall gnats impede the bull?)</ref><note xml:id="ref_21136">THEY BRUSHED THE FOE...IMPEDE THE BULL [Allusion—historical—military] Sherman’s troops were in greater numbers and better supply than Confederate forces that attempted to rout the Federals on the march. Even the substantive Confederate force, Joseph Wheeler’s cavalry, hardly posed a threat to Sherman’s men. One small Confederate militia under the command of Brig. General Pleasant J. Phillips engaged Sherman’s rear guard near Griswoldville, GA on November 22. The Confederates were decimated in the skirmish; Union soldiers discovered afterward that Phillips’s troops were primarily young boys and elderly men (“Scorched Earth,” www.civilwar.org). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>;
<ref target="#ref_21124">Their own good bridges bore them</ref><note xml:id="ref_21124">[Allusion—military] Sherman’s troops carried pontoon trains for the many river crossings between Atlanta and Savannah (Rhodes, James. “Sherman’s March to the Sea.” The American Historical Review. 6:3, 1901, pp. 466-474).
(Leslie McAbee)</note>
  Over swamps or torrents full,
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001053636-orqzahe85df8byb9-fe88944bf0831b74cc15da93e489dfef%2F142.jpg"/><ref target="#ref_21155">For behind they left a wailing,
  A terror and a <ref target="#ref_21125">ban</ref><note xml:id="ref_21125">BAN [Denotation] In this context, “ban” likely evokes two definitions that appear in Melville’s 1846 Webster’s dictionary: 1. “Curse; excommunication; anathema.” 2. “In military affairs, a proclamation by beat of drum, requiring a strict observance of discipline, either for declaring a new officer, or for punishing an offender."
(Leslie McAbee)</note>,
And blazing cinders sailing,
  And houseless households <ref target="#ref_21121">wan</ref><note xml:id="ref_21121">WAN [Denotation] Melville’s 1846 edition of Webster’s dictionary defines “wan” as “pale” or a “sickly hue.”
(Leslie McAbee)</note>,
Wide zones of counties <ref target="#ref_21126">paling</ref><note xml:id="ref_21126">PALING [Denotation] “Pale” as a verb form means “[t]o inclose with pales or stakes” (Webster. An American Dictionary of the English Language, 1846).
(Leslie McAbee)</note>,
  And towns where maniacs ran.</ref><note xml:id="ref_21155">FOR BEHIND...MANIACS RAN [Allusion—military] William T. Sherman’s Special Field Orders, No. 120, indicates: “In districts and neighborhoods where the army is unmolested, no destruction of such property should be permitted; but should guerrillas or bushwhackers molest our march, or should the inhabitants burn bridges, obstruct roads, or other-wise manifest local hostility, then army commanders should order and enforce a devastation more or less relentless, according to the measure of such hostility” (The War of the Rebellion, 713).
(Leslie McAbee)</note><ref target="#ref_21125">ban</ref><note xml:id="ref_21125">BAN [Denotation] In this context, “ban” likely evokes two definitions that appear in Melville’s 1846 Webster’s dictionary: 1. “Curse; excommunication; anathema.” 2. “In military affairs, a proclamation by beat of drum, requiring a strict observance of discipline, either for declaring a new officer, or for punishing an offender."
(Leslie McAbee)</note>,
And blazing cinders sailing,
  And houseless households <ref target="#ref_21121">wan</ref><note xml:id="ref_21121">WAN [Denotation] Melville’s 1846 edition of Webster’s dictionary defines “wan” as “pale” or a “sickly hue.”
(Leslie McAbee)</note>,
Wide zones of counties paling,
  And towns where maniacs ran.
        <ref target="#ref_21156">Was it Treason&apos;s retribution—
          <ref target="#ref_21159">Necessity the plea</ref><note xml:id="ref_21159">NECESSITY THE PLEA [Critical] [Intertextuality] Hennig Cohen cites this line as reference to Paradise Lost, IV, 393-94: “So spake the Fiend, and with necessity, / The Tyrant’s plea, excused his devilish deeds.” Cohen reads this Miltonic allusion as evidence that Melville was skeptical of claims of “military necessity” for William T. Sherman’s scorched earth campaign in Georgia, South Carolina, and North Carolina (260). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>?</ref><note xml:id="ref_21156">
[Critical] [Variant] Hennig Cohen notes that the Harper’s publication of “The March to the Sea” reads: “It was Treason’s retribution / (Necessity the plea),” but Melville’s personal copy rewrites the lines as “Was the havoc, retribution? / But howsoever it be, . . .” Cohen interprets Melville’s editing of these lines as evidence of “a progressive softening in Melville’s attitude toward the South” (260). [Allusion—military] Sherman defends in his report what has been labeled his “total warfare” tactics: "This may be a hard species of warfare, but it brings the sad realities of war home to those to who have been directly or indirectly instrumental in involving us in its attendant calamities” (qtd. in appendix to Nichols’s The Story of the Great March, 235).
(Leslie McAbee)</note>
        They will long remember Sherman
          And his streaming columns free—
            They will long remember Sherman
            Marching to the sea.
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001049237-d8xbxqp8nvf2mx6r-fe88944bf0831b74cc15da93e489dfef%2F141.jpg"/><ref target="#ref_21135">The foragers</ref><note xml:id="ref_21135">THE FORAGERS [Allusion—military] In his Special Field Orders, No. 120, Sherman determined “[t]he army will forage liberally on the country during the march” (The War of the Rebellion: A Compilation of the Official Records of the Union and Confederate Armies, Series 1-Vol 39, 713). A selection of soldiers were organized as foragers to search out food and goods from plantations, modest homesteads, and slave cabins alike. These foragers earned the name “bummers” (“Scorched Earth,” www.civilwar.org). 
Leslie McAbee</note> through calm lands
  Swept in tempest gay,
And they breathed the air of balm-lands
  <ref target="#ref_21152">Where rolled savannas lay</ref><note xml:id="ref_21152">SAVANNAS [Allusion—geographical] A reference to Savannah, GA, where Sherman ended his march. 
[Denotation] Melville’s 1846 copy of Webster’s dictionary defines “savanna” as “[a]n extensive, open plain or meadow, or a plain destitute of trees.”
[Intratextuality] In “The Armies of the Wilderness,” Melville refers to the Pampas grasslands of South America, which include the Uruguayan Savanna east of the Parana River: “(Turned adrift into war / Man runs wild on the plain, / Like the jennets let loose / On the Pampas—zebras again.). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>,
<ref target="#ref_21153">And they helped themselves from farm-lands</ref><note xml:id="ref_21153">[Allusion—military] From William T. Sherman’s Special Field Orders, No. 120: “4. The army will forage liberally on the country during the march. To this end, each brigade commander will organize a good and sufficient foraging party, under the command of one or more discreet officers, who will gather, near the route traveled, corn or forage of any kind, meat of any kind, vegetables, corn-meal, or whatever is needed by the command, aiming at all times to keep the wagons at least ten days’ provisions for his command, and three days’ forage. Soldiers must not enter the dwellings of the inhabitants, or commit any trespass; but, during a halt or camp, they may be permitted to gather turnips, potatoes, and other vegetables, and to drive in stock in sight of their camp. To regular foraging-parties must be intrusted the gathering of provisions and forage at any distance from the road traveled” (The War of the Rebellion: A Compilation of the Official Records of the Union and Confederate Armies, 713). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>—
  As who should say them nay?
        <ref target="#ref_21171">The regiments uproarious
          Laughed in Plenty&apos;s glee</ref><note xml:id="ref_21171">THE REGIMENTS...PLENTY'S GLEE [Critical] [Allusion—historical] Vincent notes that Melville’s depiction of the Union soldiers’ enthusiasm for the march could be a reference to William T. Sherman’s observation that “‘[t]here was a 'devil-may-care’ feeling pervading officers and men’” (454). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>;
        And they marched till their broad laughter
          Met the laughter of the sea:
            It was glorious glad marching,
            That marching to the sea.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The grain of endless acres
  Was threshed (as in the East)
By the trampling of the Takers,
  Strong march of man and beast;
<ref target="#ref_21158">The <ref target="#ref_21137">flails</ref><note xml:id="ref_21137">FLAILS [Denotation] Melville’s 1846 Webster’s dictionary defines “flail” as “[a]n instrument for threshing or beating corn from the ear.” 
(Leslie McAbee)</note> of those earth-shakers
  Left a famine where they ceased.</ref><note xml:id="ref_21158">THE FLAILS...FAMINE WHERE THEY CEASED [Critical] [Allusion—biblical] Hennig Cohen cites these two lines as a possible reference to Matthew 24:7: “For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom: and there shall be famines and pestilences, and earthquakes, in divers places” (KJV).
(Leslie McAbee)</note>
        <ref target="#ref_21154">The arsenals were yielded;
          The sword (that was to be),
        Arrested in the forging,
          Rued that marching to the sea</ref><note xml:id="ref_21154">THE ARSENALS...TO THE SEA [Allusion—military] A reference to the large-scale industrial and infrastructural destruction during the campaign, which great hindered the Southern war effort. From Sherman’s report: “I estimate the damage done to the State of Georgia and its military resources at one hundred millions of dollars; at least twenty millions of which has inured to our advantage, and the remainder is simple waste and destruction. This may be a hard species of warfare, but it brings the sad realities of war home to those to who have been directly or indirectly instrumental in involving us in its attendant calamities” (qtd. in appendix to Nichols’s The Story of the Great March, 235).</note>:
            It was glorious glad marching,
            But ah, the stern decree!

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001044698-2ozhzdwwil1h5mi-fe88944bf0831b74cc15da93e489dfef%2F140.jpg"/>The flocks of all those regions,
  <ref target="#ref_21151">The herds and horses good,
Poured in and swelled the legions,</ref><note xml:id="ref_21151">THE HERDS AND HORSES…THE LEGIONS [Allusion—military] William T. Sherman’s Special Field Orders, No. 120: “6. As for horses, mules, wagons, etc., belonging to the inhabitants, the cavalry and artillery may appropriate freely and without limit; discriminating, however, between the rich, who are usually hostile and the poor and industrious, usually neutral or friendly. Foraging-parties may also take mules or horses, to replace the jaded animals of their trains, or to serve as pack-mules for the regiments or brigades” (652).
Also, in Sherman’s Report of the Georgia Campaign, published in the appendix of George Nichols’s The Story of the Great March, Sherman notes: “We have also consumed the corn and fodder in the region of country thirty miles on either side of a line from Atlanta to Savannah, as also the sweet potatoes, cattle, hogs, sheep, and poultry, and have carried away more than ten thousand horses and mules, as well as a countless number of their slaves” (235). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>
  For they caught the marching mood.
        A volley ahead! They hear it;
          And they hear the repartee:
        Fighting was but frolic
          In that marching to the sea:
            It was glorious glad marching,
            A marching bold and free.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">All nature felt their coming,
  The birds like couriers flew,
And the banners brightly blooming
  <ref target="#ref_21150">The slaves by thousands drew,
And they marched beside the drumming,
  And they joined the armies blue.</ref><note xml:id="ref_21150">THE SLAVES ... ARMIES BLUE [Allusion--historical] According to (The War of the Rebellion: A Compilation of the Official Records of the Union and Confederate Armies), around 19,000 slaves abandoned plantations to join Sherman’s march (qtd in Edmund Drago’s “How Sherman’s March Through Georgia Affected the Slaves,” The Georgia Historical Quarterly, 363). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>
        <ref target="#ref_21157">The cocks crowed from the cannon
          (Pets named from <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:149" type="person">Grant</name> and <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:139" type="person">Lee</name>),
        Plumed fighters and campaigners</ref><note xml:id="ref_21157">[Critical] [Intertextuality] Hennig Cohen cites George W. Nichols’s The Story of the Great March as a likely source for Melville’s depiction of roosters as pets. Nichols writes: “The favorite pet of the camp, however, is the hero of the barn-yard. There is not a regiment nor a company, not a teamster nor a negro at headquarters, nor an orderly, but has a ‘rooster’ of one kind or another. When the column is moving, these haughty game-cocks are seen mounted upon the breech of a cannon, tied to the pack-saddle of a mule, among pots and pans, or carried lovingly in the arms of a mounted orderly; crowing with all his might from the interior of a wagon, or making the woods re-echo from his triumphant notes . . . The game-cocks which have come out of repeated conflicts victorious are honored with such names as ‘Bill Sherman,’ ‘Johnny Logan,’ etc.; while the defeated and bepecked victim is saluted with derisive appellations, such as ‘Jeff Davis,’ ‘Beauregard,’ or ‘Bob Lee’” (46).
(Leslie McAbee)</note><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:149" type="person">Grant</name> and Lee),
        Plumed fighters and campaigners
          In the marching to the sea:
            It was glorious glad marching,
            For every man was free.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001040044-1ldgfcvyddj3v7vi-fe88944bf0831b74cc15da93e489dfef%2F139.jpg"/>And the grand pines waving o&apos;er them
  Bowed to axes keen and cool.
        The columns grooved their channels.
          Enforced their own decree,
        And their power met nothing larger
          Until it met the sea:
            It was glorious glad marching,
            A marching glad and free.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><ref target="#ref_21148">Kilpatrick</ref><note xml:id="ref_21148">[Allusion—historical—military] When Joseph Wheeler’s Confederate cavalry attempted to block Sherman’s march into Milledgeville, then the capital of Georgia, Brig. General Hugh Judson Kilpatrick’s Union cavalry repelled the Confederates’ attack (“Scorched Earth,” www.civilwar.org). 
(Leslie McAbee)</note>&apos;s snare of riders
  In zigzags mazed the land,
Perplexed the pale Southsiders
  With <ref target="#ref_21149">feints</ref><note xml:id="ref_21149">FEINTS [Denotation] Melville’s 1846 Webster’s dictionary defines “feint” as “1. An assumed or false appearance; a pretense of doing something not intended to be done. 2. A mock attack” (An American dictionary of the English Language).
(Leslie McAbee)</note> on every hand;
Vague menace awed the hiders
  In forts beyond command.
        To Sherman&apos;s shifting problem
          No foeman knew the key;
        But onward went the marching
          Unpausing to the sea:
            It was glorious glad marching,
            The swinging step was free.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The flankers ranged like pigeons
  In clouds through field or wood;
</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>