<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>55 - America</title>
			
			
					
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
		
			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>			
		<text>
			<body><div xmlns="" id="55--america"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001944253-4dbv9t56eev78pvi-d223b2b208f3047f4086d3fd350e5d52%2F170.jpg"/>America

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Where the wings of a sunny Dome expand
I saw a Banner in gladsome air—
Starry, like <ref target="#ref_20973">Berenice&apos;s Hair</ref><note xml:id="ref_20973">Coma Berenices is the only modern constellation named  for a historical figure: Queen Berenice II of Egypt, wife of King Ptolemy Eugeretes (c. 248 B.C.E.) who sacrificed her long hair as a votive offering to Venus. [Allusion, astronomical]
"Bringer of Victory," from pherein "to bring" and nike "victory" [etymology] </note>—
Afloat in broadened bravery there;
With undulating long-drawn flow,
As rolled Brazilian billows go
Voluminously o&apos;er the Line.
The Land reposed in peace below;
  The children in their glee
Were folded to the exulting heart
  Of young Maternity.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">II.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Later, and it streamed in fight
  When tempest mingled with the fray,
And over the spear-point of the shaft
  I saw the ambiguous lightning play.
Valor with Valor strove, and died:
Fierce was Despair, and cruel was Pride;
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001961568-fs4dakaekuqe61or-d223b2b208f3047f4086d3fd350e5d52%2F172.jpg"/>A clear calm look. It spake of pain,
But such as purifies from stain—
Sharp pangs that never come again—
  And triumph repressed by knowledge meet,
Power dedicate, and hope grown wise,
  And youth matured for age&apos;s seat—
Law on her brow and empire in her eyes.
  So she, with graver air and lifted flag;
While the shadow, chased by light,
Fled along the far-drawn height,
  And left her on the crag.
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1438001957314-3v9pzvfyu89cc8fr-d223b2b208f3047f4086d3fd350e5d52%2F171.jpg"/>And the lorn Mother speechless stood,
Pale at the fury of her brood.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">III.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Yet later, and the silk did wind
    Her fair cold form;
Little availed the shining shroud,
  Though ruddy in hue, to cheer or warm.
A watcher looked upon her low, and said—
She sleeps, but sleeps, she is not dead.
  But in that sleep contortion showed
The terror of the vision there—
  A silent vision unavowed,
<ref target="#ref_20975">Revealing earth&apos;s foundation bare,
  And <ref target="#ref_20977">Gorgon</ref><note xml:id="ref_20977">A female creature from Greek mythology, such as Medusa, sometimes with hair made of snakes, and with a face so horrible it turned those who looked at her to stone. [Allusion, mythologocal] [Source, Hesiod's Theogony]
In the Aeneid, Gorgons lived in the entrance to the Underworld. [Source: Homer's The Aeneid];
from ancient Greek word gorgos "dreadful." [Etymology]</note> in her hidden place</ref><note xml:id="ref_20975">"The doctrine in this passage, key to Melville's thought throughout his writing career, is that the final divinity is to be found  below rather than above; that this reality is evil, not good; and that knowledge of this god causes not the peace that surpasses all understanding , but madness." (Shurr, 22) [Criticism]
Herman Melville
“The sea had jeeringly kept his finite body up, but drowned the infinite of his soul. Not drowned entirely, though. Rather carried down alive to wondrous depths, where strange shapes of the unwarped primal world glided to and fro before his passive eyes; and the miser-merman, Wisdom, revealed his hoarded heaps; and among the joyous, heartless, ever-juvenile eternities, Pip saw the multitudinous, God-omnipresent, coral insects, that out of the firmament of waters heaved the colossal orbs. He saw God’s foot upon the treadle of the loom, and spoke it; and therefore his shipmates called him mad. So man’s insanity is heaven’s sense; and wandering from all mortal reason, man comes at last to that celestial thought, which, to reason, is absurd and frantic; and weal or woe, feels then uncompromised, indifferent as his God.” [Intratextuality, Moby-Dick]</note>.
It was a thing of fear to see
  So foul a dream upon so fair a face,
And the dreamer lying in that starry shroud.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">IV.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But from the trance she sudden broke—
  The trance, or death into promoted life;
At her feet a shivered yoke,
And in her aspect turned to heaven
  No trace of passion or of strife—
</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>