<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>72 - The Scout toward Aldie</title>
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body>
				<div xml:id="the-scout-toward-aldie"><pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0193.jpg"/>
<head type="main"><ref target="#ref_21089"><hi rend="italic">THE SCOUT TOWARD ALDIE.</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_21089">"The longest poem in the book, . . . distinguished in the contents by being printed in capitals and small capitals" (Parker, II 611). Hennig Cohen notes that "separation pages set it off from the memorial verses which precede and from 'Lee in the Capitol' which follows.  In addition to its length it is unusual in its origin and its form.  Melville was not rehashing The Rebellion Record (italics) but was creating from personal experience and from events described to him by soldiers he had met, and he had chosen a genre, the literary ballad, which he had not previously attempted" (287). [biography]  "Aldie is situated in Loudon County, about ten miles south of Leesburg [Virginia], the county seat.  Loudon Valley lies between the Bull Run Mountains on the east and the Blue Ridge on the west" (Cohen, 287).  Aldie is located west of Vienna, Virginia, to which location Melville traveled with his brother Allan to see their cousin, Lieutenant Colonel Henry Gansevoort, commander of the 13th New York Cavalry, in April 1864.  The "scout" in which Melville participated that month moved west from Vienna towards Aldie--a region essentially controlled by the elusive and feared Colonel John S. Mosby and his troops (and aptly nicknamed "Mosby's Confederacy").  [biography] [place] [event] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></head>
<lb/>
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0195.jpg"/>
  <head type="sub-head"><hi rend="italic">The Scout toward Aldie.</hi></head>

<lg>
<l><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> <ref target="#ref_21113">cavalry-camp</ref> lies on the slope
<note xml:id="ref_21113">Stanton Garner notes that the real-life scout toward Aldie was composed of a rather large number of men: "[General] Tyler [sent] out a large scout of five hundred cavalry and infantry led by two brigade commanders" (1982 Melville Society piece, 14).  The group of infantry, Garner notes, was led by Colonel Arthur H. Grimshaw while Colonel Charles Russell Lowell was in charge of the group of cavalry.  [biography] [event] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">Of what was late <ref target="#ref_21114">a vernal hill,</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21114">Stanton Garner notes that when Melville and his brother arrived in camp, "The once-lush hillside had been trampled bare of its grass carpet by the troopers and their horses, and many of the trees in the vicinity had been requisitioned the previous winter to provide wood for the troopers' fires" (10).  [biography] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l>But now like a pavement bare—</l>
<l>An outpost in the perilous <ref target="#ref_21176">wilds</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21176">It is important to note that this line does not rhyme with any of the other lines in this stanza and thus stands as a kind of "outpost" to the rest of the stanza; the line's semantic meaning thus mirrors its formal placement within the stanza. [poetics] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">Which ever are lone and still;</l>
<l rend="4em">But <ref target="#ref_21087">Mosby&apos;s men</ref> are there—
<note xml:id="ref_21087">Colonel John S. Mosby, commander of the 43rd Battalion of Virginia Cavalry, otherwise known as the "Partisan Raiders," the "Partisan Rangers," "Mosby's Rangers," or simply, as denoted here in the poem, "Mosby's Men."  Formed in January 1863, Mosby's group of soldiers became known for their ability to elude Union forces and their constant, unsettling presence in northeastern Virginia.  Mosby's group of men did not formally demobilize until after the war, on April 21, 1865 (NN Published Poems, 668-669; Hennig Cohen, pp. 286-287). "Mosby's Partisan Rangers, . . . and their guerrilla tactics of surprise hit and strategic run kept a disproportionately large force of Federal troops pinned down to the defense of Washington between January 1863 and April 1865."  (NN Published Poems, 669.)  [biography] [name] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">Of Mosby best <ref target="#ref_21118">beware.</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21118">Both Jonathan A. Cook and Joseph Fargnoli observe that the poem's formal qualities are resonant of both the ballad form and rhyme royal.  Cook notes that the poem "follows ballad tradition in some basic aspects of its theme and form, except for its seven-line stanza, technically a heptastich or septet, in iambic tetrameter with a rhyme scheme of a-b-c-d-b-c-c.  The most familiar septet stanza is 'rhyme royal,' which uses iambic pentameter in a rhyme scheme of a-b-a-b-b-c-c.  Rhyme royal had been pioneered by Chaucer in The Parlement of Foules (italics), Troilus and Criseyde (italics), and four Canterbury Tales (italics), and subsequently utilized by a number of poets including Spenser in his Four Hymns (italics) and Shakespeare in The Rape of Lucrece (italics).  Melville's octosyllabic line and restricted rhyme scheme were probably intended to tone down some of the verbal music of rhyme royal while substituting frequent alliteration for reduced end rhyme" (73-74).  Fargnoli offers a similar but slightly different observation on the poem's formal qualities: "The 798-line poem, of 114 septets in a consistent, abcdbcc (italics) rhyme scheme and a prevailingly iambic, octosyllabic line, harks back to similar and related ballads and to such English lyrics and verse romances as Surrey's 'The Seafarer,' Wyatt's 'Resignation' and 'The Lute Obeys,' and Charles Sackville, the Earl of Dorset's 'Song: Written at Sea, in the First Dutch War, 1665, the Night before an Engagement.'  Related forms of sixteenth- and seventeenth-century verse romances, especially complaints, evoked by Melville's poem are those set in the dominant septet style of the rhyme royal, such as Shakespeare's 'The Rape of Lucrece' and Michael Drayton's 'Fame and Fortune.'  Typical of these verse genres, and what 'Scout' shares with them that suggests its descendancy from the archetype or the quest myth, is the story of the tragic downfall of an ambitious or noble character" (335).  [poetics] [source] [allusion] (Karah Mitchell).
</note></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Great trees the troopers felled, and leaned</l>
<l rend="2em">In antlered walls about their tents;</l>
<l n="10" >Strict watch they kept; &apos;twas <hi rend="italic">Hark! and Mark!</hi></l>
<l>Unarmed none cared to stir <ref target="#ref_21177">abroad</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21177">See the above note to line 4. [poetics] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">For berries beyond their forest-fence:</l>
<l rend="4em">As glides in seas the <ref target="#ref_21094">shark</ref>,
<note xml:id="ref_21094">"For other symbolic sharks, see 'Commemorative of a Naval Victory,' . . . lines 26-27" (Cohen, 288).[intratextuality] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">Rides Mosby through green <ref target="#ref_21088">dark</ref>.
<note xml:id="ref_21088">"This couplet attracts particular attention because of initial as well as end rhyme and the break in rhythm due to the length of the sound in green (italics), especially noticeable in relation to the brevity of dark (italics)."  (Cohen, 288) [poetics] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0196.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>All spake of him, but few had seen</l>
<l rend="2em">  Except the maimed ones or the low;</l>
<l>Yet rumor made him every thing—</l>
<l>A farmer—woodman—refugee—</l>
<l rend="2em">The man who crossed the field but now;</l>
<l n="20" rend="4em">A <ref target="#ref_21097">spell</ref> about his life did cling—
<note xml:id="ref_21097">"Like many another writer of the Romantic period, Melville sought to inform his poem with the authority of folk expression.  His setting is a land of enchantment, an 'Eerie land' (line 29).  His characters and situations fit the ballad pattern.  He introduces shape-shifters (lines 18, 700) and haunted houses (line 198); much talk of spells, charms, elves, fairies, and ghosts; and an invisible personage who ravages the countryside, invulnerable to lead bullets but perhaps not to silver ones (line 728)"  (Cohen, 287-288). Several other scholars have noted the fantasy-like qualities of the poem and the significance of these qualities when examining the larger poetic traditions that informed Melville's writing.  See Jonathan Cook, "History, Legend, and Poetic Tradition in Melville's 'The Scout Toward Aldie,'" Joseph Fargnoli's "Archetype and History in Melville's 'The Scout Toward Aldie,'" and Megan Williams' "'Sounding the Wilderness': Representations of the Heroic in Herman Melville's Battle-Pieces and Aspects of the War (italics)."  [critical] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">Who to the ground shall Mosby bring?</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The morning-bugles lonely play,</l>
<l rend="2em">Lonely the evening-bugle calls—</l>
<l>Unanswered voices in the wild;</l>
<l>The settled hush of birds in nest</l>
<l rend="2em">Becharms, and all the wood enthralls:</l>
<l rend="4em">Memory&apos;s self is so beguiled</l>
<l rend="4em">That Mosby seems a <ref target="#ref_21119">satyr&apos;s child</ref>.
<note xml:id="ref_21119">Definition from the OED: "One of a class of woodland gods or demons, in form partly human and partly bestial, supposed to be the companions of Bacchus" (definition 1.a.).  [definition]  For Jonathan Cook, this characterization of Mosby as "a satyr's child" displays yet another way in which Melville's poem utilizes "Spenserian prototypes" (75).  "If popular balladry probably helped Melville conceptualize certain aspects of his narrative poem, Spenser's poetry, an abiding influence on his writing (Moses), aided him as well.  Melville was re-reading his multi-volume edition of Spenser in August 1864, a few months after his return to New York from Washington and Northern Virginia, at which time he may have already begun the narrative poem based on his scouting expedition (Parker 578-579).  Thus it comes as no surprise that The Faerie Queene (italics) apparently contributed to several aspects of setting, theme, and characterization in 'The Scout Toward Aldie.' . . . Mosby is described as a 'satyr's child' because of his close identification with the sylvan setting of the poem . . . .  The 'satyr's child' of Books I, III, and IV of The Faerie Queene (italics) is, of course, Sir Satyrane, the offspring of a satyr and a court lady.  Raised in the woods by his wild father and then polished in the world of his civilized mother, this 'natural' knight becomes a votary and defender of Una after her attempted rape by Sans Loy in Book I, Canto VI.  The implied association in Melville's poem of Mosby with the world of Greek pastoral and Spenser's Sir Satyrane complicates the guerrilla leader's moral identity, but it is ultimately only a trick of the landscape that allows for this transformation" (74-75).  [critical] [source] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>They lived as in the Eerie Land—</l>
<l n="30" rend="2em">The fire-flies showed with fairy gleam;</l>
<l>And yet from pine-tops one might ken</l>
<l>The <ref target="#ref_21102">Capitol dome</ref>—hazy—sublime—
<note xml:id="ref_21102">"The new iron dome of the Capitol building in Washington, D.C., could be seen from 'Mosby's Confederacy' in nearby northern Virginia" (NN Published Poems, 670).  "Aldie is some 30 miles from Washington" (Cohen, 288). Grant Shreve offers an insightful observation about the significance of this physical marker, especially with reference to the Spenserian qualities of the poem: "The figurative shadow cast by the Dome introduces a looming presence upon the scene and disrupts the dreamscape of this American fairyland.  The mythical quality of the Virginian woods is shattered by the 'vision' that the Dome imposes upon the observers below.  In one sense this vision is a literal sight that perverts the physical beauty of the Arcadian scene, but it is also a glance into the future, a vision in the prophetic sense of the physical dominance of the North over the South and of the shadow, beneath which Virginia will hereafter operate" ("Shadows of Reconstruction," 15-16).  [place] [critical] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">A vision breaking on a <ref target="#ref_21120">dream</ref>:
<note xml:id="ref_21120">Noah Webster's 1846 edition of An American Dictionary of the English Language (italics)--which Melville owned--defines "vision" as follows: "1. The act of seeing external objects; actual sight. 2. The faculty of seeing; sight. 3. Something imagined to be seen, though not real; a phantom: a spectre.  --4. In Scripture (italicize), a revelation from God. 5. Something imaginary; the production of fancy. 6. Any thing which is the object of sight" (908).  For its noun form, "dream" has the following definition: "1. The thought or series of thoughts of a person in sleep. --2. In Scripture (italics), dreams (italics) were sometimes impressions on the mind of sleeping persons, made by divine agency. 3. A vain fancy; a wild conceit; an unfounded suspicion" (275).  Melville's phrasing implies a difference between the two nouns, but Webster's definitions do not fully separate the two. [definition] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">So strange it was that Mosby&apos;s men</l>
<l rend="4em">Should dare to prowl where the Dome was <ref target="#ref_21122">seen</ref>.
<note xml:id="ref_21122">The first of a number of ending couplets in the poem that utilizes near rhyme.  [poetics] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0197.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>A <ref target="#ref_21104">scout</ref> toward Aldie broke the spell.—
<note xml:id="ref_21104">"A ride toward (italics) (revision in Melville's copy)."  (Cohen, 288)  [variant] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">The <ref target="#ref_21106">Leader</ref> lies before his tent
<note xml:id="ref_21106">Colonel Charles Russell Lowell (1835-1864), of the 2nd Massachusetts Calvary, and brigade commander of the 13th New York Cavalry during the scout toward Aldie.  A graduate of Harvard College, Lowell was well-regarded during his lifetime, and his death at the Battle of Cedar Creek in October 1864 was widely mourned. [person] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l>Gazing at <ref target="#ref_21145">heaven&apos;s all-cheering lamp</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21145">"Cf. Shakespeare, Romeo and Juliet (italics), I, i, 141: '. . . so soon as the all-cheering sun . . .'" (Cohen, 288).  "Though the phrasing might be taken as formulaic, Hennig Cohen's citation of Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet (italics), . . . seems relevant in a context where the 'Leader' is about to be portrayed as Romeo-like" (NN Poems, 670). [allusion] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l>Through blandness of a morning rare;</l>
<l n="40" rend="2em">His thoughts on bitter-sweets are bent:</l>
<l rend="4em">His sunny <ref target="#ref_21105">bride</ref> is in the camp—
<note xml:id="ref_21105">The wife of Colonel Charles Russell Lowell, Josephine Shaw Lowell, nicknamed "Effy."  "Her father, Francis G. Shaw of Staten Island, had had literary dealings with Herman in connection with the firm of Putnam's, and her brother-in-law, George Washington Curtis, had been one of his editors at Putnam's" (Garner, 11).  Josephine was also the sister of Robert Gould Shaw, commander of the Massachusetts 54th, the first regiment composed of African-Americans during the Civil War, and who was killed along with a number of his men at the Second Battle of Fort Wagner in July 1863.  Garner notes that Josephine would have been in camp and actually greeted the Melvilles during their visit, while several other scholars simply note that Melville would have heard that she had visited the camp before. "The Lowells were a dazzling couple.  Charles was a handsome, brilliant, and fearless officer who, it has been said, might one day have been president of the United States had the War not cut him down.  Effy, barely out of her teens and at this time a month pregnant, was equally impressive: intelligent, witty, educated, athletic, and strong, she still managed to conform to nineteenth-century standards of feminine beauty and grace.  William James, seeing the two together on horseback, thought that 'they looked so young and victorious'" (Garner, 11-12).  [person] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">But <ref target="#ref_21131">Mosby—graves are beds of damp</ref>!
<note xml:id="ref_21131">"The ironical contrast between the bridal bed and the grave is a foreshadowing device" (Cohen, 288).  This becomes evident in a literal sense when one reads through the poem; however, one can also read this foreshadowing as a symbolic one.  In his notes to the poem, Robert Penn Warren includes Edmund Wilson's observations about the poem as a romance between not simply Colonel Lowell and his bride, but also the North and the South: "[Throughout the poem's story] we are made to feel that the colonel has a kind of fatal rendezvous with the sinister ranger [Mosby], that he is drawn to his opponent by a kind of spell that is somehow a good deal more powerful than the attraction which had drawn him to his bride.  . . . [T]he story, though so personal a product of Melville's imagination, has also its historical significance in its insight into one aspect of the Civil War.  What Melville has revealed in the fanciful tale inspired by his visit to his cousin is a mutual fascination of each of the two camps with the other, the intimate essence of a conflict which, though fratricidal, was also incestuous . . . . .  This peculiar entanglement with one another of the American North and South was, after the war, to give rise to a formula of romantic fiction which continued to be popular for decades and which produced all those novels and plays in which two lovers, one Northern, one Southern, though destined for one another, are divided by their loyalties to their different flags" (Warren, 381).  For a more recent critical piece on the significance of the poem's nuptial imagery, see Grant Shreve's "The Shadows of Reconstruction: Marriage and Reunion in Melville's 'The Scout toward Aldie.'" [critical] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The trumpet calls; he goes within;</l>
<l rend="2em">But none the prayer and sob may know:</l>
<l>Her hero he, but bridegroom too.</l>
<l>Ah, <ref target="#ref_21133">love in a tent is a queenly thing</ref>,
<note xml:id="ref_21133">Stanton Garner and Herschel Parker offer differing accounts about the Lowells' lodgings while in camp. Parker notes, "Lowell had his headquarters in a farmhouse, although he and his wife slept in a tent" (567).  Garner, on the other hand, claims that the Lowells "shared a small house" (11) and that this line is thus the result of "poetic license" (307).  According to Grant Shreve, this line "recalls the biblical tale of Jael and Sisera from the Book of Judges, wherein the fleeing foe of the Israelites, Sisera, enters the tent of Jael, who promises him protection, only to later drive a tent stake into his head once he has fallen asleep.  Stanton Garner notes that Colonel Lowell--whom Melville had followed while sojourning in the field--had stayed with his wife not in a tent but in a cottage.  Garner attributes this change to 'poetic license' (Garner 307), but the echoes of the tale of Jael and Sisera render Melville's transformation of the Colonel's residence more deliberate and weighty.  The allusiveness of the stanza not only ironizes the Colonel's final tryst but also establishes a figural shadow beneath the text that anticipates both the Colonel's death and Melville's prophetic vision of the fate of the Union" (17).  [biography] [critical] [allusion] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em"><ref target="#ref_21134">And fame, be sure, refines the vow;</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21134">Shreve argues that these lines "direct us to [Milton's] Samson Agonistes (italics).  Milton reinterprets the story of Jael through Dalila's final speech, which Melville had heavily marked in his copy of Milton's poetic works. . . .  Melville's lines echo Dalila's valorization of the fame and honor she believes her betrayal will win her.  The 'fame' that 'refines the [marriage] vow' . . . points toward both the Colonel's fame and the kind of fame Dalila exalts.  In Milton, it 'refines the vow' by purification, and in Melville, it refines by a clarification that reveals a corruption in the vow itself" (17).  [critical] [allusion] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">But fame fond wives have lived to rue,</l>
<l rend="4em">And Mosby&apos;s men fell deeds can do.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l n="50" ><ref target="#ref_21138"><hi rend="italic">Tan-tara! tan-tara! tan-tara!</hi></ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21138">From the OED (italics): "tantara, int[erjection] and n[oun]: A. int. Imitative of the sound of a flourish blown on a trumpet, or sometimes of a drum. B. n. A fanfare, or flourish of trumpets; hence, any similar sound."  [definition] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">Mounted and armed he sits a king;</l>
<l>For pride she smiles if now she peep—</l>
<l>Elate he rides at the head of his men;</l>
<l rend="2em">He is <ref target="#ref_21144">young</ref>, and command is a boyish thing:
<note xml:id="ref_21144">Lowell was only 29 years old during the scouting expedition toward Aldie.
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">They file out into the forest deep—</l>
<l rend="4em">Do Mosby and his rangers sleep?</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0198.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>The sun is gold, and the world is green,</l>
<l rend="2em">Opal the vapors of morning roll;</l>
<l>The champing horses lightly prance—</l>
<l n="60" >Full of caprice, and the riders too</l>
<l rend="2em">Curving in many a <ref target="#ref_21141">caricole</ref>.
<note xml:id="ref_21141">A misspelling of the word "caracol," defined in Webster's 1846 dictionary as follows: "1. In the manege (italics) ['A school for teaching horsemanship, and for training horses.'], a semi-round, or half turn, which a horseman makes.--2. In architecture (italics), a staircase in a helix or spiral form." [definition] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="4em">But marshaled soon, by fours advance—</l>
<l rend="4em">Mosby had checked that airy dance.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>By the hospital-tent the cripples stand—</l>
<l rend="2em"> Bandage, and crutch, and cane, and sling,</l>
<l>And palely eye the brave array;</l>
<l>The froth of the cup is gone for them</l>
<l rend="2em">(Caw! caw! the crows through the blueness wing):</l>
<l rend="4em">Yet these were late as bold, as gay;</l>
<l n="70" rend="4em">But Mosby—<ref target="#ref_21146">a clip, and grass is hay</ref>.
<note xml:id="ref_21146">"Cf. Psalms 90: 5-6: 'In the morning they are like grass which groweth up. . . . in the evening it is cut down, and withereth'" (Cohen, 288).  [allusion] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>How strong they feel on their horses free,</l>
<l rend="2em">Tingles the tendoned thigh with life;</l>
<l>Their cavalry-jackets make boys of all—</l>
<l>With golden breasts like the <ref target="#ref_21195">oriole</ref>;
<note xml:id="ref_21195">[note about the 43rd Virginia Cavalry uniforms vs the 13th NY Cavalry]
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">The chat, the jest, and laugh are rife.</l>
<l rend="4em">But word is passed from the front—a call</l>
<l rend="4em">For order; the wood is Mosby&apos;s hall.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0199.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>To which behest one rider sly</l>
<l rend="2em">(Spurred, but unarmed) gave little heed—</l>
<l n="80">Of dexterous fun not slow or spare,</l>
<l>He teased his neighbors of touchy mood,</l>
<l rend="2em">Into plungings he pricked his steed:</l>
<l rend="4em">A black-eyed man on a coal-black mare,</l>
<l rend="4em">Alive as Mosby in mountain air.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>His limbs were long, and large and round;</l>
<l rend="2em">He whispered, winked—did all but shout:</l>
<l>A healthy man for the sick to view;</l>
<l>The taste in his mouth was sweet at morn;</l>
<l rend="2em">Little of care he cared about.</l>
<l n="90" rend="4em">And yet of pains and pangs he knew—</l>
<l rend="4em">In others, maimed by Mosby&apos;s crew.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The Hospital Steward—even he</l>
<l rend="2em">(Sacred in person as a priest),</l>
<l>And on his coat-sleeve broidered nice</l>
<l>Wore the <ref target="#ref_21147">caduceus</ref>, black and green.
<note xml:id="ref_21147">Webster's 1846 dictionary offers the following definition: "In ancient mythology (italicized), Mercury's rod, a wand entwisted by two serpents."  The current Merriam-Webster (italicize) dictionary notes, "The Greek god Hermes, who served as herald and messenger to the other gods, carried a winged staff entwined with two snakes. The staff of Aesculapius, the god of healing, had one snake and no wings. The word 'caduceus,' from Latin, is a modification of Greek karykeion, from karyx, meaning 'herald.' Strictly speaking, 'caduceus' should refer only to the staff of the herald-god Hermes (Mercury to the Romans), but in practice the word is often applied to the one-snake staff as well. You might logically expect the staff of Aesculapius to be the symbol of the medical profession-and indeed, that is the symbol used by the American Medical Association. But you will also quite frequently see the true caduceus used as a medical symbol." [definition] (Karah Mitchell)
</note></l>
<l rend="2em">No wonder he sat so light on his beast;</l>
<l rend="4em">This cheery man in suit of price</l>
<l rend="4em">Not even Mosby dared to slice.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0200.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>They pass the picket by the pine</l>
<l n="100" rend="2em">And hollow log—a lonesome place;</l>
<l>His horse adroop, and pistol clean;</l>
<l>&apos;Tis cocked—kept leveled toward the wood;</l>
<l rend="2em">Strained vigilance ages his childish face.</l>
<l rend="4em">Since midnight has that stripling been</l>
<l rend="4em">Peering for Mosby through the green.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Splashing they cross the freshet-flood,</l>
<l rend="2em">And up the muddy bank they strain;</l>
<l>A horse at the spectral white-ash shies—</l>
<l>One of the span of the ambulance,</l>
<l n="110" rend="2em">Black as a hearse. They give the rein:</l>
<l rend="4em">Silent speed on a scout were wise,</l>
<l rend="4em">Could cunning baffle Mosby&apos;s spies.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Rumor had come that a band was lodged</l>
<l rend="2em">In green retreats of hills that peer</l>
<l>By Aldie (famed for the <ref target="#BP_noteV">swordless charge<hi rend="super">v</hi></ref><note xml:id="BP_noteV"><hi rend="smallcaps">Note v</hi>, <hi rend="italics">page</hi> 192. In one of Kilpatrick's earlier cavalry fights near Aldie, a Colonel who, being under arrest, had been temporarily deprived of his sword, nevertheless, unarmed, insisted upon charging at the head of his men, which he did, and the onset proved victorious.</note>).</l>
<l>Much store they&apos;d heaped of captured arms</l>
<l rend="2em">And, peradventure, pilfered cheer;</l>
<l rend="4em">For Mosby&apos;s lads oft hearts enlarge</l>
<l rend="4em">In revelry by some gorge&apos;s marge.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0201.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l n="120">&quot;Don&apos;t let your sabres rattle and ring;</l>
<l rend="2em">To his oat-bag let each man give heed—</l>
<l>There now, that fellow&apos;s bag&apos;s untied,</l>
<l>Sowing the road with the precious grain.</l>
<l rend="2em">Your carbines swing at hand—you need!</l>
<l rend="4em">Look to yourselves, and your nags beside,</l>
<l rend="4em">Men who after Mosby ride.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Picked lads and keen went sharp before—</l>
<l rend="2em">A guard, though scarce against surprise;</l>
<l>And rearmost rode an answering troop,</l>
<l n="130">But flankers none to right or left.</l>
<l rend="2em">No bugle peals, no pennon flies:</l>
<l rend="4em">Silent they sweep, and fail would swoop</l>
<l rend="4em">On Mosby with an Indian whoop.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>On, right on through the forest land,</l>
<l rend="2em">Nor man, nor maid, nor child was seen—</l>
<l>Not even a dog. The air was still;</l>
<l>The blackened hut they turned to see,</l>
<l rend="2em">And spied charred benches on the green;</l>
<l rend="4em">A squirrel sprang from the rotting mill</l>
<l n="140" rend="4em">Whence Mosby sallied late, brave blood to spill.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0202.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>By worn-out fields they cantered on—</l>
<l rend="2em">Drear fields amid the woodlands wide;</l>
<l>By cross-roads of some olden time,</l>
<l>In which grew groves; by gate-stones down—</l>
<l rend="2em">Grassed ruins of secluded pride:</l>
<l rend="4em">A strange lone land, long past the prime,</l>
<l rend="4em">Fit land for Mosby or for crime.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The brook in the dell they pass. One peers</l>
<l rend="2em">Between the leaves: &quot;Ay, there&apos;s the place—</l>
<l>There, on the oozy ledge—&apos;twas there</l>
<l n="150">We found the body (Blake&apos;s you know);</l>
<l rend="2em">Such whirlings, gurglings round the face—</l>
<l rend="4em">Shot drinking! Well, in war all&apos;s fair—</l>
<l rend="4em">So Mosby says. The bough—take care!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Hard by, a chapel. Flower-pot mould</l>
<l rend="2em">Danked and decayed the shaded roof;</l>
<l>The porch was punk; the clapboards spanned</l>
<l>With ruffled lichens gray or green;</l>
<l rend="2em">Red coral-moss was not aloof;</l>
<l rend="4em">And mid dry leaves green dead-man&apos;s-hand</l>
<l n="160" rend="4em">Groped toward that chapel in Mosby-land.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0203.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>They leave the road and take the wood,</l>
<l rend="2em">And mark the trace of ridges there—</l>
<l>A wood where once had slept the farm—</l>
<l>A wood where once tobacco grew</l>
<l rend="2em">Drowsily in the hazy air,</l>
<l rend="4em">And wrought in all kind things a calm—</l>
<l rend="4em">Such influence, Mosby! bids disarm.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>To ease even yet the place did woo—</l>
<l rend="2em">To ease which pines unstirring share,</l>
<l n="170">For ease the weary horses sighed:</l>
<l>Halting, and slackening girths, they feed,</l>
<l rend="2em">Their pipes they light, they loiter there;</l>
<l rend="4em">Then up, and urging still the Guide,</l>
<l rend="4em">On, and after Mosby ride.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>This Guide in frowzy coat of brown,</l>
<l rend="2em">And beard of ancient growth and mould,</l>
<l>Bestrode a bony steed and strong,</l>
<l>As suited well with bulk he bore—</l>
<l rend="2em">A wheezy man with depth of hold</l>
<l n="180" rend="4em">Who jouncing went. A staff he swung—</l>
<l rend="4em">A wight whom Mosby&apos;s wasp had stung.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0204.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Burnt out and homeless—hunted long!</l>
<l rend="2em">That wheeze he caught in autumn-wood</l>
<l>Crouching (a fat man) for his life,</l>
<l>And spied his lean son &apos;mong the crew</l>
<l rend="2em">That probed the covert. Ah! black blood</l>
<l rend="4em">Was his &apos;gainst even child and wife—</l>
<l rend="4em">Fast friends to Mosby. Such the strife.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>A lad, unhorsed by sliding girths,</l>
<l n="190" rend="2em">Strains hard to readjust his seat</l>
<l>Ere the main body show the gap</l>
<l>&apos;Twixt them and the rear-guard; scrub-oaks near</l>
<l rend="2em">He sidelong eyes, while hands move fleet;</l>
<l rend="4em">Then mounts and spurs. One drops his cap—</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;Let Mosby fine!&quot; nor heeds mishap.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>A gable time-stained peeps through trees:</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;You mind the fight in the haunted house?</l>
<l>That&apos;s it; we clenched them in the room—</l>
<l>An ambuscade of ghosts, we thought,</l>
<l n="200" rend="2em">But proved sly rebels on a bouse!</l>
<l rend="4em">Luke lies in the yard.&quot; The chimneys loom:</l>
<l rend="4em">Some muse on Mosby—some on doom.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0205.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Less nimbly now through brakes they wind,</l>
<l rend="2em">And ford wild creeks where men have drowned;</l>
<l>They skirt the pool, a void the fen,</l>
<l>And so till night, when down they lie,</l>
<l rend="2em">Their steeds still saddled, in wooded ground:</l>
<l rend="4em">Rein in hand they slumber then,</l>
<l rend="4em">Dreaming of Mosby&apos;s cedarn den.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l n="210">But Colonel and Major friendly sat</l>
<l rend="2em">Where boughs deformed low made a seat.</l>
<l>The Young Man talked (all sworded and spurred)</l>
<l>Of the partisan&apos;s blade he longed to win,</l>
<l rend="2em">And frays in which he meant to beat.</l>
<l rend="4em">The grizzled Major smoked, and heard:</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;But what&apos;s that—Mosby?&quot; &quot;No, a bird.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>A contrast here like sire and son,</l>
<l rend="2em">Hope and Experience sage did meet;</l>
<l>The Youth was brave, the Senior too;</l>
<l n="220">But through the Seven Days one had served,</l>
<l rend="2em">And gasped with the rear-guard in retreat:</l>
<l rend="4em">So he smoked and smoked, and the wreath he blew—</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;Any <hi rend="italic">sure</hi> news of Mosby&apos;s crew?&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0206.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>He smoked and smoked, eying the while</l>
<l rend="2em">A huge tree hydra-like in growth—</l>
<l>Moon-tinged—with crook&apos;d boughs rent or lopped—</l>
<l>Itself a haggard forest. &quot;Come!&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">The Colonel cried, &quot;to talk you&apos;re loath;</l>
<l rend="4em">D&apos;ye hear? I say he must be stopped,</l>
<l n="230" rend="4em">This Mosby—caged, and hair close cropped.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Of course; but what&apos;s that dangling there?&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Where?&quot; &quot;From the tree—that gallows-bough;</l>
<l>&quot;A bit of frayed bark, is it not?&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Ay—or a rope; did <hi rend="italic">we</hi> hang last?—</l>
<l rend="2em">Don&apos;t like my neckerchief any how;&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">He loosened it: &quot;O ay, we&apos;ll stop</l>
<l rend="4em">This Mosby—but that vile <ref target="#BP_noteW">jerk and drop!<hi rend="super">W</hi></ref><note xml:id="BP_noteW">[Melville's note:]....</note></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>By peep of light they feed and ride,</l>
<l rend="2em">Gaining a grove&apos;s green edge at morn,</l>
<l n="240">And mark the Aldie hills uprear</l>
<l>And five gigantic horsemen carved</l>
<l rend="2em">Clear-cut against the sky withdrawn;</l>
<l rend="4em">Are more behind? an open snare?</l>
<l rend="4em">Or Mosby&apos;s men but watchmen there?</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0207.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>The ravaged land was miles behind,</l>
<l rend="2em">And Loudon spread her landscape rare;</l>
<l>Orchards in pleasant lowlands stood,</l>
<l>Cows were feeding, a cock loud crew,</l>
<l rend="2em">But not a friend at need was there;</l>
<l n="250" rend="4em">The valley-folk were only good</l>
<l rend="4em">To Mosby and his wandering brood.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>What best to do? what mean yon men?</l>
<l rend="2em">Colonel and Guide their minds compare;</l>
<l>Be sure some looked their Leader through;</l>
<l>Dismsounted, on his sword he leaned</l>
<l rend="2em">As one who feigns an easy air;</l>
<l rend="4em">And yet perplexed he was they knew—</l>
<l rend="4em">Perplexed by Mosby&apos;s mountain-crew.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The Major hemmed as he would speak,</l>
<l n="260" rend="2em">But checked himself, and left the ring</l>
<l>Of cavalrymen about their Chief—</l>
<l>Young courtiers mute who paid their court</l>
<l rend="2em">By looking with confidence on their king;</l>
<l rend="4em">They knew him brave, foresaw no grief—</l>
<l rend="4em">But Mosby—the time to think is brief.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0208.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>The Surgeon (sashed in sacred green)</l>
<l rend="2em">Was glad &apos;twas not for <hi rend="italic">him</hi> to say</l>
<l>What next should be; if a trooper bleeds,</l>
<l>Why he will do his best, as wont,</l>
<l n="270" rend="2em">And his partner in black will aid and pray;</l>
<l rend="4em">But judgment bides with him who leads,</l>
<l rend="4em">And Mosby many a problem breeds.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>This Surgeon was the kindliest man</l>
<l rend="2em">That ever a callous trade professed;</l>
<l>He felt for him, that Leader young,</l>
<l>And offered medicine from his flask:</l>
<l rend="2em">The Colonel took it with marvelous zest.</l>
<l rend="4em">For such fine medicine good and strong,</l>
<l rend="4em">Oft Mosby and his foresters long.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l n="280">A charm of proof. &quot;Ho, Major, come—</l>
<l rend="2em">Pounce on yon men! Take half your troop</l>
<l>Through the thickets wind—pray speedy be—</l>
<l>And gain their rear. And, Captain Morn</l>
<l rend="2em">Picket these roads—all travelers stop;</l>
<l rend="2em">The rest to the edge of this crest with me,</l>
<l rend="2em">That Mosby and his scouts may see.&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0209.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Commanded and done. Ere the sun stood steep,</l>
<l rend="2em">Back came the Blues, with a troop of Grays,</l>
<l>Ten riding double—luckless ten!—</l>
<l n="290">Five horses gone, and looped hats lost,</l>
<l rend="2em">And love-locks dancing in a maze—</l>
<l rend="4em">Certes, but sophomores from the glen</l>
<l rend="4em">Of Mosby—not his veteran men.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Colonel,&quot; said the Major, touching his cap,</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;We&apos;ve had our ride, and here they are.&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Well done! how many found you there?&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;As many as I bring you here.&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;And no one hurt?&quot; &quot;There&apos;ll be no scar—</l>
<l rend="4em">One fool was battered.&quot; &quot;Find their lair?&quot;</l>
<l n="300" rend="4em">&quot;Why, Mosby&apos;s brood camp every where.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>He sighed, and slid down from his horse,</l>
<l rend="2em">And limping went to a spring-head nigh.</l>
<l>&quot;Why, bless me, Major, not hurt, I hope?&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Battered my knee against a bar</l>
<l rend="2em">When the rush was made; all right by-and-by.—</l>
<l rend="4em">Halloa! they gave you too much rope—</l>
<l rend="4em">Go back to Mosby, eh? elope?&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0210.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Just by the low-hanging skirt of wood</l>
<l rend="2em">The guard, remiss, had given a chance</l>
<l n="310">For a sudden sally into the cover—</l>
<l>But foiled the intent, nor fired a shot,</l>
<l rend="2em">Though the issue was a deadly trance;</l>
<l rend="4em">For, hurled &apos;gainst an oak that humped low over,</l>
<l rend="4em">Mosby&apos;s man fell, pale as a lover.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>They pulled some grass his head to ease</l>
<l rend="2em">(Lined with blue shreds a ground-nest stirred).</l>
<l>The Surgeon came—&quot;Here&apos;s a to-do!&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Ah!&quot; cried the Major, darting a glance,</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;This fellow&apos;s the one that fired and spurred</l>
<l n="320" rend="4em">Down hill, but met reserves below—</l>
<l rend="4em">My boys, not Mosby&apos;s—so we go!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The Surgeon—bluff, red, goodly man—</l>
<l rend="2em">Kneeled by the hurt one; like a bee</l>
<l>He toiled. The pale young Chaplain too—</l>
<l>(Who went to the wars for cure of souls,</l>
<l rend="2em">And his own student-ailments)—he</l>
<l rend="4em">Bent over likewise; spite the two,</l>
<l rend="4em">Mosby&apos;s poor man more pallid grew.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0211.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Meanwhile the mounted captives near</l>
<l n="330" rend="2em">Jested; and yet they anxious showed;</l>
<l>Virginians; some of family-pride,</l>
<l>And young, and full of fire, and fine</l>
<l rend="2em">In open feature and cheek that glowed;</l>
<l rend="4em">And here thralled vagabonds now they ride—</l>
<l rend="4em">But list! one speaks for Mosby&apos;s side.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Why, three to one—your horses strong—</l>
<l rend="2em">Revolvers, rifles, and a surprise—</l>
<l>Surrender we account no shame!</l>
<l>We live, are gay, and life is hope;</l>
<l n="340" rend="2em">We&apos;ll fight again when fight is wise.</l>
<l rend="4em">There are plenty more from where we came;</l>
<l rend="4em">But go find Mosby—start the game!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Yet one there was who looked but glum;</l>
<l rend="2em">In middle-age, a father he,</l>
<l>And this his first experience too:</l>
<l>&quot;They shot at my heart when my hands were up—</l>
<l rend="2em">This fighting&apos;s crazy work, I see!&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">But noon is high; what next to do?</l>
<l rend="2em">The woods are mute, and Mosby is the foe.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0212.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l n="350">&quot;Save what we&apos;ve got,&quot; the Major said;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Bad plan to make a scout too long;</l>
<l>The tide may turn, and drag them back,</l>
<l>And more beside. These rides I&apos;ve been,</l>
<l rend="2em">And every time a mine was sprung.</l>
<l rend="4em">To rescue, mind, they won&apos;t be slack—</l>
<l rend="4em">Look out for Mosby&apos;s rifle-crack.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;We&apos;ll welcome it! give crack for crack!</l>
<l rend="2em">Peril, old lad, is what I seek.&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;O then, there&apos;s plenty to be had—</l>
<l n="360">By all means on, and have our fill!&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">With that, grotesque, he writhed his neck,</l>
<l rend="4em">Showing a scar by buck-shot made—</l>
<l rend="4em">Kind Mosby&apos;s Christmas gift, he said.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>But, Colonel, my prisoners—let a guard</l>
<l rend="2em">Make sure of them, and lead to camp.</l>
<l>That done, we&apos;re free for a dark-room fight</l>
<l>If so you say.&quot; The other laughed;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Trust me, Major, nor throw a damp.</l>
<l rend="4em">But first to try a little sleight—</l>
<l n="370" rend="4em">Sure news of Mosby would suit me quite.&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0213.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Herewith he turned—&quot;Reb, have a dram?&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">Holding the Surgeon&apos;s flask with a smile</l>
<l>To a young scapegrace from the glen.</l>
<l>&quot;O yes!&quot; he eagerly replied,</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;And thank you, Colonel, but—any guile?</l>
<l rend="4em">For if you think we&apos;ll blab—why, then</l>
<l rend="4em">You don&apos;t know Mosby or his men.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The Leader&apos;s genial air relaxed.</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Best give it up,&quot; a whisperer said.</l>
<l n="380">&quot;By heaven, I&apos;ll range their rebel den!&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;They&apos;ll treat you well,&quot; the captive cried;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;They&apos;re all like us—handsome—well bred:</l>
<l rend="4em">In wood or town, with sword or pen,</l>
<l rend="4em">Polite is Mosby, bland his men.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Where were you, lads, last night?—come, tell!&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;We?—at a wedding in the Vale—</l>
<l>The bridegroom our comrade; by his side</l>
<l>Belisent, my cousin—O, so proud</l>
<l rend="2em">Of her young love with old wounds pale—</l>
<l n="390" rend="4em">A Virginian girl! God bless her pride—</l>
<l rend="4em">Of a crippled Mosby-man the bride!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0214.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Four walls shall mend that saucy mood,</l>
<l rend="2em">And moping prisons tame him down,&quot;</l>
<l>Said Captain Cloud. &quot;God help that day,&quot;</l>
<l>Cried Captain Morn, &quot;and he so young.</l>
<l rend="2em">But hark, he sings—a madcap one!&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;<hi rend="italic">O we multiply merrily in the May,</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">The birds and Mosby&apos;s men, they say!</hi> &quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>While echoes ran, a wagon old,</l>
<l n="400" rend="2em">Under stout guard of Corporal Chew</l>
<l>Came up; a lame horse, dingy white,</l>
<l>With clouted harness; ropes in hand,</l>
<l rend="2em">Cringed the humped driver, black in hue;</l>
<l rend="4em">By him (for Mosby&apos;s band a sight)</l>
<l rend="4em">A sister-rebel sat, her veil held tight.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;I picked them up,&quot; the Corporal said,</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Crunching their way over stick and root,</l>
<l>Through yonder wood. The man here—Cuff—</l>
<l>Says they are going to Leesburg town.&quot;</l>
<l n="410" rend="2em">The Colonel&apos;s eye took in the group;</l>
<l rend="2em">The veiled one&apos;s hand he spied—enough!</l>
<l rend="2em">Not Mosby&apos;s. Spite the gown&apos;s poor stuff,</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0215.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Off went his hat: &quot;Lady, fear not;</l>
<l rend="2em">We soldiers do what we deplore—</l>
<l>I must detain you till we march.&quot;</l>
<l>The stranger nodded. Nettled now,</l>
<l rend="2em">He grew politer than before:—</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;&apos;Tis Mosby&apos;s fault, this halt and search:&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">The lady stiffened in her starch.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l n="420">&quot;My duty, madam, bids me now</l>
<l rend="2em">Ask what may seem a little rude.</l>
<l>Pardon—that veil—withdraw it, please</l>
<l>(Corporal! make every man fall back);</l>
<l rend="2em">Pray, now I do but what I should;</l>
<l rend="4em">Bethink you, &apos;tis in masks like these</l>
<l rend="4em">That Mosby haunts the villages.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Slowly the stranger drew her veil,</l>
<l rend="2em">And looked the Soldier in the eye—</l>
<l>A glance of mingled foul and fair;</l>
<l n="430">Sad patience in a proud disdain,</l>
<l rend="2em">And more than quietude. A sigh</l>
<l rend="4em">She heaved, and if all unaware,</l>
<l rend="4em">And far seemed Mosby from her care.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0216.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>She came from Yewton Place, her home,</l>
<l rend="2em">So ravaged by the war&apos;s wild play—</l>
<l>Campings, and foragings, and fires—</l>
<l>That now she sought an aunt&apos;s abode.</l>
<l rend="2em">Her kinsmen? In Lee&apos;s army, they.</l>
<l rend="4em">The black? A servant, late her sire&apos;s.</l>
<l n="440" rend="4em">And Mosby? Vainly he inquires.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>He gazed, and sad she met his eye;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;In the wood yonder were you lost?&quot;</l>
<l>No; at the forks they left the road</l>
<l>Because of hoof-prints (thick they were—</l>
<l rend="2em">Thick as the words in notes thrice crossed),</l>
<l rend="4em">And fearful, made that episode.</l>
<l rend="4em">In fear of Mosby? None she showed.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Her poor attire again he scanned:</l>
<l>&quot;Lady, once more; I grieve to jar</l>
<l n="450" rend="2em">On all sweet usage, but must plead</l>
<l>To have what peeps there from your dress;</l>
<l rend="2em">That letter—&apos;tis justly prize of war&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">She started—gave it—she must need.</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;&apos;Tis not from Mosby? May I read?&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0217.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>And straight such matter he perused</l>
<l rend="2em">That with the Guide he went apart.</l>
<l>The Hospital Steward&apos;s turn began:</l>
<l>&quot;Must squeeze this darkey; every tap</l>
<l rend="2em">Of knowledge we are bound to start.&quot;</l>
<l n="460" rend="4em">&quot;Garry,&quot; she said, &quot;tell all you can</l>
<l rend="4em">Of Colonel Mosby—that brave man.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Dun know much, sare; and missis here</l>
<l rend="2em">Know less dan me. But dis I know—&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Well, what?&quot; &quot;I dun know what I know.&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;A knowing answer!&quot; The hump-back coughed,</l>
<l rend="2em">Rubbing his yellowish wool like tow.</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;Come—Mosby—tell!&quot; &quot;O dun look so!</l>
<l rend="4em">My gal nursed missis—let we go.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Go where?&quot; demanded Captain Cloud;</l>
<l n="470" rend="2em">&quot;Back into bondage? Man, you&apos;re free!&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Well, <hi rend="italic">let</hi> we free!&quot; The Captain&apos;s brow</l>
<l>Lowered; the Colonel came—had heard:</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Pooh! pooh! his simple heart I see—</l>
<l rend="4em">A faithful servant.—Lady&quot; (a bow),</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;Mosby&apos;s abroad—with us you&apos;ll go.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0218.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Guard! look to your prisoners; back to camp!</l>
<l rend="2em">The man in the grass—can he mount and away?</l>
<l>Why, how he groans!&quot; &quot;Bad inward bruise—</l>
<l>Might lug him along in the ambulance&quot;</l>
<l n="480" rend="2em">&quot;Coals to Newcastle! let him stay.</l>
<l rend="4em">Boots and saddles!—our pains we lose,</l>
<l rend="4em">Nor care I if Mosby hear the news!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>But word was sent to a house at hand,</l>
<l rend="2em">And a flask was left by the hurt one&apos;s side.</l>
<l>They seized in that same house a man,</l>
<l>Neutral by day, by night a foe—</l>
<l rend="2em">So charged his neighbor late, the Guide.</l>
<l rend="4em">A grudge? Hate will do what it can;</l>
<l rend="4em">Along he went for a Mosby-man.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l n="490">No secrets now; the bugle calls;</l>
<l rend="2em">The open road they take, nor shun</l>
<l>The hill; retrace the weary way.</l>
<l>But one there was who whispered low,</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;This is a feint—we&apos;ll back anon;</l>
<l rend="4em">Young Hair-Brains don&apos;t retreat, they say;</l>
<l rend="4em">A brush with Mosby is the play!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0219.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>They rode till eve. Then on a farm</l>
<l rend="2em">That lay along a hill-side green,</l>
<l>Bivouacked. Fires were made, and then</l>
<l n="500">Coffee was boiled; a cow was coaxed</l>
<l rend="2em">And killed, and savory roasts were seen;</l>
<l rend="4em">And under the lee of a cattle-pen</l>
<l rend="4em">The guard supped freely with Mosby&apos;s men.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The ball was bandied to and fro;</l>
<l rend="2em">Hits were given and hits were met:</l>
<l>&quot;Chickamauga, Feds—take off your hat!&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;But the Fight in the Clouds repaid you, Rebs!&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Forgotten about Manassas yet?&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">Chatting and chaffing, and tit for tat,</l>
<l n="510" rend="4em">Mosby&apos;s clan with the troopers sat.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Here comes the moon!&quot; a captive cried;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;A song! what say? Archy, my lad!&quot;</l>
<l>Hailing the still one of the clan</l>
<l>(A boyish face with girlish hair),</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Give us that thing poor Pansy made</l>
<l rend="4em">Last Year.&quot; He brightened, and began;</l>
<l rend="4em">And this was the song of Mosby&apos;s man:</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0220.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l><hi rend="italic">Spring is come; she shows her pass—</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">Wild violets cool!</hi></l>
<l n="520"><hi rend="italic">South of woods a small close grass—</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">A vernal wool!</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Leaves are a&apos;bud on the sassafras—</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">They&apos;ll soon be full:</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Blessings on the friendly screen—</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">I&apos;m for the South! says the leafage green.</hi></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l><hi rend="italic">Robins! fly, and take your fill</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">Of out-of-doors—</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Garden, orchard, meadow, hill,</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">Barns and bowers;</hi></l>
<l n="530"><hi rend="italic">Take your fill, and have your will—</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">Virginia&apos;s yours!</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">But, bluebirds! keep away, and fear</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">The ambuscade in bushes here.</hi></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;A green song that,&quot; a sergeant said;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;But where&apos;s poor Pansy? gone, I fear&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Ay, mustered out at Ashby&apos;s Gap.&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;I see; now for a live man&apos;s song;</l>
<l rend="2em">Ditty for ditty—prepare to cheer.</l>
<l rend="4em">My bluebirds, you can fling a cap!</l>
<l n="540" rend="4em">You barehead Mosby-boys—why—clap!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0221.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l><hi rend="italic">Nine Blue-coats went a-nutting</hi></l>
<l rend="2em"><hi rend="italic">Slyly in Tennessee—</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">Not for chestnuts—better than that—</hi></l>
<l rend="2em"><hi rend="italic">Hush, you bumble-bee!</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">Nutting, nutting—</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">All through the year there&apos;s nutting!</hi></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l><hi rend="italic">A tree they spied so yellow,</hi></l>
<l rend="2em"><hi rend="italic">Rustling in motion queer;</hi></l>
<l><hi rend="italic">In they fired, and down they dropped—</hi></l>
<l n="550" rend="2em"><hi rend="italic">Butternuts, my dear!</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">Nutting, nutting—</hi></l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="italic">Who&apos;ll &apos;list to go a-nutting?</hi></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Ah! why should good fellows foemen be?</l>
<l rend="2em">And who would dream that foes they were—</l>
<l>Larking and singing so friendly then—</l>
<l>A family likeness in every face.</l>
<l rend="2em">But Captain Cloud made sour demur:</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;Guard! keep your prisoners <hi rend="italic">in</hi> the pen,</l>
<l rend="4em">And let none talk with Mosby&apos;s men.&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0222.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l n="560">That captain was a valorous one</l>
<l rend="2em">(No irony, but honest truth),</l>
<l>Yet down from his brain cold drops distilled,</l>
<l>Making stalactites in his heart—</l>
<l rend="2em">A conscientious soul, forsooth;</l>
<l rend="4em">And with a formal hate was filled</l>
<l rend="4em">Of Mosby&apos;s band; and some he&apos;d killed.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Meantime the lady rueful sat,</l>
<l rend="2em">Watching the flicker of a fire</l>
<l>Were the Colonel played the outdoor host</l>
<l n="570">In brave old hall of ancient Night.</l>
<l rend="2em">But ever the dame grew shyer and shyer,</l>
<l rend="4em">Seeming with private grief engrossed—</l>
<l rend="4em">Grief far from Mosby, housed or lost.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The ruddy embers showed her pale.</l>
<l rend="2em">The Soldier did his best devoir:</l>
<l>&quot;Some coffee?—no?—cracker?—one?&quot;</l>
<l>Cared for her servant—sought to cheer:</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;I know, I know—a cruel war!</l>
<l rend="4em">But wait—even Mosby&apos;ll eat his bun;</l>
<l n="580" rend="4em">The Old Hearth—back to it anon!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0223.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>But cordial words no balm could bring;</l>
<l rend="2em">She sighed, and kept her inward chafe,</l>
<l>And seemed to hate the voice of glee—</l>
<l>Joyless and tearless. Soon he called</l>
<l rend="2em">An escort: &quot;See this lady safe</l>
<l rend="4em">In yonder house.—Madam, you&apos;re free.</l>
<l rend="4em">And now for Mosby.—Guide! with me.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>(&quot;A night-ride, eh?&quot;) &quot;Tighten your girths!</l>
<l rend="2em">But, buglers! not a note from you.</l>
<l n="590">Fling more rails on the fires—a blaze!&quot;</l>
<l>(&quot;Sergeant, a feint—I told you so—</l>
<l rend="2em">Toward Aldie again. Bivouac, adieu!&quot;)</l>
<l rend="4em">After the cheery flames they gaze,</l>
<l rend="4em">Then back for Mosby through the maze.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The moon looked through the trees, and tipped</l>
<l rend="2em">The scabbards with her elfin beam;</l>
<l>The Leader backward cast his glance,</l>
<l>Proud of the cavalcade that came—</l>
<l rend="2em">A hundred horses, bay and cream:</l>
<l n="600" rend="4em">&quot;Major! look how the lads advance—</l>
<l rend="4em">Mosby we&apos;ll have in the ambulance!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0224.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;No doubt, no doubt:—was that a hare?—</l>
<l rend="2em">First catch, then cook; and cook him brown.&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Trust me to catch,&quot; the other cried—</l>
<l>&quot;The lady&apos;s letter!—a dance, man, dance</l>
<l rend="2em">This night is given in Leesburg town!&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;He&apos;ll be there too!&quot; wheezed out the Guide;</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;That Mosby loves a dance and ride!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;The lady, ah!—the lady&apos;s letter—</l>
<l n="610" rend="2em">A <hi rend="italic">lady</hi>, then, is in the case,&quot;</l>
<l>Muttered the Major. &quot;Ay, her aunt</l>
<l>Writes her to come by Friday eve</l>
<l rend="2em">(To-night), for people of the place,</l>
<l rend="4em">At Mosby&apos;s last fight jubilant,</l>
<l rend="4em">A party give, though table-cheer be scant.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The Major hemmed. &quot;Then this night-ride</l>
<l rend="2em">We owe to her?—One lighted house</l>
<l>In a town else dark.—The moths, begar!</l>
<l>Are not quite yet all dead!&quot; &quot;How? how?&quot;</l>
<l n="620" rend="2em">&quot;A mute, meek mournful little mouse!—</l>
<l rend="4em">Mosby has wiles which subtle are—</l>
<l rend="4em">But woman&apos;s wiles in wiles of war!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0225.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Tut, Major! by what craft or guile—&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Can&apos;t tell! but he&apos;ll be found in wait.</l>
<l>Softly we enter, say, the town—</l>
<l>Good! pickets post, and all so sure—</l>
<l rend="2em">When—crack! the rifles from every gate,</l>
<l rend="4em">The Gray-backs fire—dash up and down—</l>
<l rend="4em">Each alley unto Mosby known!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l n="630">&quot;Now, Major, now—you take dark views</l>
<l rend="2em">Of a moonlight night.&quot; &quot;Well, well, we&apos;ll see,&quot;</l>
<l>And smoked as if each whiff were gain.</l>
<l>The other mused; then sudden asked,</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;What would you do in grand decree?&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">I&apos;d beat, if I could, Lee&apos;s armies—then</l>
<l rend="4em">Send constables after Mosby&apos;s men.&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Ay! ay!—you&apos;re odd.&quot; The moon sailed up;</l>
<l rend="2em">On through the shadowy land they went.</l>
<l>&quot;<hi rend="italic">Names must be made and printed be!</hi> &quot;</l>
<l n="640">Hummed the blithe Colonel. &quot;Doc, your flask!</l>
<l rend="2em">Major, I drink to your good content.</l>
<l rend="4em">My pipe is out—enough for me!</l>
<l rend="4em">One&apos;s buttons shine—does Mosby see?</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0226.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;But what comes here?&quot; A man from the front</l>
<l rend="2em">Reported a tree athwart the road.</l>
<l> &quot;Go round it, then; no time to bide;</l>
<l>All right—go on! Were one to stay</l>
<l rend="2em">For each distrust of a nervous mood,</l>
<l rend="4em">Long miles we&apos;d make in this our ride</l>
<l n="650" rend="4em">Through Mosby-land.—On! with the Guide!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Then sportful to the Surgeon turned:</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;Green sashes hardly serve by night!&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Nor bullets nor bottles,&quot; the Major sighed,</l>
<l>&quot;Against these moccasin-snakes—such foes</l>
<l rend="2em">As seldom come to solid fight:</l>
<l rend="4em">They kill and vanish; through grass they glide;</l>
<l rend="4em">Devil take Mosby!—&quot; his horse here shied.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Hold! look—the tree, like a dragged balloon;</l>
<l rend="2em">A globe of leaves—some trickery here;</l>
<l n="660">My nag is right—best now be shy.&quot;</l>
<l>A movement was made, a hubbub and snarl;</l>
<l rend="2em">Little was plain—they blindly steer.</l>
<l rend="4em">The Pleiads, as from ambush sly,</l>
<l rend="4em">Peep out—Mosby&apos;s men in the sky!</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0227.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>As restive they turn, how sore they feel,</l>
<l rend="2em">And cross, and sleepy, and full of spleen,</l>
<l>And curse the war. &quot;Fools, North and South!&quot;</l>
<l>Said one right out. &quot;O for a bed!</l>
<l rend="2em">O now to drop in this woodland green!&quot;</l>
<l n="670" rend="4em">He drops as the syllables leave his mouth—</l>
<l rend="4em">Mosby speaks from the undergrowth—</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Speaks in a volley! out jets the flame!</l>
<l rend="2em">Men fall from their saddles like plums from trees;</l>
<l>Horses take fright, reins tangle and bind;</l>
<l>&quot;Steady—dismount—form—and into the wood!&quot;</l>
<l rend="2em">They go, but find what scarce can please:</l>
<l rend="4em">Their steeds have been tied in the field behind</l>
<l rend="4em">And Mosby&apos;s men are off like the wind.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>Sound the recall! vain to pursue—</l>
<l n="680" rend="2em">The enemy scatters in wilds he knows,</l>
<l>To reunite in his own good time;</l>
<l>And, to follow, they need divide—</l>
<l rend="2em">To come lone and lost on crouching foes:</l>
<l rend="4em">Maple and hemlock, beech and lime,</l>
<l rend="4em">Are Mosby&apos;s confederates, share the crime.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0228.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Major,&quot; burst in a bugler small,</l>
<l rend="2em">&quot;The fellow we left in Loudon grass—</l>
<l>Sir Slyboots with the inward bruise,</l>
<l>His voice I heard—the very same—</l>
<l n="690" rend="2em">Some watchword in the ambush pass;</l>
<l rend="4em">Ay, sir, we had him in his shoes—</l>
<l rend="4em">We caught him—Mosby—but to lose!&quot;</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Go, go!—these saddle-dreamers! Well,</l>
<l rend="2em">And here&apos;s another.—Cool, sir, cool!&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Major, I saw them mount and sweep,</l>
<l>And one was humped, or I mistake,</l>
<l rend="2em">And in the skurry dropped his wool.&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;A wig! go fetch it:—the lads need sleep;</l>
<l rend="4em">They&apos;ll next see Mosby in a sheep!</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l n="700">&quot;Come, come, fall back! reform yours ranks—</l>
<l rend="2em">All&apos;s jackstraws here! Where&apos;s Captain Morn?—</l>
<l>We&apos;ve parted like boats in a raging tide!</l>
<l>But stay-the Colonel—did he charge?</l>
<l rend="2em">And comes he there? &apos;Tis streak of dawn;</l>
<l rend="4em">Mosby is off, the woods are wide—</l>
<l rend="4em">Hist! there&apos;s a groan—this crazy ride!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0229.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>As they searched for the fallen, the dawn grew chill;</l>
<l rend="2em">They lay in the dew: &quot;Ah! hurt much, Mink?</l>
<l>And—yes—the Colonel!&quot; Dead! but so calm</l>
<l n="710">That death seemed nothing—even death,</l>
<l rend="2em">The thing we deem every thing heart can think;</l>
<l rend="4em">Amid wilding roses that shed their balm,</l>
<l rend="4em">Careless of Mosby he lay—in a charm!</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The Major took him by the hand—</l>
<l rend="2em">Into the friendly clasp it bled</l>
<l>(A ball through heart and hand he rued):</l>
<l>&quot;Good-by!&quot; and gazed with humid glance;</l>
<l rend="2em">Then in a hollow revery said,</l>
<l rend="4em">&quot;The weakest thing is lustihood;</l>
<l n="720" rend="4em">But Mosby—&quot; and he checked his mood.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Where&apos;s the advance?—cut off, by heaven!</l>
<l rend="2em">Come, Surgeon, how with your wounded there?&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;The ambulance will carry all&quot;</l>
<l>&quot;Well, get them in; we go to camp.</l>
<l rend="2em">Seven prisoners gone? for the rest have care.&quot;</l>
<l rend="4em">Then to himself, &quot;This grief is gall;</l>
<l rend="4em">That Mosby!—I&apos;ll cast a silver ball!&quot;</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0230.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;Ho!&quot; turning—&quot;Captain Cloud, you mind</l>
<l rend="2em">The place where the escort went—so shady?</l>
<l n="730">Go, search every closet low and high,</l>
<l>And barn, and bin, and hidden bower—</l>
<l rend="2em">Every covert—find that lady!</l>
<l rend="4em">And yet I may misjudge her—ay,</l>
<l rend="4em">Women (like Mosby) mystify.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>&quot;We&apos;ll see. Ay, Captain, go—with speed!</l>
<l rend="2em">Surround and search; each living thing</l>
<l>Secure; that done, await us where</l>
<l>We last turned off. Stay! fire the cage</l>
<l rend="2em">If the birds be flown.&quot; By the cross-road spring</l>
<l n="740" rend="4em">The bands rejoined; no words; the glare</l>
<l rend="4em">Told all. Had Mosby plotted there?</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The weary troop that wended now—</l>
<l rend="2em">Hardly it seemed the same that pricked</l>
<l>Forth to the forest from the camp:</l>
<l>Foot-sore horses, jaded men;</l>
<l rend="2em">Every backbone felt as nicked,</l>
<l rend="4em">Each eye dim as a sick-room lamp,</l>
<l rend="4em">All faces stamped with Mosby&apos;s stamp.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0231.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>In order due the Major rode—</l>
<l n="750" rend="2em">Chaplain and Surgeon on either hand;</l>
<l>A riderless horse a negro led;</l>
<l>In a wagon the blanketed sleeper went;</l>
<l rend="2em">Then the ambulance with the bleeding band;</l>
<l rend="4em">And, an emptied oat-bag on each head,</l>
<l rend="4em">Went Mosby&apos;s men, and marked the dead.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>What gloomed them? what so cast them down,</l>
<l rend="2em">And changed the cheer that late they took,</l>
<l>As double-guarded now they rode</l>
<l>Between the files of moody men?</l>
<l n="760" rend="2em">Some sudden consciousness they brook,</l>
<l rend="4em">Or dread the sequel. That night&apos;s blood</l>
<l rend="4em">Disturbed even Mosby&apos;s brotherhood.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The flagging horses stumbled at roots,</l>
<l rend="2em">Floundered in mires, or clinked the stones;</l>
<l>No rider spake except aside;</l>
<l>But the wounded cramped in the ambulance,</l>
<l rend="2em">It was horror to hear their groans—</l>
<l rend="4em">Jerked along in the woodland ride,</l>
<l rend="4em">While Mosby&apos;s clan their revery hide.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0232.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l n="770">The Hospital Steward—even he—</l>
<l rend="2em">Who on the sleeper kept his glance,</l>
<l>Was changed; late bright-black beard and eye</l>
<l>Looked now hearse-black; his heavy heart,</l>
<l rend="2em">Like his fagged mare, no more could dance;</l>
<l rend="4em">His grape was now a raisin dry:</l>
<l rend="4em">&apos;Tis Mosby&apos;s homily—<hi rend="italic">Man must die.</hi></l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>The amber sunset flushed the camp</l>
<l rend="2em">As on the hill their eyes they fed;</l>
<l>The pickets dumb looks at the wagon dart;</l>
<l n="780">A handkerchief waves from the bannered tent—</l>
<l rend="2em">As white, alas! the face of the dead:</l>
<l rend="4em">Who shall the withering news impart?</l>
<l rend="4em">The bullet of Mosby goes through heart to heart!</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l>They buried him where the lone ones lie</l>
<l rend="2em">(Lone sentries shot on midnight post)—</l>
<l>A green-wood grave-yard hid from ken,</l>
<l>Where sweet-fern flings an odor nigh—</l>
<l rend="2em">Yet held in fear for the gleaming ghost!</l>
<l rend="4em">Though the bride should see threescore and ten,</l>
<l n="790" rend="4em">She will dream of Mosby and his men.</l>
</lg>

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0233.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l>Now halt the verse, and turn aside—</l>
<l rend="2em">The cypress falls athwart the way;</l>
<l>No joy remains for bard to sing;</l>
<l>And heaviest dole of all is this,</l>
<l rend="2em">That other hearts shall be as gay</l>
<l rend="4em">As hers that now no more shall spring:</l>
<l rend="4em">To Mosby-land the dirges cling.</l>
</lg>

</div>
</body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
