<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="italic">Supplement</hi></hi></title>
		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div id="75--supplement">
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0265.jpg"/>
<head rend="main"><l rend="12em">&#xA0;&#xA0;<hi rend="italic">S U P P L E M E N T.</hi></l></head>
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0267.jpg"/>
<!--
<ref target="#EDnoteSupp1"></ref>
<note xml:id="EDnoteSupp1"></note>
-->
<p><hi rend="smallcaps"> Were</hi> I fastidiously anxious for the symmetry of this book, it would close with the notes. But the times are such that patriotism—not free from solicitude—urges a claim overriding all literary scruples.
</p>

<p>It is more than a year since the memorable <ref target="#EDnoteSupp1">surrender</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp1">Lee's surrender to Grant at Appomattox Court House, VA, on 9 April 1865 signaled the end of the Civil War. From February to July of 1866, Melville published five Civil War poems in <hi rend="italic">Harper's New Monthly Magazine</hi> and included them among the 72 lyric and long poems in <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi>, published in late August, 1866. He probably wrote the book's "Supplement" in the summer of that year.</note>, but events have not yet rounded themselves into completion. Not justly can we complain of this. There has been an upheavel affecting the basis of things; to altered circumstances complicated adaptations are to be made; there are difficulties great and novel. But is Reason still waiting for Passion to spend itself? We have sung of the soldiers and sailors, but who shall hymn the politicians?
</p>

<p>In view of the infinite desirableness of Re-establishment, and considering that, so far as feeling is concerned, it depends not mainly on the temper in which the South regards the North, but rather conversely; one who never was a blind adherent feels constrained to submit some thoughts, counting on the indulgence of his countrymen.
</p>

<p>And, first, it may be said that, if among the feelings and opinions growing immediately out of a great civil

<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0268.jpg"/> convulsion, there are any which time shall modify or do away, they are presumably those of a less temperate and charitable cast.
</p>

<p>There seems no reason why patriotism and <ref target="#EDnoteSuppRN1">narrowness</ref>
<note xml:id="EDnoteSuppRN1">In his bound sheets of <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi> (Copy C), Melville underlined "narrowness" in pencil and inscribed "narrowmindedness" on a slant in the left margin, but soon after he erased both the underlining and the word. The timing of the erasure follows one of at least two scenarios. Melville might have erased "narrowmindedness" immediately, rejecting it on its own terms; or he might have retained it but reconsidered it a few words later when he was prompted to revise "imparitality" to "fairmindedness" (as discussed below), at which point he erased "narrowmindedness" as repetitious. Also possible is that Melville revised "impartiality" to "fairmindedness" first, and then considered and rejected "narrowmindedness."</note> <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v2/battle-pieces-ii-0270.jpg"/> should go together, or why intellectual <ref target="#EDnoteSuppRN2">impartiality</ref>
<note xml:id="EDnoteSuppRN2">In Copy C, Melville underlined "impartiality" in pencil and inscribed an "x" in the right margin. Beside a similar "x" in the top margin, he wrote "fairmindedness." As noted above, this revision is coordinated, in two or three possible time sequences, with the revision of "narrowness" to "narrowmindedness." The deletion of "impartiality" also removes a possibly unwanted partial redundancy with "partisan" later on.</note> should be confounded with political trimming, or why serviceable truth should keep cloistered by a cause not partisan. Yet the work of <ref target="#EDnoteSupp2">Reconstruction</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp2">The Reconstruction Era (1866-1877) introduced federal measures (including constitutional amendments, voting rights acts, and the Freedmen's Bureau) for assimilating the southern states and formerly enslaved people into the Union. In the immediate aftermath of the war, Congress overrode vetoes by Lincoln's presidential successor Andrew Johnson, until the mid-term Congressional elections of November 1866, which gave further impetus to reconstruction legislation. Melville composed his "Supplement" during this fractious political moment.</note>, if admitted to be feasible at all, demands little but common sense and Christian charity. Little but these? These are much.
</p>
<p>Some of us are concerned because as yet the South shows no penitence. But what exactly do we mean by this? Since down to the close of the war she never confessed any for braving it, the only penitence now left her is that which springs solely from the sense of discomfiture; and since this evidently would be a contrition hypocritical, it would be unworthy in us to demand it. Certain it is that penitence, in the sense of voluntary humiliation, will never be displayed. Nor does this afford just ground for unreserved condemnation. It is enough, for all practical purposes, if the South have been taught by the terrors of civil war to feel that Secession, like Slavery, is against Destiny; that both now lie buried in one grave; that her fate is linked with ours; and that together we comprise the Nation.
</p>

<p>The clouds of heroes who battled for the Union it is <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0269.jpg"/> needless to eulogize here. But how of the soldiers on the other side? And when of a free community we name the soldiers, we thereby name the people. It was in subserviency to the slave-interest that Secession was plotted; but it was under the plea, plausibly urged, that certain inestimable rights guaranteed by the Constitution were directly menaced, that the people of the South were cajoled into revolution. Through the arts of the conspirators and the perversity of fortune, the most sensitive love of liberty was entrapped into the support of a war whose implied end was the erecting in our advanced century of an Anglo-American empire based upon the systematic degradation of man.
</p>

<p>Spite this clinging reproach, however, signal military virtues and achievements have conferred upon the Confederate arms historic fame, and upon certain of the commanders a renown extending beyond the sea—a renown which we of the North could not suppress, even if we would. In personal character, also, not a few of the military leaders of the South enforce forbearance; the memory of others the North refrains from disparaging; and some, with more or less of reluctance, she can respect. Posterity, sympathizing with our convictions, but removed from our passions, may perhaps go farther here. If George IV. could, <ref target="#EDnoteSuppRN3">out of the graceful instinct of a gentleman,</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSuppRN3">In Copy C, Melville deleted "out of the graceful instinct of a gentleman" in pencil and added a printer's deletion symbol in the right margin.</note> raise an honorable monument in
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0270.jpg"/> the great fane of Christendom over the remains of the enemy of his dynasty, <ref target="#EDnoteSupp3">Charles Edward</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp3">Charles Edward Stuart (1720-1788), the Jacobite pretender to the British throne, known popularly as "Bonnie Prince Charlie," invaded England in 1745, achieved momentary victory at the battle of Prestonpans, but was defeated at Culloden in 1746. He lived in exile in Rome, where, in 1819, a posthumous monument commemorating him and the Stuart line was erected in a sconce in St. Peter's Basilica, in the Vatican (or what Melville calls the "great fane [i.e. shrine] of Christendom"). Despite the Jacobite insurrection against his own father and line, King George IV admired the Stuarts and supported construction of the Vatican memorial.</note>, the invader of England and victor in the rout at Preston Pans—upon whose head the king&apos;s ancestor but one reign removed has set a price—is it probable that the grandchildren of General Grant will pursue with rancor, or slur by sour neglect, the memory of Stonewall Jackson?
</p>

<p>But the South herself is not wanting in recent histories and biographies which record the deeds of her chieftains—writings freely published at the North by loyal houses, widely read here, and with a deep though saddened interest. By students of the war such works are hailed as welcome accessories, and tending to the completeness of the record.
</p>

<p>Supposing a happy issue out of present perplexities, then, in the generation next to come, Southerners there will be yielding allegiance to the Union, feeling all their interests bound up in it, and yet cherishing unrebuked that kind of feeling for the memory of the soldiers of the fallen Confederacy that <ref target="#EDnoteSupp4">Burns, Scott, and the Ettrick Shepherd</ref>
<note xml:id="EDnoteSupp4">Robert Burns (1759-1796), Walter Scott (1771-1832), and the "Ettrick Shepherd" James Hogg (1770-1835) were Scotland's principal poets and novelists, still popular in Melville's day. Melville argues that the sympathies for Scottish rebellion expressed in their writings were tempered by their respect for the valor of the soldiers fighting it and that this balancing of local resistance and universal honor did not undermine their loyalty to the British crown. The same balance, Melville projects, might pertain for future generations and writers of the American South. </note> felt for the memory of the
<ref target="#EDnoteSupp5">gallant clansmen</ref>
<note xml:id="EDnoteSupp5">These "clansmen" referred to belong to Scottish clans depicted, in particular, in the novels of Walter Scott. Though the American white supremacist "Ku Klux Klan" was officially founded in December 1865, its reign of terror did not emerge until after 1866.</note> ruined through their fidelity to the Stuarts—a feeling whose passion was tempered by the poetry imbuing it, and which in no wise affected their loyalty to the Georges, and which, it may be added, indirectly contributed excellent things to literature. But, setting
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0271.jpg"/> this view aside, dishonorable would it be in the South were she willing to abandon to shame the memory of brave men who with signal personal disinterestedness warred in her behalf, though from motives, as we believe, so deplorably astray.
</p>

<p>Patriotism is not baseness, neither is it inhumanity. The mourners who this summer bear flowers to the mounds of the Virginian and Georgian dead are, in their domestic bereavement and proud affection, as sacred in the eye of Heaven as are those who go with similar offerings of tender grief and love into the cemeteries of our Northern martyrs. And yet, in one aspect, how needless to point the contrast.
</p>

<p>Cherishing such sentiments, it will hardly occasion surprise that, in looking over the battle-pieces in the foregoing collection, I have been tempted to withdraw or modify some of them, fearful lest in presenting, though but dramatically and by way of a poetic record, the passions and epithets of civil war, I might be contributing to a bitterness which every sensible American must wish at an end. So, too, with the emotion of victory as reproduced on some pages, and particularly toward the close. It should not be construed into an exultation misapplied—an exultation as ungenerous as unwise, and made to minister, however indirectly, to that kind of censoriousness too apt to be produced in certain natures
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0272.jpg"/> by success after trying reverses. Zeal is not of necessity religion, neither is it always of the same essence with poetry or patriotism.
</p>

<p>There were excesses which marked the conflict, most of which are perhaps inseparable from a civil strife so intense and prolonged, and involving warfare in some border countries new and imperfectly civilized. Barbarities also there were, for which the Southern people collectively can hardly be held responsible, though perpetrated by ruffians in their name. But surely other qualities—exalted ones—courage and fortitude matchless, were likewise displayed, and largely; and justly may these be held the characteristic traits, and not the former.
</p>

<p>In this view, what Northern writer, however patriotic, but must revolt from acting on paper a part any way akin to that of the live dog to the dead lion; and yet it is right to rejoice for our triumph, so far as it may justly imply an advance for our whole country and for humanity.
</p>

<p>Let it be held no reproach to any one that he pleads for reasonable consideration for our late enemies, now stricken down and unavoidably debarred, for the time, from speaking through authorized agencies for themselves. Nothing has been urged here in the foolish hope of conciliating those men—few in number, we trust—who have resolved never to be reconciled to the
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0273.jpg"/> Union. On such hearts every thing is thrown away except it be religious commiseration, and the sincerest. Yet let them call to mind that <ref target="#EDnoteSupp6">unhappy Secessionist</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp6">Plantation owner, slave-holder, and agronomist Edmund Ruffin (1794-1865), too old to serve in the Confederate army, was allegedly the first to fire on Ft. Sumter and the first to enter the surrendered fort. He committed suicide in June 1865 at his son's home outside of Richmond, VA.</note>, not a military man, who with impious alacrity fired the first shot of the Civil War at Sumter, and a little more than four years afterward fired the last one into his own heart at Richmond.
</p>

<p>Noble was the gesture into which patriotic passion surprised the people in a utilitarian time and country; yet the glory of the war falls short of its pathos—a pathos which now at last ought to disarm all animosity.
</p>

<p>How many and earnest thoughts still rise, and how hard to repress them. We feel what past years have been, and years, unretarded years, shall come. May we all have moderation; may we all show candor. Though, perhaps, nothing could ultimately have averted the strife, and though to treat of human actions is to deal wholly with second causes, nevertheless, let us not cover up or try to extenuate what, humanly speaking, is the truth—namely, that those unfraternal denunciations, continued through years, and which at last inflamed to deeds that ended in bloodshed, were reciprocal; and that, had the preponderating strength and the prospect of its unlimited increase lain on the other side, on ours might have lain those actions which now in our late opponents we stigmatize under the name of Rebellion. As frankly <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0274.jpg"/> let us own—what it would be unbecoming to parade were foreigners concerned—that our triumph was won not more by skill and bravery than by superior resources and crushing numbers; that it was a triumph, too, over a people for years politically misled by designing men, and also by some honestly-erring men, who from their position could not have been otherwise than broadly influential; a people who, though indeed, they sought to perpetuate the curse of slavery, and even extend it, were not the authors of it, but (less fortunate, not less righteous than we) were the fated inheritors; a people who, having a like origin with ourselves, share essentially in whatever worthy qualities we may possess. No one can add to the lasting reproach which hopeless defeat has now cast upon Secession by withholding the recognition of these verities.
</p>

<p>Surely we ought to take it to heart that that kind of pacification, based upon principles operating equally all over the land, which lovers of their country yearn for, and which our arms, though signally triumphant, did not bring about, and which law-making, however anxious, or energetic, or repressive, never by itself can achieve, may yet be largely aided by generosity of sentiment public and private. Some revisionary legislation and adaptive is indispensable; but with this should harmoniously work another kind of prudence, not unallied <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0275.jpg"/> with entire magnanimity. Benevolence and policy—Christianity and Machiavelli—dissuade from penal severities toward the subdued. Abstinence here is as obligatory as considerate care for our unfortunate fellow-men late in bonds, and, if observed, would equally prove to be wise forecast. The great qualities of the South, those attested in the War, we can perilously alienate, or we may make them nationally available at need.
</p>

<p>The blacks, in their infant pupilage to freedom, appeal to the sympathies of every humane mind. The paternal guardianship which for the interval government exercises over them was prompted equally by duty and benevolence. Yet such kindliness should not be allowed to exclude kindliness to communities who stand nearer to us in nature. For the future of the freed slaves we may well be concerned; but the future of the whole country, involving the future of the blacks, urges a paramount claim upon our anxiety. Effective benignity, like the Nile, is not narrow in its bounty, and true policy is always broad. To be sure, it is vain to seek to glide, with moulded words, over the difficulties of the situation. And for them who are neither partisans, nor enthusiasts, nor theorists, nor cynics, there are some doubts not readily to be solved. And there are fears. Why is not the cessation of war now at length attended with the settled calm of peace?
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0276.jpg"/> Wherefore in a clear sky do we still turn our eyes toward the South, as the Neapolitan, months after the eruption, turns his toward <ref target="#EDnoteSupp7">Vesuvius</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp7">The volcano Vesuvius overlooking Naples was particularly active throughout the 19th century, with eight devastating eruptions during Melville's lifetime.</note>? Do we dread lest the repose may be deceptive? In the recent convulsion has the crater but shifted? Let us revere that sacred uncertainty which forever impends over men and nations. Those of us who always abhorred slavery as an atheistical iniquity, gladly we join in the exulting chorus of humanity over its downfall. But we should remember that emancipation was accomplished not by deliberate legislation; only through agonized violence could so mighty a result be effected. In our natural solicitude to confirm the benefit of liberty to the blacks, let us forbear from measures of dubious constitutional rightfulness toward our white countrymen—measures of a nature to provoke, among other of the last evils, exterminating hatred of race toward race. In imagination let us place ourselves in the unprecedented position of the Southerners—their position as regards the millions of ignorant manumitted slaves in their midst, for whom some of us now claim the suffrage. Let us be Christians toward our fellow-whites, as well as philanthropists toward the blacks our fellow-men. In all things, and toward all, we are enjoined to do as we would be done by. Nor should we forget that benevolent desires, after passing a certain point, can not un-
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0277.jpg"/>dertake their own fulfillment without incurring the risk of evils beyond those sought to be remedied. Something may well be left to the graduated care of future legislation, and to heaven. In one point of view the co-existence of the two races in the South—whether the negro be bond or free—seems (even as it did to Abraham Lincoln) a grave evil. Emancipation has ridded the country of the reproach, but not wholly of the calamity. Especially in the present transition period for both races in the South, more or less of trouble may not unreasonably be anticipated; but let us not hereafter be too swift to charge the blame exclusively in any one quarter. With certain evils men must be more or less patient. Our institutions have a potent digestion, and may in time convert and assimilate to good all elements thrown in, however originally alien.
</p>

<p>But, so far as immediate measures looking toward permanent Re-establishment are concerned, no consideration should tempt us to pervert the national victory into oppression for the vanquished. Should plausible promise of eventual good, or a deceptive or spurious sense of duty, lead us to essay this, count we must on serious consequences, not the least of which would be divisions among the Northern adherents of the Union. Assuredly, if any honest <ref target="#EDnoteSupp8">Catos</ref>
<note xml:id="EDnoteSupp8">Roman politician, stoic, and supportor of the Republic Marcus Porcius Cato (95 BCE-49 BCE) committed suicide rather than live under Julius Caesar's dictatorship.</note> there be who thus far have gone with us, no longer will they do so, but oppose us, and
<pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0278.jpg"/> as resolutely as hitherto they have supported. But this path of thought leads toward those waters of bitterness from which one can only turn aside and be silent.
</p>

<p>But supposing Re-establishment so far advanced that the Southern seats in Congress are occupied, and by men qualified in accordance with those cardinal principles of representative government which hitherto have prevailed in the land—what then? Why the Congressman elected by the people of the South will—represent the people of the South. This may seem a flat conclusion; but, in view of the last five years, may there not be latent significance in it? What will be the temper of those Southern members? and, confronted by them, what will be the mood of our own representatives? In private life true reconciliation seldom follows a violent quarrel; but, if subsequent intercourse be unavoidable, nice observances and mutual are indispensable to the prevention of a new rupture. Amity itelf can only be maintained by reciprocal respect, and true friends are punctilious equals. On the floor of Congress North and South are to come together after a passionate duel, in which the South though proving her valor, has been made to <ref target="#EDnoteSupp9">bite the dust</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp9">A common variant on Psalms 72: "They that dwell in the wilderness shall bow before him and his enemies shall lick the dust."</note>. Upon differences in debate shall acrimonious recriminations be exchanged? shall censorious superiority assumed by one section provoke defiant self-assertion on the other? shall <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0279.jpg"/> <ref target="#EDnoteSupp10">Manassas and Chickamauga be retorted for Chattanooga and Richmond</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp10">A pairing of two Confederate and two Union victories, respectively, each featured in <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi> poems.</note>? Under the supposition that the full Congress will be composed of gentlemen, all this is impossible. Yet if otherwise, it needs no prophet of Israel to foretell the end. The maintenance of Congressional decency in the future will rest mainly with the North. Rightly will more forbearance be required from the North than the South, for the North is victor.
</p>

<p>But some there are who may deem these latter thoughts inapplicable, and for this reason: Since the test-oath operatively excludes from Congress all who in any way participated in Secession, therefore none but Southerners wholly in harmony with the North are eligible to seats. This is true for the time being. But the oath is alterable; and in the wonted fluctuations of parties not improbably it will undergo alteration, assuming such a form, perhaps, as not to bar the admission into the National Legislature of men who represent the populations lately in revolt. Such a result would involve no violation of the principles of democratic government. Not readily can one perceive how the political existence of the millions of late Secessionists can permanently be ignored by this Republic. The years of the war tried our devotion to the Union; the time of peace may test the sincerity of our faith in democracy.
</p>

<p>In no spirit of opposition, not by way of challenge, <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v1/battle-pieces-i-0280.jpg"/> is any thing here thrown out. These thoughts are sincere ones; they seem natural—inevitable. Here and there they must have suggested themselves to many thoughtful patriots. And, if they be just thoughts, ere long they must have that weight with the public which already they have had with individuals.
</p>

<p>For that heroic band—those <ref target="#EDnoteSupp11">children of the furnace</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp11">In the Book of Daniel, Babylonian king Nebuchadnezzar requires his subjects to workship his image or suffer burning in a fiery furnace. Three Hebrew youths—Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego—refuse to bow down but are protected by an angel from the flames of the furnace.</note> who, in regions like Texas and Tennessee, maintained their fidelity through terrible trials—we of the North felt for them, and profoundly we honor them. Yet passionate sympathy, with resentments so close as to be almost domestic in their bitterness, would hardly in the present juncture tend to discreet legislation. Were the Unionists and Secessionists but as <ref target="#EDnoteSupp12">Guelphs and Ghibellines</ref><note xml:id="EDnoteSupp12">Warring factions in 12th and 13th-century northern Italian city-states, in support of the Pope and Holy Roman Emperor, respectively.</note>? If not, then far be it from a great nation now to act in the spirit that animated a triumphant town-faction in the Middle Ages. But crowding thoughts must at last be checked; and, in times like the present, one who desires to be impartially just in the expression of his views, moves as among sword-points presented on every side.
</p>

<p>Let us pray that the <ref target="#EDnoteSuppRN4">terrible</ref> <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v2/battle-pieces-ii-0282.jpg"/> <note xml:id="EDnoteSuppRN4">In Copy C, Melville underlined "terrible" in pencil and inscribed "great" in the left margin. The tentative revision to "great" is probably to remove a repetition of "terrible" in "terrible trials" found in the preceding paragraph.</note> historic tragedy of our time may not have been enacted without instructing our whole beloved country through terror and pity; and may fulfillment verify in the end those expectations which kindle the bards of Progress and Humanity.
<l rend="12em">&#xA0;&#xA0;THE END.</l>
</p>

</div>
</body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
