<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Front flyleaf 1 - Copy C</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>

            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
            <date/>
            <authority/>
            <availability><p/></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
        <lb/>
         <pb facs="/images/battle-pieces-v2/battle-pieces-ii-0005.jpg"/>
         <p><ref target="#EDnoteFlyLeaf1CopyCRN1">"Revised" sheets - with <lb/> Herman's corrections -</ref>
       <note xml:id="EDnoteFlyLeaf1CopyCRN1"><p>REVISION NARRATIVE: In a common practice in Melville's day, publishers would issue unbound "sheets" of a book, permitting purchasers to arrange for their own personal bindings. In addition, publishers would issue bound copies with their own bindings. Melville's publisher, Harper and Brothers, sent the author a set of unbound sheets, which he read thoroughly, adding penciled inscriptions throughout. This early interaction with his own post-publication text is known as "Copy C." Harpers also sent Melville their own bound copy of <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi>, the volume known as "Copy A," which also contains Melville's penciled inscriptions. Both copies are located at Houghton Libray, Harvard College.</p>
     <p>Here, Elizabeth Shaw Melville's undated pencil inscription on what MEL designates as flyleaf 1 in Copy C identifies Copy C as "'Revised' sheets" and specifies the penciled inscriptions therein as "Herman's corrections." ESM's wording, while probably not intended to do so, raises questions about the nature of Melville's marginal inscriptions. "Revised" suggests new wording reflecting changes of mind; whereas "corrections" suggests that Melville found and fixed typos or other misprintings and therefore indicates a return of the text to an originally intended wording or meaning.</p>
     <p>ESM's wording on flyleaf 1 also resonates different approaches in scholarly editing. Traditional textual editing focuses on achieving a reading text that represents the editors' conception of some single moment in the author's intentions. Following that principle, editors may decide to add revisions and/or corrections into their reading text of the work, thereby mixing texts from distinctly different physical versions of the work. However, MEL's fluid-text approach emphasizes a writer's shifting, oscillating, and evolving intentions, and, therefore, employs protocols that sustain the integrity of each physical version's texts rather than mixing them together. Melville's pencilings help demonstrate the difference between traditional and fluid-text editorial approaches. On the one hand, the NN "eclectic" edition of <hi rend="italic">Battle-Pieces</hi> incorporates not all but selected revisions from Copies A and C into their reading text. However, in MEL's fluid-text digital edition, we reproduce the same print text found in both copies and provide (in the form of pop-up notes) "Revision Narratives" that explain Melville's penciled inscriptions in both copies A and C. In addition, MEL's side-by-side display of Copies A and C enables readers to view Melville's pencilings as they appear in the context of each copy. Pages with pencilings are indicated with asterisks in the "Jump to" selection boxes beneath each copy in the display.
    </p> </note></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
