<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="3">
                <pb facs="#f002"/>
                <p>unpopular merit, that <lb/>amid the thick stir of other things, the hint of<lb/> my tasteful
                    friend was disregarded; and for<lb/> four years the Mosses on the Old Manse
                    never<lb/> refreshed me with their perennial green. It<lb/> may be, however,
                    that all this while the book,<lb/> likewise, was only improving in flavor
                    and<lb/> body. At any rate, it so chanced that this<lb/> long procrastination
                    eventuated in a happy re-<lb/>sult. At breakfast the other day, a mountain<lb/>
                    girl, a cousin of mine, who for the last two<lb/> weeks has every morning helped
                    me to straw-<lb/>berries and raspberries, which, like the roses<lb/> and pearls
                    in the fairy tale, seemed to fall into<lb/> the saucer from those
                    strawberry-beds, her<lb/> cheeks--this delightful creature, this charming<lb/>
                    Cherry says to me-- "I see you spend your<lb/> mornings in the haymow; and
                    yesterday I<lb/> found there 'Dwight's Travels in New En-<lb/>gland.' Now I have
                    something far better than<lb/> that, something more congenial to our summer<lb/>
                    on these hills. Take these raspberries, and<lb/> then I will give you some
                    moss." "Moss!"<lb/> said I. "Yes, and you must take it to the<lb/> barn with you, and good-by to 'Dwight' ".</p>
                <p>With that she left me, and soon returned<lb/> with a volume, verdantly bound, and
                    garnished<lb/> with a curious frontispiece in green; nothing<lb/> less than a
                    fragment of real moss cunningly pressed to a fly-leaf. "Why this," said I<lb/>
                    spilling my raspberries, "this is the 'Mosses<lb/> from an Old Manse.'" "Yes"
                    said cousin<lb/> Cherry, "yes, it is that flowery Hawthorne."<lb/> "Hawthorne
                    and Mosses," said I ,"no more:<lb/> it is morning: it is July in the country: and I</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>