<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<text>
		<body>
			<p><pb facs="#f003"/> <metamark>3</metamark></p>
			<p>am off for the barn".</p>
			<p>Stretched on that new mown clover, <lb/> <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-with" hand="metadata#HM">with</del> the hill-side breeze blowing over me <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-from" hand="metadata#HM">from</del> <lb/> through the wide barn door, and soothed by the hum of the <lb/> bees in the meadows around, how magically <lb/> stole over me this Mossy Man! And how amply, <lb/> how bountifully, did he redeem that delicious <lb/> promise to his guests in the Old Manse, of whom <lb/> it is written-- "Others could give them pleasure, <lb/> " <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-and" hand="metadata#HM">and</del> <metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" hand="metadata#HM" place="above">or</add> amusement, or instruction--these could be <lb/> " picked up anywhere--but it was for me to <lb/> " give them rest. Rest, in a life of trouble! What <lb/> " better could be done for <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-these" hand="metadata#HM">those</del> weary and <lb/> " world-worn spirits? what better could be done <lb/> " for anybody, who came within our magic <lb/> " circle, than to throw the spell of a magic spirit <lb/> " over him,"-- So all that day, <metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_add-half-" hand="metadata#HM" place="above">half-</add>buried in the <lb/> new clover <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_delete-ofthehalf" hand="metadata#HM">of the half-buried</del>, I watched this Hawthorne's <lb/> "Assyrian dawn, and Paphian sunset and moon-<lb/> rise, from the summit of our Eastern Hill."</p>
			<p>The soft ravishments of the man spun me round <lb/> about in a web of dreams, and when the book was <lb/> dosed, when the spell was over, this wizard <lb/> "dismissed me with but misty reminiscences, as if <lb/> I had been dreaming of him."</p>
			<p>What a mild moonlight of contemplative <lb/>humor bathes that Old Manse!--the rich and <lb/> rare distilment of a spicy and slowly-oozing heart. <lb/> No rollicking <metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f003_add-rudeness," hand="metadata#HM" place="above">rudeness</add>, no gross fun fed on fat dinners, <lb/> and bred in the lees of wine,--but a humor <lb/> so spiritually gentle, so high, so deep, and yet</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>