<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="5">
                <pb facs="#f004"/>
                <p>so richly relishable, that<lb/> it were hardly inappropriate in an angel. It<lb/>
                    is the very religion of mirth; for nothing so<lb/> human but it may be advanced
                    to that. The<lb/> orchard of the Old Manse seems the visible<lb/> type of the
                    fine mind that has described it.--<lb/> those twisted and contorted old trees,
                    "that<lb/> stretch out their crooked branches, and take such hold of the
                    imagination, that we remem-<lb/>ber them as humorists and odd-fellows."<lb/> And
                    then, as surrounded by these grotesque<lb/> forms, and hushed in the noon-day
                    repose of<lb/> this Hawthorne's spell, how aptly might the<lb/> still fall of
                    his ruddy thoughts into your soul<lb/> be symbolized by "the thump of a
                    great<lb/> apple, in the stillest afternoon, falling without<lb/> a breath of
                    wind, from the mere necessity of<lb/> perfect ripeness!" For no less ripe
                    than<lb/> ruddy are the apples of the thoughts and fancies<lb/> in this sweet
                    Man of Mosses.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="align(center)"> "Buds and Bird-voices"--</hi><lb/> What a
                    delicious thing is that! "Will the<lb/> world ever be so decayed, that Spring
                    may not<lb/> renew its greenness?" And the "Fire-<lb/>Worship." Was ever the
                    hearth so glorified<lb/> into an altar before? The mere title of that<lb/> piece
                    is better than any common work in fifty<lb/> folio volumes. How exquisite is
                    this:-- "Nor<lb/> did it lessen the charm of his soft, familiar<lb/> courtesy
                    and helpfulness, that the mighty<lb/> spirit, were opportunity offered him,
                    would<lb/> run riot through the peaceful house, wrap its<lb/> inmates in his
                    terrible embrace, and leave<lb/> nothing of them save their whitened</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
