<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<p><pb facs="#f005"/> <metamark>6</metamark></p>
				<p>bones. This possibility of mad destruction only <lb/> made his domestic kindness the more beautiful <lb/> and touching. It was so sweet of him, being <lb/> endowed with such power, to dwell, day after <lb/> day, and one long, lonesome night after <lb/> another, on the dusky hearth, only now and then <lb/> betraying his wild nature, by thrusting his <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-wild" hand="metadata#HM">wild</del> <lb/> red tongue out of the chimney-top! True, he had <lb/> done much mischief in the world, and was <lb/> pretty certain to do more, but his warm heart <lb/> atoned for all; He was kindly to the race of man."</p>
				<p>But he has still other apples, <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-all" hand="metadata#HM">all</del> not <lb/> quite so ruddy, though full as ripe;-- apples, that <lb/> have been left to wither on the tree, after the <lb/> pleasant autumn gathering is past. The <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-j" hand="metadata#HM">Thelth?</del> <lb/> sketch of "the Old Apple Dealer is conceived in <lb/> the subtlest spirit of sadness; he whose "subdued <lb/> and nerveless boyhood prefigured his abortive <lb/> prime, which, likewise, contained within itself <lb/> the prophecy and image of his lean and torpid <lb/> age." Such <metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_add-touches" hand="metadata#HM" place="above">touches</add> <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-tones" hand="metadata#HM">tones</del> as are in this piece can not <lb/> proceed from any common heart. They argue <lb/> such a depth of tenderness, such a boundless sym<lb/>-pathy with all forms of being, such an omni-<lb/>present love, that we must needs say, that this <lb/> Hawthorne is here almost alone in <metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_add-his" hand="metadata#HM" place="above">his</add> <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-his" hand="metadata#HM">his</del> generation, <lb/> --at least, in the artistic manifestation of these <lb/> things. Still <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-more" hand="metadata#HM">more</del> more. Such <metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_add-touches" hand="metadata#HM" place="above">touches</add> <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-words" hand="metadata#HM">words</del> as these, <lb/> -- and many, very many <metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_add-similarones" hand="metadata#HM" place="above">similar ones</add> <del change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_delete-more2" hand="metadata#HM">more</del>, all through his <lb/> chapters<metamark>^</metamark><add change="metadata#StB" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f005_add---" hand="metadata#HM" place="above">--</add>furnish clews, whereby we enter a</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>