<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="8">
                <pb facs="#f007"/>
                <p>"Methinks I should tremble now, were his<lb/> wizard power of gliding through all
                    impedi-<lb/>ments in search of me, to place him suddenly<lb/> before my eyes".</p>
                <p> How profound, nay appalling, is the moral<lb/> evolved by the Earth's Holocaust;
                    where--<lb/>beginning with the hollow follies and affect-<lb/>ations of the world,--all
                    vanities and empty<lb/> theories and forms are, one after another, and<lb/> by an
                    admirably graduated, growing compre-<lb/>hensiveness, thrown into the allegorical
                    fire,<lb/> till, at length, nothing is left but the all-<lb/>engendering heart of man;
                    which remaining<lb/> still unconsumed, the great conflagration is<lb/> nought.</p>
                <p> Of a piece with this, is the "Intelligence<lb/> Office," a wondrous symbolizing of
                    the secret<lb/> workings in men's souls. There are other<lb/> sketches, still more charged
                    with ponderous<lb/> import.</p>
                <p>"The Christmas Banquet," and "The<lb/> Bosom Serpent" would be fine subjects for a<lb/>
                    curious and elaborate analysis, touching the<lb/> conjectural parts of the mind that
                    produced<lb/> them. For spite of all the Indian-summer<lb/> sunlight on the hither side of
                    Hawthorne's<lb/> soul, the other side--like the dark half of the<lb/> physical sphere--is
                    shrouded in a blackness,<lb/> ten times black. But this darkness but gives<lb/> more
                    effect to the ever-moving dawn, that<lb/> forever advances through it, and
                    circumnavi-<lb/>gates his world. Whether Hawthorne has<lb/> simply availed himself of this
                    mystical<lb/> blackness as a means to the wondrous effects he<lb/> makes it to produce in
                    his lights and shades;<lb/> or whether there really lurks in him, perhaps<lb/> unknown to
                    himself, a touch of Puritanic<lb/> gloom,--this, I cannot</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
