<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="leaf">
            <p>
               <pb facs="#f009"/>
            </p>
            <p>largely developed in him. Perhaps he does<lb/>not give us a ray of his light for every shade <lb/>of his <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">dark.</hi> But however this may be, this <lb/>blackness it is that furnishes the infinite obscure <lb/>of his back-ground,-- that back-ground, against<lb/> which Shakespeare plays his grandest conceits, <lb/>the things that have made for Shakespeare <lb/>his <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">loftiest, but most circumscribed</hi> renown, as the <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">profoundest</hi>
               <lb/>of thinkers. For by philosophers Shakespeare is <lb/>not <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">adored</hi> as the great man of tragedy and <lb/>comedy.--"Off with his head! so much for <lb/>Buckingham!" this sort of rant, <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">interlined</hi>
               <lb/> by <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">an</hi>other hand, bring<hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">s</hi> down the house,--those <lb/>mistaken souls, who dream of Shakespeare <lb/>as a <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">mere</hi> man of Richard-the-Third humps, and <lb/>Macbeth daggers. But it is those deep <lb/>
               <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">far-away</hi> things in him; those occasional flashings-forth of <lb/>the intuitive Truth in him; those short, <lb/>quick probings <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">at</hi> the very axis of reality:-- these <lb/>are the things that make Shakespeare, Shakes-<lb/>peare. Through the <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">mouths</hi> of the dark charac-<lb/>ters of Hamlet, Timon, Lear, and Iago, he <lb/>craftily says, <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">or </hi>
               <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">sometimes</hi>
               <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"> insinuates</hi> the things, <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">which</hi> we feel to be so <lb/>terrifically true, that it were all but mad-<lb/>ness for any good man, in his own proper<lb/>character, to utter, or even hint of them. <lb/>
               <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">Tormented</hi> into desperation, Lear the frantic King <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">tears off the mask,</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi xmlns="" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">&amp;</hi> speaks the sane madness of vital truth. <lb/>But, as I before said, it is the least part of <lb/>genius that attracts admiration. And so, </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>