<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="10">
                <pb facs="#f009"/>
                <p>largely developed in him. Perhaps he<lb/> does not give us a ray of his light for
                    every<lb/> shade of his dark. But however this may be,<lb/> this blackness it is
                    that furnishes the infinite<lb/> obscure of his background,--that
                    back-<lb/>ground, against which Shakspeare plays his<lb/> grandest conceits,
                    the things that have made for<lb/> Shakspeare his loftiest, but most
                    circumscribed<lb/> renown, as the profoundest of thinkers. For<lb/> by
                    philosophers Shakspeare is not adored as the<lb/> great man of tragedy and
                    comedy.-- "Off with<lb/> his head! so much for Buckingham!" This<lb/> sort of
                    rant, interlined by another hand, brings<lb/> down the house,--those mistaken
                    souls, who<lb/> dream of Shakspeare as a mere man of<lb/> Richard-the-Third
                    humps, and Macbeth dag-<lb/>gers. But it is those deep far-away things in<lb/>
                    him; those occasional flashings-forth of the<lb/>intuitive Truth in him; those
                    short, quick probings at the very axis of reality;--these<lb/> are the things
                    that make Shakspeare, Shak-<lb/>speare. Through the mouths of the dark<lb/>
                    characters of Hamlet, Timon, Lear, and Iago,<lb/> he craftily says, or sometimes
                    insinuates the<lb/> things, which we feel to be so terrifically true,<lb/> that
                    it were all but madness for any good man,<lb/> in his own proper character, to
                    utter, or even<lb/> hint of them. Tormented into desperation,<lb/> Lear the
                    frantic King tears off the mask, and<lb/> speaks the same madness of vital
                    truth. But,<lb/> as I before said, it is the least part of genius<lb/> that
                    attracts admiration. And so, </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
