<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="11">
                <pb facs="#f010"/>
                <p> much of the<lb/> blind, unbridled admiration that has been heap-<lb/>ed upon
                    Shakespeare, has been lavished upon<lb/> the least part of him. And few of his
                    endless<lb/> commentators and critics seem to have re-<lb/>membered, or even
                    perceived, that the immedi-<lb/>ate products of a great mind are not so
                    great,<lb/> as that undeveloped, and sometimes undeve-<lb/>lopable yet
                    dimly-discernable greatness, to<lb/> which these immediate products are but the
                    in-<lb/>fallible indices. In Shakespeare's tomb lies in-<lb/>finitely more than
                    Shakespeare ever wrote.<lb/> And if I magnify Shakespeare, it is not so<lb/>
                    much for what he did do, as for what he did<lb/> not do, or refrained from
                    doing. For in this<lb/> world of lies, Truth is forced to fly like a<lb/> scared
                    white doe in the woodlands; and only<lb/> by cunning glimpses will she reveal
                    herself, as<lb/> in Shakespeare and other masters of the great<lb/> Art of
                    Telling the Truth,--even though it be<lb/> covertly, and by snatches.</p>
                <p>But if this view of the all-popular Shak-<lb/>espeare be seldom taken by his
                    readers, and if<lb/> very few who extol him have ever read him<lb/> deeply, or,
                    perhaps, only have seen him on the<lb/> tricky stage, (which alone made, and is
                    still<lb/> making him his mere mob renown)--if few<lb/> men have time, or
                    patience, or palate, for the<lb/> spiritual truth as it is in that great
                    genius;--<lb/>it is, then, no matter of surprise that in a con-<lb/>temporaneous
                    age, Nathaniel Hawthorne is a<cb/> man as yet almost utterly mistaken among<lb/>
                    men. Here and there, in some quiet arm-<lb/> chair in the noisy town, or some
                    deep nook<lb/> among the noiseless mountains, he may be ap-<lb/>preciated for
                    something of what he is.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
