<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="leaf">
            <p>
               <pb facs="#f010"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">much of the blind, unbridled</hi> admiration that has been heaped <lb/>upon Shakespeare, has been lavished upon the <lb/> least part of him. And few of his endless <lb/> commentators &amp; critics seem to have <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">remembered,</hi>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">or even</hi>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>that the immediate products of a great mind <lb/> are not so great, as that undeveloped, <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">(&amp; sometimes undevelopable)</hi> yet <lb/> dimly-discern<hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">able</hi> greatness, to which <lb/>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">these immediate products</hi> are but the infallible indices. In Shakespeare's <lb/> tomb lies infinitely more than <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">Shakspeare</hi> ever wrote. <lb/> And if I magnify Shakespeare, it is not so much <lb/> for what he did<hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">do,</hi> as for what he did not <lb/> do<hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">or refrained from doing.</hi> For in this world of lies, Truth is <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">forced</hi> to <lb/> fly like a scared white doe in the woodlands; <lb/> and only by cunning glimpses will she reveal <lb/> herself, as in Shakespeare and other <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">masters</hi> of <lb/> the great <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">Art</hi> of Telling the Truth<hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">,--</hi>even though <lb/> it be covertly, and by snatches.</p>
            <p>      But <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">if</hi> this view of the all-popular <lb/>   Shakspeare <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">be</hi> seldom taken by his readers, and if very <lb/> few who extol him, have ever read him deeply,<lb/>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">or, perhaps,</hi> only have seen him on the tricky stage<hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">, (</hi>which <lb/> alone made, and is still making him his mere <lb/> mob renown<hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">) --</hi> if few men have time, or patience, <lb/> or palate <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">,</hi> for the spiritual truth as it is in <lb/>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">that</hi> great genius; -- it is<hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">then,</hi> no matter of surprise <lb/> that <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">in a contemporaneous age</hi>, Nathaniel Hawthorne is a man, <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">as yet, almost</hi> utterly <lb/>mistaken among men. Here &amp; there, in some <lb/>quiet arm-chair in the noisy town, or some <lb/>deep nook among the <hi  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">noisless</hi> mountains, he may <lb/>be appreciated for something of what he is.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>