<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="12">
                <pb facs="#f011"/>

                <p>But <lb/>unlike Shakspeare, who was forced to the <lb/>contrary course by
                    circumstances, Hawthorne<lb/> (either from simple disinclination, or else
                    <lb/>from inaptitude) refrains from all the popular-<lb/>izing noise and show of
                    broad farce and <lb/>blood-besmeared tragedy; content with the<lb/> still, rich
                    utterances of a great intellect in re-<lb/>pose, and which sends few thoughts
                    into circu-<lb/>lation, except they be arterialized at his large<lb/> warm
                    lungs, and expanded in his honest heart.</p>
                <p>Nor need you fix upon that blackness in <lb/>him, if it suit you not. Nor,
                    indeed, will all<lb/> readers discern it; for it is, mostly, insinuated<lb/> to
                    those who may best understand it, and ac-<lb/>count for it; it is not obtruded
                    upon every one<lb/> alike.</p>
                <p> Some may start to read of Shakspeare and <lb/>Hawthorne on the same page. They
                    may say, <lb/>that if an illustration were needed, a lesser <lb/>light might
                    have sufficed to elucidate this Haw-<lb/>thorne, this small man of yesterday.
                    But I <lb/>am not willingly one of those who, as touching <lb/>Shakespeare at
                    least, exemplify the maxim of <lb/>Rochefoucault, that "we exalt the reputation
                    <lb/>of some, in order to depress that of others";-<lb/>who, to teach all
                    noble-souled aspirants that <lb/>there is no hope for them, pronounce
                    Shak-<lb/>speare absolutely unapproachable. But Shak-<lb/>speare has been
                    approached. There are minds <lb/>that have gone as far as Shakspeare into the
                    <lb/>universe. And hardly a mortal man, who, at <lb/>some time or other, has not
                    felt as great <lb/>thoughts in him as any you will find in Ham-<lb/>let. We must
                    not inferentially malign man-<lb/>kind</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
