<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="13">
                <pb facs="#f012"/>
                <p>for the sake of any one man, whoever he <lb/>may be. This is too cheap a purchase
                    of con-<lb/>tentment for conscious mediocrity to make. <lb/>Besides, this
                    absolute and unconditional adora-<lb/>tion of Shakspeare has grown to be a
                    <lb/>part of our Anglo Saxon superstitions. <lb/>The Thirty-Nine articles are
                    now Forty. <lb/>Intolerance has come to exist in this matter. <lb/>You must
                    believe in Shakspeare's unapproach-<lb/>ability, or quit the country. But what
                    sort of <lb/>a belief is this for an American, a man who is <lb/>bound to carry
                    republican progressiveness into <lb/>Literature as well as into Life? Believe
                    me, <lb/>my friends, that men, not very much inferior <lb/>to Shakspeare, are
                    this day being born on the <lb/>banks of the Ohio. And the day will come<lb/>
                    when you shall say, Who reads a book by an <lb/>Englishman that is a modern? The
                    great<lb/> mistake seems to be, that even with those <lb/>Americans who look
                    forward to the coming of <lb/>a great literary genius among us, they
                    some-<lb/>how fancy he will come in the costume of <lb/>Queen Elizabeth's day,
                    be a writer of dramas <lb/>founded upon old English history or the tales <lb/>of
                    Boccaccio. Whereas, great geniuses are <lb/>parts of the times, they themselves
                    are the <lb/>times, and possess a correspondent coloring. <lb/>It is of a piece
                    with the Jews, who, while their <lb/>Shiloh was meekly walking in their
                    streets,<lb/> were still praying for his magnificent coming; <lb/>looking for
                    him in a chariot, who was already <lb/>among them on an ass. Nor must we
                    forget<lb/> that, in his own life-time, Shakspeare was</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
