<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="leaf">
            <p>
               <pb facs="#f012"/>
            </p>
            <p>for the sake of any one man, whoever he <lb/>may be. This is too cheap a purchase of contentment <lb/>for conscious mediocrity to make. Besides, <lb/>this absolute and unconditional adoration of <lb/>Shakespeare has grown to be a part of our <lb/>Anglo Saxon superstition<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">s</hi>. The <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">T</hi>hirty <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">N</hi>ine articles are <lb/>now <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">F</hi>orty. Intolerance has come to exist in <lb/>this matter. <note facs="#f012_z007" resp="#comp" type="compositorial">Lyman</note> You must believe in Shakespeare<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">'s</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">unapproachability,</hi> or <lb/>quit the country. But what sort of a belief <lb/>is this for an American, a man who is bound <lb/>to carry republican progress<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">-iveness</hi> into <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">L</hi>itera-<lb/>ture, as well as into <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">L</hi>ife? Believe me, my <lb/>friends, that <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">
                  <hi rend="bold">men</hi> not very much inferior to</hi> Shakespeare<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">,</hi> are this day being born <lb/>on the banks of the Ohio. And the day will <lb/> come, when you shall<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/> say who reads a book <lb/>by an Englishman<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">that is a modern?</hi>     The great mistake <lb/>seems to be, that even with those Americans <lb/>who look forward <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">to</hi> the coming of a <lb/>great <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">literary</hi> genius among us, they somehow fancy he <lb/>will come in the costume of Queen Elizabeth's <lb/>day,-- be a writer of dramas founded upon <lb/>old English history, or the tales of Boccaccio. <lb/>Whereas, great geniuses are part<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">s</hi> of the times; <lb/>they themselves are the times; and possess a <lb/>correspondent coloring. It is of a <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">piece</hi> with <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">t</hi>he Jews, who <lb/>while their Shiloh was meekly walking in <lb/>their streets, were still praying for his magnifi-<lb/>cent coming; looking for him in a chariot, who <lb/>was already among them on an ass. Nor must we <lb/>forget, that, in his own life-time, Shakespeare was</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>