<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="leaf" n="14">
            <pb facs="#f013"/>
            <p>not Shakespeare, but only Master William Shakespeare <lb/> of the shrewd, thriving,<note/>
               business firm of Condell, Shakespeare &amp; <corr change="#StE" facs="#f013_z007">Co.</corr>, proprietors <lb/> of the Globe Theatre in
               London; <reg change="metatdata#StE" facs="#f013_z008">&amp; </reg>by a  courtly author, <lb/> of
               the name of Chettle, was hooted at, as an <quote change="#readingNH"
                  facs="#f013_z004 #f013_z005 #f013_z006"
                  source="Shakespeare Volume 1">"upstart <lb/> crow" beautified "with
                  other birds' feathers."</quote>
               <note facs="#f013_z004 #f013_z005 #f013_z006">The quote
                  from <hi rend="italic">Greene's Groats-worth of Witte</hi>, slightly misquoted here, was marked
                  on p. xv of volume I of Meville's <hi rend="italic">Dramatic Works of William Shakespeare</hi>: "for there is an upstart crow, beautified with our feathers, that, with his tiger's heart wrapped in a player's hide, supposes he is as well able to bombast out a blank verse as the best of you...". The NN edition claimed that the
                  <hi rend="italic">Literary World</hi> retained both "errors" in its printing, but in fact "Groats-worth" was entered in the Stationers' Register 'upon the peril of Henry Chettle' on 20 September 1592, two and a half weeks after Greene's death on 3 September. On the page that Melville marked, Chettle is also mentioned as the publisher. As Chettle arranged for the book to be published, some have claimed that he authored the book, so Melville's claim is not quite an error. MEL therefore retains his original wording.</note>For, mark it
               well, <lb/> imitation is often the first charge brought against real <lb/>
               originality. Why this is so, there is not space to set forth here. You must
               <lb/> have plenty of sea-room to tell the <lb/>
               Truth<note>HM modified "truth" to be upper case</note> in; especially, when it seems to have an aspect
               <lb/> of newness, as America did in 1492, <reg change="#StE" facs="#f013_z010">tho'</reg> it was then <lb/> just as old, and perhaps
               older than Asia, only <lb/>
               those<note/> sagacious philosophers, the common sailors, had
               never <lb/> seen it before;
               swearing it was all water and moonshine <lb/> there. (to be
               concluded next week)<note>Added by Duyckinck...</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
