<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf" n="21">
                <pb facs="#f020"/>
                <p>And by confessing <lb/>him, you thereby confess others; you brace <lb/>the whole
                    brotherhood. For genius, all over <lb/>the world, stands hand in hand, and one
                    shock <lb/>of recognition runs the whole circle round.</p>
                <p>In treating of Hawthorne, or rather of Haw-<lb/>thorne in his writings (for I
                    never saw the <lb/>man; and in the chances of a quiet plantation <lb/>life,
                    remote from his haunts, perhaps never <lb/>shall); in treating of his works, I
                    say, I have <lb/>thus far omitted all mention of his "Twice <lb/>Told Tales",
                    and "Scarlet Letter." Both are <lb/>excellent; but full of such manifold,
                    strange <lb/>and diffusive beauties, that time would all but <lb/>fail me, to
                    point the half of them out. But <lb/>there are things in those two books, which,
                    <lb/>had they been written in England a century <lb/>ago, Nathaniel Hawthorne
                    had utterly dis-<lb/>placed many of the bright names we now <lb/>revere on
                    authority. But I am content to <lb/>leave Hawthorne to himself, and to the
                    infalli-<lb/>ble finding of posterity; and however great <lb/>may be the praise
                    I have bestowed upon him, <lb/>I feel, that in so doing, I have more served and
                    <lb/>honored myself, than him. For, at bottom, <lb/>great excellence is praise
                    enough to itself; but <lb/>the feeling of a sincere and appreciative love
                    <lb/>and admiration towards it, this is relieved by <lb/>utterance; and warm,
                    honest praise, ever <lb/>leaves a pleasant flavor in the mouth; and <lb/>it is
                    an honorable thing to confess to what is <lb/>honorable in others.</p>
                <p>But I cannot leave my subject yet. No man <lb/>can read a fine author, and relish
                    him to his <lb/>very bones while he reads, without</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
