<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f022"/>
                <p>is better than to be in <lb/>at the harvest of others. To be frank (though,
                    <lb/>perhaps, rather foolish) notwithstanding what <lb/>I wrote yesterday of
                    these Mosses, I had not <lb/>then culled them all; but had, nevertheless,
                    <lb/>been sufficiently sensible of the subtle essence <lb/>in them, as to write
                    as I did. To what infinite <lb/>height of loving wonder and admiration I may
                    <lb/>yet be borne, when by repeatedly banquetting <lb/>on these Mosses, I shall
                    have thoroughly in-<lb/>corporated their whole stuff into my being,--<lb/>that,
                    I can not tell. But already I feel that this Hawthorne <lb/>has dropped
                    germinous seeds into <lb/>my soul. He expands and deepens down, the <lb/>more I
                    contemplate him; and further and <lb/>further, shoots his strong New England
                    roots <lb/>into the hot soil of my Southern soul.</p>
                <p>By careful reference to the "Table of Con-<lb/>tents," I now find, that I have
                    gone through all <lb/>the sketches; but that when I yesterday wrote, <lb/>I had
                    not at all read two particular pieces, to <lb/>which I now desire to call
                    special attention,--<lb/>"A Select Party," and "Young Goodman <lb/>Brown." Here,
                    be it said to all those whom <lb/>this poor fugitive scrawl of mine may tempt
                    <lb/>to the perusal of the "Mosses," that they must <lb/>on no account suffer
                    themselves to be trifled <lb/>with, disappointed, or deceived by the triviality
                    <lb/>of many of the titles to these sketches. For<lb/> in more than one
                    instance, the title utterly be-<lb/>lies the piece. It is as if rustic demijohns
                    con-<lb/>taining the very best and costliest of Faler-<lb/>nian and Tokay, were
                    labelled "Cider,"<lb/> "Perry," and "Elderberry wine." The truth <lb/>seems to
                    be, that like many other geniuses, this <lb/>Man of Mosses takes great delight
                    in hood-<lb/>winking the world,--at least, with respect to <lb/>himself.
                    Personally, I doubt not, that he <lb/>rather prefers to be generally esteemed
                    but a <lb/>so-so sort of author; being willing to</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
