<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f023"/>
                <p>reserve <lb/>the thorough and acute appreciation of what he <lb/>is, to that
                    party most qualified to judge--that <lb/>is, to himself. Besides, at the bottom
                    of their <lb/>natures, men like Hawthorne, in many things, <lb/>deem the
                    plaudits of the public such strong <lb/>presumptive evidence of mediocrity in
                    the ob-<lb/>ject of them, that it would in some degree ren-<lb/>der them
                    doubtful of their own powers, did <lb/>they hear much and vociferous braying
                    con-<lb/>cerning them in the public pastures. True, I <lb/>have been braying
                    myself (if you please to be <lb/>witty enough, to have it so), but then I claim
                    <lb/>to be the first that has so brayed in this parti-<lb/>cular matter; and
                    therefore, while pleading <lb/>guilty to the charge still claim all the merit
                    <lb/>due to originality.</p>
                <p>But with whatever motive, playful or pro-<lb/>found, Nathaniel Hawthorne has
                    chosen to en-<lb/>title his pieces in the manner he has, it is cer-<lb/>tain,
                    that some of them are directly calculated <lb/>to deceive-- egregiously deceive,
                    the superfi-<lb/>cial skimmer of pages. To be downright and <lb/>candid once
                    more, let me cheerfully say, that <lb/>two of these titles did dolefully dupe no
                    less <lb/>an eagle-eyed reader than myself; and that, <lb/>too, after I had been
                    impressed with a sense of <lb/>the great depth and breadth of this American
                    <lb/>man. "Who in the name of thunder" (as the <lb/>country- people say in this
                    neighborhood),<lb/> "who in the name of thunder, would antici-<lb/>pate any
                    marvel in a piece entitled 'Young<lb/> Goodman Brown?'" You would of course
                    <lb/>suppose that it was a simple little tale, intend-<lb/>ed as a supplement to
                    "Goody Two Shoes." <lb/>Whereas, it is deep as Dante; nor can you <lb/>finish
                    it, without addressing the author in his <lb/>own words--"It is yours to
                    penetrate, in every <lb/>bosom, the deep mystery of sin". And with<lb/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
