<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="leaf">
				<p>
					<pb facs="#f023"/>
					<metamark change="#StE" facs="#f023_z008" function="folio" n="22" place="margin top">folio number "22"</metamark>
				</p>
				<p>reserve the thorough and acute appreciation of what<lb/> he is, to that party most qualified to judge--that is, <del change="#StC" facs="#f023_z007" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">to</del><lb/><add change="#StC" facs="#f023_z006" hand="#HM" place="margin" rend="no_caret">to </add><del change="#StC" facs="#f023_z005" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">say </del>himself. Besides, at the bottom of their natures, men<lb/> like Hawthorne, in many things, deem the plaudits of<lb/> the public such strong presumptive evidence of mediocrity<lb/> in the object of them, that it would in some degree<lb/> render them doubtful of their own powers, did they<lb/> hear much and vociferous braying concerning them in<lb/> the public pastures. True, I have been braying myself<lb/> (if you please to be witty enough, to have it so) but<lb/> then I claim to be the first that has so brayed in<lb/> this particular <del change="#StC" facs="#f023_z004" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">matter </del>matter; and therefore, while<lb/> pleading guilty to the charge<metamark change="#StC" facs="#f023_z003" function="caret" place="below" rend="caret">deleted caret</metamark> <add change="#StC" facs="#f023_z001" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret"><del change="#StC" facs="#f023_z001" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">of braying,</del></add> still claim all the merit due to originality.<lb/></p>
				<p>But with whatever motive, playful or profound,<lb/> Nathaniel Hawthorne has chosen to entitle his pieces<lb/> in the manner he has, it is certain, that some of them<lb/> are directly calculated to deceive<metamark change="#StBa" facs="#f023_z002" function="caret" place="below" rend="caret">caret</metamark><add change="#StBa" facs="#f023_z000" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">--</add>egregiously deceive,<lb/> the superficial skimmer of pages. To be downright and<lb/> candid once more, let me cheerfully say, that two<lb/> of these titles did dolefully dupe no less an eagle-eyed<lb/> reader than myself; and that, too, after I had<lb/> been impressed with a sense of the great depth and<lb/> breadth of this American man. "Who in the name<lb/> of thunder" (as the country- people say in this neighborhood)<lb/> "who in the name of thunder," would anticipate any<lb/> marvel in a piece entitled "Young Goodman Brown"? You<lb/> would of course suppose that it was a simple little<lb/> tale, intended as a supplement to "Goody Two Shoes." Whereas,<lb/> it is deep as Dante; nor can you finish it, without<lb/> addressing the author in his own words--"It is yours to pene-<lb/>trate, in every bosom, the deep mystery of sin". And with</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>