<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f024"/>
                <p>Young Goodman, too, in allegorical pursuit of <lb/>his Puritan wife, you cry out
                    in your anguish:</p>
                <p>"'Faith !' shouted Goodman Brown, in a voice <lb/>of agony and desperation; and
                    the echoes of the <lb/>forest mocked him, crying-- 'Faith! Faith!' as if
                    <lb/>bewildered wretches were seeking her all through <lb/>the wilderness."</p>
                <p>Now this same piece, entitled "Young Good-<lb/>man Brown," is one of the two that
                    I had not <lb/>all read yesterday; and I allude to it now, <lb/>because it is,
                    in itself, such a strong positive<lb/> illustration of that blackness in
                    Hawthorne, <lb/>which I had assumed from the mere occasional <lb/>shadows of it,
                    as revealed in several of the <lb/>other sketches. But had I previously perused
                    <lb/>"Young Goodman Brown," I should have been <lb/>at no pains to draw the
                    conclusion, which I <lb/>came to, at a time when I was ignorant that the
                    <lb/>book contained one such direct and unqualified <lb/>manifestation of
                    it.</p>
                <p>The other piece of the two referred to, is <lb/>entitled "A Select Party," which,
                    in my first <lb/>simplicity upon originally taking hold of the <lb/>book, I
                    fancied must treat of some pumpkin-<lb/>pie party in old Salem, or some
                    chowder-<lb/>party on Cape Cod. Whereas, by all the gods <lb/>of Peedee! it is
                    the sweetest and sublimest <lb/>thing that has been written since Spencer
                    <lb/>wrote. Nay, there is nothing in Spencer that <lb/>surpasses it, perhaps
                    nothing that equals it. <lb/>And the test is this: read any canto in "The
                    <lb/>Faery Queen," and then read "A Select <lb/>Party," and decide which pleases
                    you the most,--<lb/>that is, if you are qualified to judge. Do not <lb/>be
                    frightened at this; for when Spencer was <lb/>alive, he was thought of very much
                    as Haw-<lb/>thorne is now,--was generally accounted just <lb/>such a "gentle"
                    harmless man. It may be, <lb/>that to common eyes, the sublimity of
                    Haw-<lb/>thorne seems lost in his sweetness,--as per-<lb/>haps in this same
                    "Select Party" of his; for <lb/>whom he has builded so august a dome of
                    sun-<lb/>set clouds, and served them on richer plate<lb/> than</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
