<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="leaf">
				<p>
					<pb facs="#f025"/>
					<metamark change="StE" facs="#f025_z018" function="folio" n="24" place="top right margin">folio number "24"</metamark>
				</p>
				<p>Belshazzar's when he banquetted his lords in Babylon.<lb/></p>
				<p>But my <metamark change="#StA" facs="#f025_z017" function="caret" place="inline" rend="caret">caret</metamark><add change="#StB" facs="#f025_z016" hand="#EM" place="above" rend="caret">chief </add>business now, is to point out a <lb/>particular page in this piece, having reference to an honored<lb/> guest, who <add change="#StB" facs="#f025_z015" hand="#EM" place="inspace" rend="no-caret">under </add>the name of "The Master Genius"<lb/> but in the guise <add change="#StC" facs="#f025_z014" hand="#HM" place="inline" rend="no-caret"><corr change="#StE" facs="#f025_z014">of </corr></add><corr change="#StE" facs="#f025_z014">"a</corr> <del change="#StC" facs="#f025_z013" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">poor </del>young man of poor attire,<lb/> with no insignia of rank or acknowledged eminence",<lb/> is introduced to the Man of Fancy, who is the giver of <del change="#StC" facs="#f025_z012" hand="#HM">this</del><lb/> <add change="#StC" facs="#f025_z011" hand="#HM" place="margin" rend="no-caret">the </add><del change="#StC" facs="#f025_z010" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">gorgeous </del>feast. Now the page having reference to this<lb/> "Master Genius," so happily expresses much of what I yesterday<lb/> wrote, touching the coming of the literary Shiloh of<lb/> America, that I cannot but be charmed by the<lb/> coincidence; especially, when it shows such a parity of idea<add change="#StBa" facs="#f025_z009" hand="#HM" place="inline">s</add>, at least in this one <del change="#StC" facs="#f025_z007" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">part </del><add change="#StC" facs="#f025_z008" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="no-caret">point,</add> between a man<lb/> like Hawthorne and a <del change="#StC" facs="#f025_z004" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">calm person</del> <add change="#StC" facs="#f025_z005" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">man</add><metamark change="#StC" facs="#f025_z006" function="caret" place="inline" rend="caret">caret with guideline</metamark>like me.<lb/></p>
				<p>And here, let me throw out another conceit of<lb/> mine touching this American Shiloh, or "Master Genius,"<lb/> as Hawthorne calls him. May it not be, that this<lb/> commanding mind has not been, is not, and never will<lb/> be, individually developed in any one man? And would<lb/> it, indeed, appear so unreasonable to suppose, that this<lb/> great fullness and overflowing may be, or may be destined<lb/> to be, shared by a plurality of men of genius? Surely, to<lb/> take the very greatest example on record, Shakespeare cannot<lb/> be regarded as in himself the concretion of all the genius<lb/> of his time; nor as so immeasurably beyond Marlow, Webster,<lb/> Ford, Beaumont, Jonson, that <corr change="#StBa" facs="#f025_z003">those </corr>great men can be<lb/> said to share none of his<metamark change="#StB" facs="#f025_z002" function="caret" place="inline" rend="caret">caret with guideline</metamark> <del change="#StC" facs="#f025_z000" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">genius. </del><add change="#StC" facs="#f025_z001" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">power?</add> For one, I conceive <lb/>that there were dramatists in Elizabeth's day, between<lb/> whom and Shakespeare the distance was by no means great. Let<lb/> anyone, hitherto little acquainted with those neglected old <lb/>authors, for the first time read them thoroughly, or even<lb/> read Charles Lamb's Specimens of them, and he will</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>