<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="leaf">
                <pb facs="#f026"/>
                <p>be <lb/>amazed at the wondrous ability of those Anaks <lb/>of men, and shocked at
                    this renewed example <lb/>of the fact, that Fortune has more to do with
                    <lb/>fame than merit,-- though, without merit, last-<lb/>ing fame there can be
                    none.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, it would argue too ill of my <lb/>country were this maxim to hold
                    good con-<lb/>cerning Nathaniel Hawthorne, a man, who <lb/>already, in some few
                    minds, has shed "such a <lb/>light, as never illuminates the earth save when
                    <lb/>a great heart burns as the household fire of a <lb/>grand intellect."</p>
                <p>The words are his,--in the "Select Party;"<lb/> and they are a magnificent
                    setting to a coinci-<lb/>dent sentiment of my own, but ramblingly
                    ex-<lb/>pressed yesterday, in reference to himself. <lb/>Gainsay it who will, as
                    I now write, I am <lb/>Posterity speaking by proxy--and after times <lb/>will
                    make it more than good, when I declare, <lb/>that the American, who up to the
                    present day, <lb/>has evinced, in literature, the largest brain <lb/>with the
                    largest heart, that man is Nathaniel <lb/>Hawthorne. Moreover, that whatever
                    Na-<lb/>thaniel Hawthorne may hereafter write, "The <lb/>Mosses from an Old
                    Manse" will be ulti-<lb/>mately accounted his master-piece. For there <lb/>is a
                    sure, though a secret sign in some works <lb/>which prove the culmination of the
                    powers <lb/>(only the developable ones, however) that <lb/>produced them. But I
                    am by no means de-<lb/>sirous of the glory of a prophet. I pray <lb/>Heaven that
                    Hawthorne may <hi rend="italics">yet</hi> prove me an <lb/>impostor in this
                    prediction. Especially, as I <lb/>somehow cling to the strange fancy, that, in
                    all <lb/>men, hiddenly reside certain wondrous, occult <lb/>properties--as in
                    some plants and minerals--<lb/>which by some happy but very rare accident
                    <lb/>(as bronze was discovered by the melting of <lb/>the iron and brass in the
                    burning of Corinth) <lb/>may chance to be called forth here on earth; <lb/>not
                    entirely waiting for their better discovery <lb/>in the more congenial, blessed
                    atmosphere of <lb/>heaven.</p>
                <p>Once more--for it is hard to be finite upon <lb/>an infinite subject, and all subjects
                    are infinite.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
