<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="leaf">
				<pb facs="#f026"/>
				<metamark change="#StA" facs="#f026_z011" function="folio" n="25" place="right top">25</metamark>
				<p>be amazed at the wondrous ability of those<lb/> <del change="#StB" facs="#f026_z009" hand="#HM" rend="multi-stroke">now half-forgotten</del> <add change="#StB" facs="#f026_z010" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">Anaks of</add> ^men, and shocked at this renewed<lb/> example of the fact, that Fortune has more to do with<lb/> fame than merit, -- though, without merit, lasting fame there can be none.<lb/></p>
				<p>Nevertheless, it would argue too illy of my country<lb/> were this maxim to hold good concerning Nathaniel<lb/> Hawthorne, a man, who already, in some few minds,<lb/> has shed "such a light, as never illuminates the earth,<lb/> save when a great heart burns as the household fire<lb/> of a grand intellect."<lb/></p>
				<p>The words are his,--in the "Select Party"; and they<lb/> are a magnificent setting to a coincident sentiment of<lb/> my own, but <del change="#StB" facs="#f026_z006" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">freely </del><add change="#StB" facs="#f026_z007" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret"><del change="#StB" facs="#f026_z008" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">are </del>ramblingly</add> ^expressed yesterday, in reference to him<lb/>self. Gainsay it who will, as I now write, I am Posterity<lb/> speaking by proxy -- and after times will make it more<lb/> than good, when I declare -- that the American, who up<lb/> to the present day, has evinced, in Literature, the largest<lb/> brain <del change="#StB" facs="#f026_z004" hand="#HM" rend="single-stroke">and </del><add change="#StB" facs="#f026_z005" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">with </add>^the largest heart, that man is Nathaniel<lb/> Hawthorne. Moreover, that whatever Nathaniel Hawthorne<lb/> may hereafter write, "The Mosses from an Old Manse" will<lb/> be ultimately accounted his masterpiece. For there is<lb/> a sure, though a secret sign in some works which <lb/>prove the culmination of the powers^ <add change="#StB" facs="#f026_z003" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">(only the developable ones, however)</add> that produced <lb/>them. But I am by no means desirous of the <lb/>glory of a prophet. I pray Heaven that Hawthorne may <lb/>yet prove me an impostor in this prediction. <lb/>Especially, as I somehow cling to the<lb/> strange fancy, that, in all men, hiddenly reside<lb/> certain wondrous, occult properties -- as in some ^<add change="#StB" facs="#f026_z002" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">plants and</add> minerals -- <lb/>which by some happy but very rare accident (as bronze was <lb/> discovered by the melting of the iron and brass in the burning of Corinth)<lb/> may chance to be called forth here on earth; not entirely <lb/>waiting for their better discovery in the more congenial, <lb/>blessed atmosphere of heaven.<lb/></p>
				<p>Once more- - for it is hard to be finite<lb/> upon an infinite subject, and all ^<add change="#StB" facs="#f026_z001" hand="#HM" place="above" rend="caret">subjects </add><del change="#StB" facs="#f026_z000" hand="#HM" rend="multi-stroke">things </del>are infinite.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>