<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Versions of "Hawthorne and his Mosses"</title>
				<author>Herman Melville</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>Herman Melville Electronic Library</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Information about the source</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="leaf" n="1">
				<pb facs="#f000"/>
				<head>Hawthorne &amp; His Mosses,</head>
				<head>By a Virginian Spending July in Vermont</head>
				<p>A papered chamber in a fine<lb/> old farm-house -- a mile from any other dwelling,<lb/> and dipped to the eaves in foliage -- surrounded by<lb/> mountains, old woods, and Indian ponds, -- this, surely, is<lb/> the place to write of Hawthorne. Some charm is in<lb/> this northern air, for love and duty seem both impelling<lb/> to the task. A man of a deep &amp; noble nature has seized<lb/> me in this seclusion. His wild, witch voice rings thro' me;<lb/> or, in softer cadences, I seem to hear it in the songs of<lb/> the hill-side birds, that sing in the larch trees at my<lb/> window.</p>
				<p>Would that all excellent books were foundlings,<lb/> without father or mother, that so it might be, we<lb/> could glorify them, without including their ostensible authors. Nor<lb/> would any true man take exception to this; -- least of all,<lb/> he who writes, -- <ref target="note_9f762d8685424b2e8380ea53d69940e4" type="editorial">"When the Artist rises high enough to<lb/> achieve the Beautiful, the symbol by which he makes it<lb/> perceptible to mortal senses becomes of little value in his<lb/> eyes, while his spirit possesses itself in the enjoyment<lb/> of the reality."</ref><note xml:id="note_9f762d8685424b2e8380ea53d69940e4">HM did not mark this passage in his copy of Mosses from an Old Manse. This is the final line from "The Artist of the Beautiful, on which Melville left marginalia on four pages. Melville mistakenly capitalized "artist" and switched tenses in copying the sentence -- "When the artist rose enough to achieve the Beautiful, the symbol by which he made it perceptible to mortal senses became of little value in his eyes, while his spirit possessed itself in the enjoyment of the reality" (p. 191 in HM's 1846 Wiley &amp; Putnam edition).</note></p>
				<p>But more than this. I know not</p>
			</div>
			
			<div type="leaf" n="2">
				<pb facs="#f001"/>
				<p>what would be the right name to put on the<lb/> title-page of an excellent book, but this I feel, that <lb/>the names of all fine authors are fictitious ones, far <lb/>more so than that of Junius-- simply standing, as they do, for the <lb/> mystical, ever-eluding Spirit of all Beauty, which <lb/> ubiquitously possesses  men of genius. Purely <reg>imaginative</reg>
					<orig>imagina<lb/> tive</orig> as this fancy may appear, it nevertheless seems to <lb/> receive some warrantry from the fact, that on a personal <lb/> interview no great author has ever come up to the <lb/> idea of his reader. But that dust of which our <lb/> bodies are composed, how can it fitly express <lb/> the nobler intelligences among us? With reverence be <lb/> it spoken, that not even in the case of one deemed <lb/> more than man, not even in our Saviour, did his <lb/>
					visible frame betoken anything of the augustness of the nature within. <lb/> Else, how could those Jewish eyewitnesses fail to <lb/> see heaven in his glance.</p>
				<p> It is curious, how a man may travel <lb/> along a country road, and yet miss the grandest, <lb/> or sweetest of prospects, by reason of an intervening <lb/> hedge,  so like all other hedges, as in no way <lb/> to hint of the  wide landscape beyond.<lb/> So  has it been with me concerning the enchanting <lb/> landscape in the soul of this Hawthorne, this most <lb/> excellent Man of Mosses. His "Old Manse" has been <lb/> written now four years, but I never read it till a day or two since.<lb/>. I had seen it in the book-stores -- <lb/> heard of it often -- even had it recommended to me <lb/> by a tasteful friend, as a rare, quiet book, perhaps <lb/> too deserving of popularity to be popular. But there are <lb/> so many books called "excellent," and so much</p>
			</div>
			
			
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>