<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hawthorne and His Mosses</title>
            <author>Herman Melville</author>
            <editor role="general" xml:id="JB">John Bryant</editor>
            <editor role="general" xml:id="CO">Christopher Ohge</editor>
            <editor role="associate" xml:id="BH">Brandon Hurst</editor>
            <editor role="assistant" xml:id="YS">Yuying Shen</editor>
            <editor role="assistant" xml:id="YC">Yihong Cai</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Melville Electronic Library, 2025</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>New York Public Library</repository>
                  <idno>MssCol 873 (https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/24bb7f40-184f-0133-2d4b-58d385a7bbd0)</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote xml:id="HM">Revisions by Herman Melville</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="ESM">Revisions by Elizabeth Shaw Melville</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="ED">Revisions by Evert Duyckinck, editor of the Literary World</handNote>
                     <handNote xml:id="comp">Revisions made by compositors of the Literary World (Lyman, McIntyre, Alexander)</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation><!-- manuscript revisions and genetic stages -->
            <listChange>
               <change xml:id="StA">Stage A: Manuscript draft (not known to survive)
					</change>
               <change xml:id="StB">Stage B: Fair copy stage by Elizabeth Shaw Melville</change>
               <change xml:id="StBa">Stage Ba: Corrections to Stage B text by Elizabeth Shaw Melville and Herman Melville</change>
               <change xml:id="StC">Stage C: Substantive Revisions by Herman Melville</change>
               <change xml:id="StD">Stage D: Changes made by Evert Duyckinck in preparation for publication in the Literary World</change>
               <change xml:id="StE">Stage E: Changes made by the compositors of the Literary World</change>
            </listChange>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="leaf" n="1">
            <pb facs="#f000"/>
            <head>Hawthorne &amp; His Mosses,</head>
            <head>By a Virginian Spending July in Vermont</head>
            <head>Part I</head>
            <p>A papered chamber in a fine<lb/> old farm-house -- a mile from any other dwelling,<lb/> and dipped to the eaves in foliage -- surrounded by<lb/> mountains, old woods, and Indian ponds, -- this, surely, is<lb/> the place to write of Hawthorne. Some charm is in<lb/> this northern air, for love and duty seem both impelling<lb/> to the task. A man of a deep &amp; noble nature has seized<lb/> me in this seclusion. His wild, witch voice rings thro' me;<lb/> or, in softer cadences, I seem to hear it in the songs of<lb/> the hill-side birds, that sing in the larch trees at my<lb/> window.</p>
            <p>Would that all excellent books were foundlings,<lb/> without father or mother, that so it might be, we<lb/> could glorify them, without including their ostensible authors. Nor<lb/> would any true man take exception to this; -- least of all,<lb/> he who writes, -- </p>
            <p>But more than this. I know not</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="2">
            <pb facs="#f001"/>
            <p>what would be the right name to put on the<lb/> title-page of an excellent book, but this I feel, that <lb/>the names of all fine authors are fictitious ones, far <lb/>more so than that of Junius-- simply standing, as they do, for the <lb/> mystical, ever-eluding Spirit of all Beauty, which <lb/> ubiquitously possesses  men of genius. Purely <reg>imaginative</reg>
               <orig>imagina<lb/> tive</orig> as this fancy may appear, it nevertheless seems to <lb/> receive some warrantry from the fact, that on a personal <lb/> interview no great author has ever come up to the <lb/> idea of his reader. But that dust of which our <lb/> bodies are composed, how can it fitly express <lb/> the nobler intelligences among us? With reverence be <lb/> it spoken, that not even in the case of one deemed <lb/> more than man, not even in our Saviour, did his <lb/>
					visible frame betoken anything of the augustness of the nature within. <lb/> Else, how could those Jewish eyewitnesses fail to <lb/> see heaven in his glance.</p>
            <p> It is curious, how a man may travel <lb/> along a country road, and yet miss the grandest, <lb/> or sweetest of prospects, by reason of an intervening <lb/> hedge,  so like all other hedges, as in no way <lb/> to hint of the  wide landscape beyond.<lb/> So  has it been with me concerning the enchanting <lb/> landscape in the soul of this Hawthorne, this most <lb/> excellent Man of Mosses. His "Old Manse" has been <lb/> written now four years, but I never read it till a day or two since.<lb/>. I had seen it in the book-stores -- <lb/> heard of it often -- even had it recommended to me <lb/> by a tasteful friend, as a rare, quiet book, perhaps <lb/> too deserving of popularity to be popular. But there are <lb/> so many books called "excellent," and so much</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="3">
            <pb facs="#f002"/>
            <p>unpopular merit, that amid the thick stir of <lb/> other things, the hint of my tasteful friend was <lb/> disregarded; and for four years the Mosses on <lb/> the old Manse never refreshed me with their <lb/> perennial green. It may be, however, that all this <lb/> while, the book, like wine, was only improving in <lb/> flavor and body. At any rate, it so chanced <lb/> that this long procrastination eventuated in a happy <lb/> result. At breakfast the other day, a mountain <lb/> girl, a cousin of mine, who for the last two weeks <lb/> has every morning helped me to strawberries and <lb/> raspberries,-- which, likethe roses and pearls in the fairy tale, <lb/> seemed to fall into the saucer from those strawberry- <lb/> beds her cheeks,-- this delightful creature, this charming <lb/> Cherry says to me -- "I see you spend your mornings <lb/> in the hay-mow; and yesterday I found there '"Dwight's <lb/> Travels in New England'". Now I have something far <lb/> better than that,--something more congenial to our <lb/> summer on these hills. Take these raspberries, and <lb/> then I will give you some moss." -- "Moss"! said I. -- "Yes, <lb/> and you must take it to the barn with you, and <lb/> good-bye to 'Dwight' ". [With that she left me,<lb/> and soon returned with a volume, verdantly <lb/> bound, and garnished with a curious frontispiece in <lb/> green,-- nothing less, than a fragment of real moss <lb/> cunningly pressed to a fly-leaf. -- "Why this," said I <lb/> spilling my raspberries, "this is the 'Mosses from an <lb/> Old Manse'." "Yes" said cousin Cherry "yes, it is that flowery <lb/> Hawthorne." --</p>
            <p>-- "Hawthorne and Mosses" said I "no more: <lb/> it is morning: it is July in the country: and I</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="4">
            <pb facs="#f003"/>
            <p>am off for the barn".</p>
            <p>Stretched on that new mown clover, <lb/> the hill-side breeze blowing over me <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">thro'</hi> the wide barn door, and soothed by the hum of the <lb/> bees in the meadows around, how magically <lb/> stole over me this <hi rend="bold">Mossy</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Man</hi>! And how amply, <lb/> how bountifully, did he redeem that delicious <lb/> promise to his guests in the Old Manse, of whom <lb/> it is written -- "Others could give them pleasure, <lb/> "<hi rend="bold">or</hi> amusement, or instruction -- these could be <lb/> "picked up anywhere -- but it was for me to <lb/> "give them rest. Rest, in a life of trouble! What <lb/> "better could be done for  weary and <lb/> "world-worn spirits? what better could be done <lb/> "for anybody, who came within our magic <lb/> "circle, than to throw the spell of a magic spirit <lb/> "over him?" -- So all that day, <hi rend="bold">half-</hi>buried in the <lb/> new clover , I watched this Hawthorne's <lb/> "Assyrian dawn, and Paphian sunset and moon-<lb/> rise, from the summit of our Eastern Hill."</p>
            <p>The soft ravishments of the man spun me round <lb/> about in a web of dreams, and when the book was <lb/> closed, when the spell was over, this wizard <lb/> "dismissed me with but misty reminiscences, as if <lb/> I had been dreaming of him"</p>
            <p>What a mild moonlight of contemplative <lb/>humor bathes that Old Manse!-- the rich and <lb/> rare distilment of a spicy and slowly-oozing heart.<lb/> No rollicking <hi rend="bold">rudeness,</hi> no gross fun fed on fat dinners, <lb/> and bred in the lees of wine,-- but a humor <lb/> so spiritually gentle, so high, so deep, and yet</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="5">
            <pb facs="#f004"/>
            <p>so richly  relishable, that it <hi rend="bold">were</hi>
               <lb/> hardly  inappropriate in an angel. <hi rend="bold">It</hi> is the <lb/> very religion of mirth; for nothing so human <lb/> but it may be advanced to that. The orchard of <lb/> the <hi rend="bold">Old</hi> Manse seems the visible type of the <lb/> fine mind that has described  it. Those <lb/> twisted, and contorted old trees, <hi rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold"/>And then, as surrounded <lb/> by these grotesque forms, and hushed in the <lb/> noon-day repose of this Hawthorne's <hi rend="bold">spell</hi>, how <hi rend="bold">aptly</hi>
               <lb/> might the still fall of his ruddy thoughts <lb/> into your soul be symbolized by "the thump of <lb/> a great apple, in the <hi rend="bold">stillest</hi> afternoon, falling <lb/> without a breath of wind, from the mere <lb/> necessity of perfect ripeness"<hi rend="bold">!</hi> For no less ripe <lb/> than ruddy are the apples of <hi rend="bold">the</hi> thoughts and fancies in <lb/> this sweet Man of Mosses. "Buds and Bird-voices"-- <lb/> What a delicious thing is that!"Will the world <lb/> ever be so decayed, that Spring may not renew <lb/> its greenness<hi rend="bold">?</hi>"<hi rend="bold">--</hi> And the "Fire-Worship"<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Was ever <lb/> the hearth so glorified into an altar before? <lb/> The mere title of that piece is better than any <lb/> common work in fifty folio volumes. How <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">exquisite</hi> is this:-- "Nor did it lessen the charm <lb/> "of his soft, familiar courtesy and helpfulness, <lb/> that the mighty spirit, were opportunity offered <lb/> him, would run riot through the peaceful <lb/> house, wrap its inmates in his terrible embrace, <lb/>and leave nothing of them save their whitened</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="6">
            <pb facs="#f005"/>
            <p>bones. This possibility of mad destruction only <lb/> made his domestic kindness the more beautiful <lb/> and touching. It was so sweet of him, being <lb/> endowed with such power, to dwell, day after <lb/> day, and one long, lonesome night after <lb/> another, on the dusky hearth, only now &amp; then <lb/> betraying his wild nature, by thrusting his <lb/> red tongue out of the chimney-top! True, he had <lb/> done much mischief in the world, and was <lb/> pretty certain to do more, but his warm heart <lb/> atoned for all<hi rend="bold">;</hi> He was kindly to the race of man."</p>
            <p>But he has still other apples,  not <lb/> quite so ruddy, though full as ripe;--apples, that <lb/> have been left to wither on the tree, after the <lb/> pleasant autumn gathering is past. The <lb/> sketch of "<hi rend="bold">The</hi> Old Apple Dealer is conceived in <lb/> the subtlest spirit of sadness; he whose "subdued <lb/> and nerveless boyhood prefigured his abortive <lb/> prime, which, likewise, contained within itself <lb/> the prophecy and image of <hi rend="bold">his</hi> lean and torpid <lb/> age" Such <hi rend="bold">touches</hi> as are <hi rend="bold">in</hi> this piece can not <lb/> proceed from any common heart. They argue <lb/> such a depth of tenderness, such a boundless sym<lb/>-pathy with <hi rend="bold">all</hi> forms of being, such an omni-<lb/>present love, that we must needs say, that this <lb/> Hawthorne is here almost alone in <hi rend="bold">his</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">generation,</hi>
               <lb/> -- at least, in the artistic manifestation of these <lb/> things<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Still</hi> more. Such <hi rend="bold">touches</hi> as these, <lb/> -- and many, very many <hi rend="bold">similar ones,</hi>, all through his <lb/> chapters<hi rend="bold">--</hi>furnish clews, whereby we enter a</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="7">
            <pb facs="#f006"/>
            <p>little way into the intricate, profound <lb/> heart <hi rend="bold">where</hi> they originated. And we see, that <lb/> suffering<hi rend="bold">,</hi> some time or other <hi rend="bold">&amp; in some shape or other, -- </hi>
               <lb/>this only can enable any man to depict it in <lb/>others. All over <hi rend="bold">him,</hi> Hawthorne's melancholy rests <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/> like an Indian Summer<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">which tho' bathing a whole country <lb/> in one softness, still reveals the distinctive  hue of </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">every</hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> towering hill</hi>, <hi rend="bold">&amp; each </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">far-winding vale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is the least part of genius <lb/> that attracts admiration. Where Hawthorne is <lb/> known, he seems to be <hi rend="bold">deemed</hi> a pleasant <lb/> writer, with a pleasant style, -- a sequestered, <lb/> harmless man, from whom any deep and <lb/> weighty thing would <hi rend="bold">hardly be anticipated: --</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">a man who means no meanings.</hi>
               <lb/> But there is no man, in <hi rend="bold">whom</hi> humor and love, <lb/> like mountain peaks, soar to such a rapt height, <lb/> as to receive the irradiations of the upper <lb/> skies; --  there is no man in <lb/> whom humor &amp; love are developed in that <lb/> high form called genius; no such man can exist <lb/> without also possessing, as the <hi rend="bold">indispensable complement </hi>
               <lb/> of <hi rend="bold">these,</hi> a great, deep intellect, which drops down <lb/> into <hi rend="bold">the</hi> universe like a <hi rend="bold">plummet</hi>. <hi rend="bold">Or, love</hi> and humor <lb/>are only the eyes, through which such an intellect <lb/> views this world. The great beauty in such a <lb/> mind is but the product of its strength. What, <lb/> to all readers, can be more charming than the <lb/>piece entitled "Monsieur du Miroir"<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and to <lb/> a <hi rend="bold">reader</hi> at all capable of <hi rend="bold">fully</hi> fathoming it, what, at the <lb/> same time, can possess more mystical depth <lb/>of meaning? <hi rend="bold">-- Yes,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">there he sits,</hi> and look<hi rend="bold">s</hi> at me, --<lb/>this "shape of mystery", this "identical Monsieur du Miroir<hi rend="bold">."</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="8">
            <pb facs="#f007"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">--</hi> "Methinks I should tremble now, were his <lb/> wizard power of gliding through all impediments <lb/> in search of me, to place him suddenly before <lb/> my eyes" How profound, nay appalling, is <lb/> the moral evolved by the "Earth's Holocaust"<hi rend="bold">;</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">where</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">--</hi> beginning with the hollow follies and <lb/> affectation<hi rend="bold">s</hi> of the world, -- <hi rend="bold">all vanities and </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">empty</hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> theories</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">&amp;</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">forms,</hi> are<hi rend="bold">, </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">one after another, &amp; by an admirably graduated, </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">growing comprehensiveness</hi>; thrown into the allegorical fire, till, <hi rend="bold">at length,</hi>
               <lb/> nothing is left but the all-<lb/>engendering heart of man; which remaining <lb/> still unconsumed, the great conflagration is <lb/>. <hi rend="bold">Of</hi> a piece with this, is the <lb/> "Intelligence Office"<hi rend="bold">,</hi> a wondrous symbolizing <lb/> of <hi rend="bold">the</hi> secret workings in <hi rend="bold">mens' souls.</hi>
               <restore/> are <lb/> other sketches, still more charged with <lb/> ponderous import."The Christmas Banquet"<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">&amp;</hi> "The <lb/> Bosom <hi rend="bold">Serpent"</hi> would be <hi rend="bold">fine subjects</hi>
               <lb/> for a curious and elaborate analysis, touching <lb/> the conjectural parts of the mind that produced <lb/> them. For spite of all the <hi rend="bold">Indian-summer</hi> sunlight <hi rend="bold">on</hi> the <lb/> hither side of Hawthorne's soul, the other side -- like <lb/> the dark half of the physical sphere -- is shrouded <lb/> in a blackness, <hi rend="bold">ten times</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">black.</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>   But this darkness <lb/> but gives more effect to the evermoving dawn, <lb/> that forever <hi rend="bold">advances</hi> through it, and <hi rend="bold">circumnavigates</hi>
               <lb/> his world. Whether Hawthorne has simply availed <lb/> himself of this mystical blackness as a means <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">to</hi> the wondrous effects he makes it to produce <lb/> in his lights &amp; shades; or whether there really <lb/> lurks in him, perhaps unknown to himself, <lb/> a touch of Puritanic gloom,-- this, I cannot</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="9">
            <pb facs="#f008"/>
            <p>altogether tell. Certain it is, however, that<lb/> this great power of blackness in him derives<lb/> its force from its appeals to that Calvinistic<lb/> sense of <hi rend="bold">Innate</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Depravity</hi> and original Sin, from whose<lb/> visitations, in some shape or other, no deeply thinking<lb/> mind is always &amp; wholly free. <hi rend="bold">For, in</hi> certain moods,<lb/> no man can weigh this world, without throwing<lb/> in something, <hi rend="bold">somehow</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Original</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Sin</hi>, to strike the<lb/> uneven balance. At all events, perhaps no<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">writer</hi> has ever <hi rend="bold">wielded</hi> this terrific thought with<lb/>greater <hi rend="bold">terror</hi> than this same harmless<lb/> Hawthorne. Still more: this black <hi rend="bold">conceit pervades him,</hi>
               <lb/> through &amp; through. You may be witched by his<lb/> sunlight,-- transported by the bright gildings<lb/> in the skies he builds over you;-- but there is<lb/> the blackness of darkness beyond; and even <hi rend="bold">his</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">bright</hi> gildings but fringe, and play upon the<lb/> edges of thunder-clouds<hi rend="bold">.</hi>--  In one word, the<lb/> world is mistaken in this Nathaniel Hawthorne.<lb/> He himself must often have smiled at its<lb/> absurd misconception <hi rend="bold">of him.</hi> He is immeasurably deeper<lb/> than the plummet of the mere critic. For it<lb/> is not the <hi rend="bold">brain</hi> that can test such a man;<lb/> it is only the heart. You cannot come to<lb/> know greatness by <hi rend="bold">inspecting it;</hi> there is no<lb/> glimpse to be caught of it, except by intuition;<lb/> you <hi rend="bold">need not</hi> ring it, you but touch it, and you find<lb/> it is gold</p>
            <p>     now <hi rend="bold">it is</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">that</hi> blackness in Hawthorne, of<lb/> which I have spoken, that so fixes &amp; fascinates<lb/> me. It may be<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">nevertheless,</hi> that it is too</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="10">
            <p>
               <pb facs="#f009"/>
            </p>
            <p>largely developed in him. Perhaps he does<lb/>not give us a ray of his light for every shade <lb/>of his <hi rend="bold">dark.</hi> But however this may be, this <lb/>blackness it is that furnishes the infinite obscure <lb/>of his back-ground,-- that back-ground, against<lb/> which Shakespeare plays his grandest conceits, <lb/>the things that have made for Shakespeare <lb/>his <hi rend="bold">loftiest, but most circumscribed</hi> renown, as the <hi rend="bold">profoundest</hi>
               <lb/>of thinkers. For by philosophers Shakespeare is <lb/>not <hi rend="bold">adored</hi> as the great man of tragedy and <lb/>comedy.--"Off with his head! so much for <lb/>Buckingham!" this sort of rant, <hi rend="bold">interlined</hi>
               <lb/> by <hi rend="bold">an</hi>other hand, bring<hi rend="bold">s</hi> down the house,--those <lb/>mistaken souls, who dream of Shakespeare <lb/>as a <hi rend="bold">mere</hi> man of Richard-the-Third humps, and <lb/>Macbeth daggers. But it is those deep <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">far-away</hi> things in him; those occasional flashings-forth of <lb/>the intuitive Truth in him; those short, <lb/>quick probings <hi rend="bold">at</hi> the very axis of reality:-- these <lb/>are the things that make Shakespeare, Shakes-<lb/>peare. Through the <hi rend="bold">mouths</hi> of the dark charac-<lb/>ters of Hamlet, Timon, Lear, and Iago, he <lb/>craftily says, <hi rend="bold">or </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">sometimes</hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> insinuates</hi> the things, <hi rend="bold">which</hi> we feel to be so <lb/>terrifically true, that it were all but mad-<lb/>ness for any good man, in his own proper<lb/>character, to utter, or even hint of them. <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Tormented</hi> into desperation, Lear the frantic King <hi rend="bold">tears off the mask,</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">&amp;</hi> speaks the sane madness of vital truth. <lb/>But, as I before said, it is the least part of <lb/>genius that attracts admiration. And so, </p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="11">
            <pb facs="#f010"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">much of the blind, unbridled</hi> admiration that has been heaped <lb/>upon Shakespeare, has been lavished upon the <lb/> least part of him. And few of his endless <lb/> commentators &amp; critics seem to have <hi rend="bold">remembered,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">or even</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>that the immediate products of a great mind <lb/> are not so great, as that undeveloped, <hi rend="bold">(&amp; sometimes undevelopable)</hi> yet <lb/> dimly-discern<hi rend="bold">able</hi> greatness, to which <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">these immediate products</hi> are but the infallible indices. In Shakespeare's <lb/> tomb lies infinitely more than <hi rend="bold">Shakspeare</hi> ever wrote. <lb/> And if I magnify Shakespeare, it is not so much <lb/> for what he did<hi rend="bold">do,</hi> as for what he did not <lb/> do<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">or refrained from doing.</hi> For in this world of lies, Truth is <hi rend="bold">forced</hi> to <lb/> fly like a scared white doe in the woodlands; <lb/> and only by cunning glimpses will she reveal <lb/> herself, as in Shakespeare and other <hi rend="bold">masters</hi> of <lb/> the great <hi rend="bold">Art</hi> of Telling the Truth<hi rend="bold">,--</hi>even though <lb/> it be covertly, and by snatches.</p>
            <p>      But <hi rend="bold">if</hi> this view of the all-popular <lb/>   Shakspeare <hi rend="bold">be</hi> seldom taken by his readers, and if very <lb/> few who extol him, have ever read him deeply,<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">or, perhaps,</hi> only have seen him on the tricky stage<hi rend="bold">, (</hi>which <lb/> alone made, and is still making him his mere <lb/> mob renown<hi rend="bold">) --</hi> if few men have time, or patience, <lb/> or palate <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">,</hi> for the spiritual truth as it is in <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">that</hi> great genius; -- it is<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">then,</hi> no matter of surprise <lb/> that <hi rend="bold">in a contemporaneous age</hi>, Nathaniel Hawthorne is a man, <hi rend="bold">as yet, almost</hi> utterly <lb/>mistaken among men. Here &amp; there, in some <lb/>quiet arm-chair in the noisy town, or some <lb/>deep nook among the <hi rend="bold">noisless</hi> mountains, he may <lb/>be appreciated for something of what he is.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="12">
            <pb facs="#f011"/>
            <p>But unlike Shakespeare, who was forced <lb/>to <hi rend="bold">the contrary course</hi> by circumstances, Hawthorne <hi rend="bold">(</hi>either from <lb/>simple disinclination, or else from inaptitude) <lb/>refrains from all the <hi rend="bold">popularizing noise</hi> and show of <lb/>broad farce, <hi rend="bold">&amp;</hi> blood-besmeared tragedy; <lb/>content with the still, rich utterance<hi rend="bold">s</hi> of a <lb/>great intellect in repose, and which sends <lb/>few thoughts into circulation, except they be <lb/>arterialized <hi rend="bold">at</hi> his large warm lungs, and <lb/>expanded in his honest heart.</p>
            <p>Nor need you <lb/>fix upon that blackness in him, if it suit <lb/>you not. Nor, indeed, will all readers discern <lb/>it, for it is, <hi rend="bold">mostly,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">insinuated</hi> to those who may <lb/>best undersand it, and account for it; it is <lb/>not obtruded upon every one alike.</p>
            <p>     Some may start to read of Shakespeare and <lb/>Hawthorne on the same page. They may say, that if <lb/>an illustration were needed, a lesser light might have <lb/>sufficed to elucidate this Hawthorne, this <hi rend="bold">small</hi> man of <lb/>yesterday. But I am not, willingly, one of those, who, <lb/>as touching Shakespeare at least, exemplify the <lb/>maxim of Rochefoucault, that "we exalt the reputation <lb/>of some, in order to depress that of others"<hi rend="bold">;--</hi> who, to <lb/>teach all <hi rend="bold"> noble-souled aspirants</hi> that there is no hope for them, <lb/>pronounce Shakespeare absolutely unapproachable. <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">But</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Shakespeare</hi> has been approached. There are minds <lb/>that have gone as <hi rend="bold">far</hi> as Shakespeare into <lb/>the universe. And hardly a mortal man, <hi rend="bold">who,</hi>
               <lb/>at some time or other, has not felt <lb/>as great thoughts in him as any you will find <lb/>in Hamlet. We must not <hi rend="bold">inferentially</hi> malign mankind</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="13">
            <pb facs="#f012"/>
            <p>for the sake of any one man, whoever he <lb/>may be. This is too cheap a purchase of contentment <lb/>for conscious mediocrity to make. Besides, <lb/>this absolute and unconditional adoration of <lb/>Shakespeare has grown to be a part of our <lb/>Anglo Saxon superstition<hi rend="bold">s</hi>. The <hi rend="bold">T</hi>hirty <hi rend="bold">N</hi>ine articles are <lb/>now <hi rend="bold">F</hi>orty. Intolerance has come to exist in <lb/>this matter.</p>
            <p>You must believe in Shakespeare<hi rend="bold">'s</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">unapproachability,</hi> or <lb/>quit the country. But what sort of a belief <lb/>is this for an American, a man who is bound <lb/>to carry republican progress<hi rend="bold">-iveness</hi> into <hi rend="bold">L</hi>itera-<lb/>ture, as well as into <hi rend="bold">L</hi>ife? Believe me, my <lb/>friends, that <hi rend="bold">
                  <hi rend="bold">men</hi> not very much inferior to</hi> Shakespeare<hi rend="bold">,</hi> are this day being born <lb/>on the banks of the Ohio. And the day will <lb/> come, when you shall say who reads a book <lb/>by an Englishman <hi rend="bold">that is a modern?</hi>     The great mistake <lb/>seems to be, that even with those Americans <lb/>who look forward <hi rend="bold">to</hi> the coming of a <lb/>great <hi rend="bold">literary</hi> genius among us, they somehow fancy he <lb/>will come in the costume of Queen Elizabeth's <lb/>day,-- be a writer of dramas founded upon <lb/>old English history, or the tales of Boccaccio. <lb/>Whereas, great geniuses are part<hi rend="bold">s</hi> of the times; <lb/>they themselves are the times; and possess a <lb/>correspondent coloring. It is of a <hi rend="bold">piece</hi> with <hi rend="bold">t</hi>he Jews, who <lb/>while their Shiloh was meekly walking in <lb/>their streets, were still praying for his magnifi-<lb/>cent coming; looking for him in a chariot, who <lb/>was already among them on an ass. Nor must we <lb/>forget, that, in his own life-time, Shakespeare was</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="14">
            <pb facs="#f013"/>
            <p>not Shakespeare, but only Master William Shakespeare <lb/> of the <hi rend="bold">shrewd, thriving</hi>, business firm of Condell, Shakespeare &amp; Co., proprietors <lb/> of the Globe Theatre in London; <reg change="metatdata#StE" facs="#f013_z008">&amp; </reg>by a  courtly author, <lb/> of the name of Chettle, was hooted at, as an "upstart <lb/> crow" beautified "with other birds' feathers." For, mark it well, <lb/> imitation is often the first charge brought against real <lb/> originality. Why this is so, there is not space to set forth here. You must <lb/> have plenty of sea-room to tell the <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Truth</hi> in; especially, when it seems to have an aspect <lb/> of newness, as America did in 1492, <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f013_z010">tho'</reg> it was then <lb/> just as old, and perhaps older than Asia, only <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">those </hi>sagacious philosophers, the common sailors, had never <lb/> seen it before; swearing it was all water <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f013_z012">&amp;</reg> moonshine <lb/> there. <hi rend="bold">（to be concluded next week)</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="15">
            <pb facs="#f014"/>
            <head>Part II</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Hawthorne and His Mosses</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold"> By a Virginian Spending July in Vermont</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">[</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">concluded from the last number.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">]</hi>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Now</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">I</hi> do not  ^<hi rend="bold">say that</hi> Nathaniel of Salem is a <lb/>greater than William of Avon<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or as great<hi rend="bold">.</hi> But <lb/>the difference between the two men is by no <lb/>means immeasurable<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Not a very great deal <lb/> more<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and Nathaniel were <hi rend="bold">verily</hi> William.</p>
            <p>This<hi rend="bold">,</hi> too<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I mean<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that if Shakespeare has <lb/>not been equalled<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">give the world time, <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f014_z034">&amp;</reg>
               </hi>he is sure to be surpassed<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">in one hemisphere or the other.</hi>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/> Nor will <lb/>it <hi rend="bold">at</hi> all do to say<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that the world is getting<hi rend="bold">grey &amp; grizzled</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <lb/>now<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and has lost that fresh charm which <lb/>she wore of old<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and by virtue of which <lb/>the great poets of past times made themselves <lb/>
               <lb/>what we esteem them <hi rend="bold">to be</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">.</hi> Not so. the world is as young today<hi rend="bold">,</hi> as when it was <lb/>created<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and th<hi rend="bold">is</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Vermont</hi> morning dew is as wet to <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">my</hi> feet<hi rend="bold">,</hi> as Eden's <hi rend="bold">dew</hi> to Adam<hi rend="bold">'s</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">.</hi> Nor has <lb/>Nature been all over ransacked by our <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f014_z015 #f014_z016">progen--<lb/>itors,</reg> so t<hi rend="bold">hat</hi> no new charms and mysteries remain <lb/>for this lat<hi rend="bold">t</hi>er generation to find. Far from it<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>The <hi rend="bold">trillionth</hi> part has not yet been <lb/>said<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and all that has been said<hi rend="bold">,</hi> but <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f014_z007 #f014_z008">mul-<lb/>tiplies</reg> the avenues to what <hi rend="bold">remains</hi> to be said<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>It is not so much paucity<hi rend="bold">,</hi> as superabundance <lb/>of material that <hi rend="bold">seems to</hi> incapacitate<hi rend="bold">modern authors.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="16">
            <pb facs="#f015"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">praise mediocrity even, in her own children, before she <lb/> praises (for everywhere, merit demands acknowledgment from every one) <lb/> the best excellence in the children of any other land. Let <lb/> her own authors, I say, have the priority of appreciation. I <lb/> was much pleased with a hot-headed Carolina cousin of mine, <lb/> who once said,--"If there </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">were</hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> no other American to stand <lb/> by, in Literature,--why, then, I would stand by Pop Emmons <lb/> and his "Fredoniad," and till </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">a</hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> better epic came along, <lb/> swear it was not very far behind the Iliad." Take away <lb/> the words, and in spirit he was sound</hi>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="17">
            <pb facs="#f016"/>
            <p>Let America then <hi rend="bold">prize</hi> and cherish her <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">writers;</hi>yea<hi rend="bold">,</hi> let her glorify them. They are not <lb/> so many in number<hi rend="bold">,</hi> as to exhaust her <lb/> good-will<hi rend="bold">.</hi> And while she has good kit<hi rend="bold">h</hi>
               <lb/> and kin of her own<hi rend="bold">,</hi> to take to her bosom<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> let her not lavish her embraces upon the <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">household of</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">a</hi>n alien<hi rend="bold">.</hi> For believe it or not <lb/> England<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">after all, is, in many things</hi>, an alien to us. China has more <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">bowels</hi> of <hi rend="bold">real</hi> love for us than she. But even <lb/>were there no <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">)</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">--</hi>were there none of <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">strong literary individualites among us, as there are some dozens at least,</hi>
               <lb/>nevertheless<hi rend="bold">, </hi>let America <hi rend="bold">first</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">she praises (for everywhere, merit demands acknowledgment from every one)</hi> the best excellence in the children of any <lb/> other land<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Said a hot-headed Carolina cousin of mine,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">"If</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">there were no </hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold"> to stand by, </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">in Literature"</hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> said he, "why, then, I would</hi>
               <lb/> stand by Pop Emmons and his <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <lb/> swear it was not very far behind <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
            </p>
            <p>Not that American genius <lb/> needs patronage in order to expand. For that <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">explosive</hi> sort of stuff will expand though screwed <lb/> up in a vice<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and bur<hi rend="bold">s</hi>t it<hi rend="bold">,</hi> though it were <lb/> triple steel. It is for the nation's sake<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> and not for her authors' sake<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that I would <lb/>have America be heedful of the <hi rend="bold">increasing</hi>
               <lb/> greatness among her writers. <hi rend="bold">For</hi> how great <lb/> the shame<hi rend="bold">,</hi> if other nations should be before <lb/> her<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in crowning her heroes of the pen. But <lb/> this is almost the case now<hi rend="bold">.</hi> American <lb/> authors have received more just and <lb/> discriminating praise <hi rend="bold">(</hi>however <hi rend="bold">loftily </hi>and ridiculously</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="18">
            <pb facs="#f017"/>
            <p>given<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">in </hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">certain cases)</hi> even from some Englishmen<hi rend="bold">,</hi> than<lb/> from <hi rend="bold">their</hi> own countrymen<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">There are hardly five critics in America, and several of them are asleep.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">A</hi>s for<lb/> patronage<hi rend="bold">,</hi> it is the American author who<lb/> now patronizes the country<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and not his<lb/> country him. And if at times some<lb/> among them appeal to the people for <hi rend="bold">more<lb/>
               </hi>recognition<hi rend="bold">,</hi> it is not alway<hi rend="bold">s</hi> with selfish<lb/>motives<hi rend="bold">,</hi> but patriotic ones.</p>
            <p>It is true<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that but few of <hi rend="bold">them</hi>
               <lb/> as yet have <hi rend="bold">evinced </hi>that <hi rend="bold">decided </hi>originality<lb/> which merits great praise<hi rend="bold">.</hi> But that<lb/> graceful  writer<hi rend="bold">,</hi> who perhaps of all<lb/> American<hi rend="bold">s</hi> has received <hi rend="bold">the</hi> most plaudits<lb/> from his own country for his productions<hi rend="bold">,--</hi>that<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">very popular <reg change="metadata#StE">&amp; </reg>amiable</hi>writer<hi rend="bold">,</hi> however good<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE">&amp; </reg>self-reliant</hi> in many things<hi rend="bold">,</hi> perhaps<lb/> owes his chief <hi rend="bold">reputation</hi> to the self-acknowledged<lb/>imitation of a<hi rend="bold">foreign</hi>model<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and to the studied avoidance of all topics but smooth <lb/> ones<hi rend="bold">. </hi>But it is bett<hi rend="bold">er</hi> to fail in originality<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> than to <hi rend="bold">succeed</hi> in imitation<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">H</hi>e who has<lb/> never failed <hi rend="bold">somewhere, </hi> that man can not be great. <hi rend="bold">Failure is the true test of greatness</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">A</hi>nd <hi rend="bold">if </hi>it be said<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that <hi rend="bold">continual</hi>success is a<lb/> proof that a man <hi rend="bold">wisely</hi> knows his po<hi rend="bold">wers</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">,-</hi>
               <lb/>it is only to be added<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">in that case,</hi> he knows them to<lb/> be small<hi rend="bold">. </hi>Let us believe it<hi rend="bold">,</hi> then<hi rend="bold">,</hi> once for all<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> that there is no hope for us in the<hi rend="bold">se</hi> smooth pleasing<lb/> writers that know their <hi rend="bold">powers.</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Without malice, but to speak the plain fact, they</hi> but furnish an appendix to Goldsmith<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and other<lb/> English authors. And we want no American<lb/> Goldsmiths<hi rend="bold">:</hi> nay<hi rend="bold">,</hi> we want no American Miltons<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="19">
            <pb facs="#f018"/>
            <p>It were the vilest thing you could say<lb/> of a true American author<hi rend="bold">.</hi>that he were<lb/> an American <hi rend="bold">Tompkins.</hi> Call him an American<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> and have done<hi rend="bold">;</hi> for you cannot say<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">a nobler thing of him.</hi>-But it is<lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">not meant</hi> that all American writers should<lb/> studiously cleave to <hi rend="bold">nationality </hi>in their<lb/> writings<hi rend="bold">;</hi> only this<hi rend="bold">,</hi> no American writer should<lb/> write like an Englishman<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or a Frenchman<hi rend="bold">;</hi>
               <lb/> let him write like a man<hi rend="bold">,</hi> for then he will be<lb/> sure to write like an American<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Let us<lb/> away with this  leaven of <hi rend="bold">literary</hi>
               <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f018_z041 #f018_z042">flunkey-<lb/>ism</reg> towards England<hi rend="bold">.</hi> If either must play<lb/> the flunkey<hi rend="bold">in this thing,</hi> let England do it<hi rend="bold">,</hi> not us<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>. While we are rapidly<lb/> preparing for that <hi rend="bold">political</hi> supremacy<lb/>among <hi rend="bold">the</hi> nations<hi rend="bold">,</hi> which <hi rend="bold">prophetically </hi>awaits <hi rend="bold">us at</hi>
               <lb/> the close of the <hi rend="bold">present</hi>century<hi rend="bold">;</hi> in a literary<lb/> point of view<hi rend="bold">,</hi> we are deplorably unprepared<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">for it;</hi> and we seem studious to remain so. Hitherto<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> reasons might have existed why this should be<hi rend="bold">;</hi>
               <lb/> but no good reason exists now. And all<lb/>that is requisite to amendment in this matter<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> is simply this<hi rend="bold">:</hi> that<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">while freely acknowledging all excellence, everywhere,</hi> we should refrain from<lb/> unduly <hi rend="bold">lauding</hi>foreign writers<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f018_z021"/>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="iiifmossesmanifest.json#f018_z021">&amp;, </reg>at the same time,</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/> duly <hi rend="bold">recognise</hi> the meritorious<lb/> writers that are our own<hi rend="bold">;--</hi>those writers<hi rend="bold">,</hi> who<lb/> breathe that unshackled<hi rend="bold">,</hi> democratic spirit <hi rend="bold">of Christianity</hi>
               <lb/> in all things<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">which</hi>now takes the<hi rend="bold">practical</hi> lead<lb/> in th<hi rend="bold">is</hi> world, though  at the same</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="20">
            <pb facs="#f019"/>
            <p>time led by <hi rend="bold">ourselves-us Americans.</hi> Let us boldly contemn all <lb/>imitation<hi rend="bold">,</hi> though it comes to us graceful and<lb/> fragrant as the morning<hi rend="bold">;</hi>And foster all<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">originality</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">, </hi>though<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">at first</hi>, it be crabbed and ugly as our<lb/> own pine knots. And if any of our authors<lb/> fail<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or seem to fail<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">then, in the words of my</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">enthusiastic Carolina cousin,</hi> let us clap him on the<lb/> shoulder<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and back him against all Europe<lb/> for his second round. The truth is<hi rend="bold">,</hi> th<hi rend="bold">at </hi>in<lb/> our point of view<hi rend="bold">,</hi> th<hi rend="bold">is</hi> matter of a national<lb/> literature has come to such a pass with us<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> that in some sense we must turn bullies<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> else the day is lost<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or superiority so far<lb/> beyond us<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that we can hardly <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">say it will ever be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now<hi rend="bold">,</hi> my countrymen<hi rend="bold">,</hi> as an<lb/> excellent author<hi rend="bold">,</hi> of your own flesh and<lb/> blood<hi rend="bold">,--</hi>an <hi rend="bold">un</hi>imitating<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and<hi rend="bold">,</hi> perhaps<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in his way<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">an </hi>inimitable man<hi rend="bold">--</hi>whom better can I commend<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">to </hi>you<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in the first place, than Nathaniel Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>He is one of the new<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and <hi rend="bold">far</hi> better generation<lb/> of your writer<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">T</hi>he smell of your<hi rend="bold">beeches</hi>
               <lb/> and hemlocks is upon him<hi rend="bold">; </hi>your own<lb/> broad prairies are in his soul<hi rend="bold">; </hi>and if you<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">travel</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">away</hi> inland into his deep and<lb/> noble nature<hi rend="bold">,</hi> you will hear the far roar<lb/> of his Niagara. Give not over to future<lb/> generations the glad duty of acknowledging<lb/> him for what he is<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Take that joy to<lb/> yourself, in your own generation<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and so shall<lb/> he feel those grateful <hi rend="bold">impressions</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">in </hi>him<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> that may<hi rend="bold">possibly</hi> prompt him to the full flower<lb/> of some<hi rend="bold">still</hi> greater achievement in your eyes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="21">
            <pb facs="#f020"/>
            <p>And by confessing him<hi rend="bold">,</hi> you thereby confess<lb/> others<hi rend="bold">;</hi> you brace the whole brotherhood<hi rend="bold">. </hi>For genius<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> all over the world<hi rend="bold">,</hi> stands hand in hand<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and<lb/> one shock of recognition runs the whole circle<lb/> round<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In treating of Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or rather of <lb/>Hawthorne in his writing<hi rend="bold">s</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">(</hi>for I never saw the<lb/> man<hi rend="bold">; </hi>and in the chances of a quiet <hi rend="bold">plantation</hi> life<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> remote from his haunts<hi rend="bold">,</hi> perhaps never shall<hi rend="bold">)</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">;</hi>
               <lb/> in <hi rend="bold">treating</hi> of his works<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I say<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I have thus<lb/> far omitted all mention of  his "Twice Told<lb/> Tales<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f020_z040">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f020_z040">,</reg>
               </hi>
               <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f020_z040"/>and "Scarlet Letter<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f020_z039">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f020_z039">.</reg>
               </hi> Both are excellent<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> but full of such manifold<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">strange</hi> and diffu<hi rend="bold">sive</hi>
               <lb/> beauties<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that time would <hi rend="bold">all but</hi> fail me<hi rend="bold">,</hi> to<lb/> point the half of them out. But there are<lb/> things in th<hi rend="bold">o</hi>se two books<hi rend="bold">,</hi> which<hi rend="bold">,</hi> had they been<lb/> written in England a century ago<hi rend="bold">,</hi> Nathaniel<lb/> Hawthorne had utterly displaced <hi rend="bold">many of the bright names we now revere on authority.</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/> But I am content to leave Hawthorne to<lb/> himself<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">and to the infallible finding of posterity;</hi> and however great may be the praise<lb/> I have bestowed upon him<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I feel<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that in<lb/> so doing<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I have more <hi rend="bold">served</hi> and honored<lb/> myself<hi rend="bold">,</hi> than him<hi rend="bold">.</hi> For<hi rend="bold">,</hi> at bottom<hi rend="bold">,</hi> great<lb/> excellence is praise enough to itself<hi rend="bold">;</hi> but the<lb/> feeling of<hi rend="bold"> a sincere and appreciative love <reg change="#StE" facs="#f020_z009">&amp;</reg> admiration towards</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">it</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">this</hi> is relieved by utterance; and warm<hi rend="bold">,</hi> honest praise<lb/> ever leaves a pleasant flavor in the mouth<hi rend="bold">;</hi>
               <lb/> and it is an honorable thing to <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">confess to </hi>what is honorable in others<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I cannot leave my subject yet. No<lb/> man can read a fine author<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and relish him<lb/> to his very bones<hi rend="bold">,</hi> while he reads<hi rend="bold">,</hi> without</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="22">
            <pb facs="#f021"/>
            <p/>
            <p>subsequently fancying to himself some ideal<lb/> image of the man and his mind<hi rend="bold">.</hi> And if<lb/> you rightly look for it<hi rend="bold">,</hi> you will almost<lb/> always find that <hi rend="bold">t</hi>he <hi rend="bold">author</hi> himself has some<hi rend="bold">where</hi>
               <lb/> furnished you with his own picture<hi rend="bold">.</hi>For<lb/> poets (whether in prose or verse)<hi rend="bold">,</hi> being painters<lb/> of Nature<hi rend="bold">,</hi> are like their brethren of the pencil<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>the true portrait-painters<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">who</hi>, in the multitude<lb/> of likenesses to be <hi rend="bold">sketched,</hi> do not <hi rend="bold">invariably</hi>
               <lb/> omit their own<hi rend="bold">;<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f021_z033"> &amp; </reg>in all high instances, they paint them</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">without any vanity,  though, at times, with a lurking something,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">take several pages to properly define.</hi>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <quote change="metadata#readingNH" facs="#f021_z008" source="Mosses">
               <p>
                  <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>I submit it<hi rend="bold">,</hi> then<hi rend="bold">,</hi> to those best<lb/> acquainted with the man personally<hi rend="bold">,</hi> whether<lb/> the following is not Nathaniel Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">;--</hi>
                  <lb/>and to himself<hi rend="bold">,</hi> whether something involved in<lb/> it does not express the temper of this mind<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
                  <lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">--</hi>that lasting temper of all true, candid men<lb/>
                  <hi rend="bold">--</hi>a seeker<hi rend="bold">,</hi> not a finder yet<hi rend="bold">:--</hi>
                  <lb/>
               </p>
               <p>A man now entered, in neglected attire, with the<lb/> aspect of a thinker, but somewhat too rough-hewn and brawny for a scholar<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
                  <lb/> His face was full of sturdy vigor, with some finer and keener<lb/> attribute beneath<hi rend="bold">;</hi> though harsh at first, it was tempered with the glow<lb/> of a large, warm heart, which had force enough to heat his powerful<lb/> intellect through and through. He advanced to the Intelligencer, and<lb/> looked at him with a glance of such stern sincerity, that<lb/> perhaps few secrets were beyond its scope.</p>
               <p>
                  <lb/>"<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f021_z009">"I seek for Truth",</reg> said he."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">x x x x x x</hi>
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            </quote>
            <p>Twenty-four hours have elapsed since writing the<lb/> foregoing. I have just returned from the hay mow<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> charged more and more with love and admiration of Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/> For I have just been gleaning through the <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f021_z004">m</reg>osses<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> picking up many things here and there that had previously<lb/> escaped me<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">And</hi> I found that but to glean after this man<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="23">
            <pb facs="#f022"/>
            <p>is better than to be in at the harvest of others<hi rend="bold">.</hi> To be<lb/> frank <hi rend="bold">(</hi>though<hi rend="bold">,</hi> perhaps<hi rend="bold">,</hi> rather foolish<hi rend="bold">)</hi> notwithstanding what<lb/> I wrote yesterday of these <hi rend="bold">M</hi>osses<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I had not then culled<lb/> them all<hi rend="bold">;</hi> but had<hi rend="bold">,</hi> nevertheless<hi rend="bold">,</hi> been sufficiently <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">sensible of the</hi> subtle essence<hi rend="bold">, </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">in them, as to write</hi> as I did<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/> To what infinite height of loving wonder and admiration<lb/> I may yet be borne<hi rend="bold">,</hi> when by repeatedly banquetting on<lb/> these <hi rend="bold">M</hi>osses<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I shall have thoroughly incorporated the<hi rend="bold">ir</hi>
               <lb/> whole stuff into my being<hi rend="bold">,</hi>--that<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I can not tell<hi rend="bold">.</hi> But<lb/> already I feel that this Hawthorne has dropped <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z049 #f022_z050">ger-<lb/>minous</reg> seeds into my soul<hi rend="bold">.</hi> He expands and deepens<lb/> down<hi rend="bold">,</hi> the more I contemplate him<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and further<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and <lb/>further<hi rend="bold">,</hi> shoots his strong New-England roots into<hi rend="bold">the hot soil</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">of</hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> my Southern soul.</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By careful <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>reference to the <hi rend="bold">"</hi>Table of Contents<hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z036">",</reg>
               </hi> I now <lb/>find<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that I have gone through all the sketches<hi rend="bold">;</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">but</hi> that <lb/>when I yeterday wrote<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I had not at all read two <lb/>particular pieces<hi rend="bold">,</hi> to which I now desire to call special <lb/>attention<hi rend="bold">,--</hi>"A Select Party<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z028">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z028">,</reg>
               </hi> and "Young Goodman Brown<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z027">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z027">.</reg>
               </hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Here,</hi> be it said to all those whom this poor fugitive <lb/>scrawl of mine may tempt to the purusal of the "Mosses<hi rend="bold">,</hi>" <lb/>that they must on no account suffer themselves to be <lb/>trifled with<hi rend="bold">,</hi> disappointed<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">or</hi> deceived by the <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">t</hi>riviality of many of the titles to these Sketches<hi rend="bold">.</hi> For <lb/>in more than one instance<hi rend="bold">,</hi> the title utterly belies <lb/>the piece<hi rend="bold">.</hi> It is as if rustic demjohns containing the <lb/>very best and <hi rend="bold">costliest </hi>of <hi rend="bold">F</hi>alernian and Tokay<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>were labeled "Cider<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z014">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z014">,</reg>
               </hi> "Perry<hi rend="bold">,</hi>" and "Elder-berry Wine<reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z012">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="metadata#StE" facs="#f022_z012">.</reg>
               </hi> The<lb/> truth seems to be<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that like many other geniuses<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>this <hi rend="bold">M</hi>an of <hi rend="bold">M</hi>osses takes great delight in hoodwinking <lb/>the world<hi rend="bold">,--</hi>at least<hi rend="bold">,</hi> with respect to himself<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Personally<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>I dou<hi rend="bold">b</hi>t not<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that he rather prefers to be <hi rend="bold">generally</hi> esteemed but <lb/>a so-so sort of author<hi rend="bold">;</hi> being willing to</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="24">
            <pb facs="#f023"/>
            <p>reserve the thorough and acute appreciation of what<lb/> he is<hi rend="bold">,</hi> to that party <hi rend="bold">most</hi> qualified to judge<hi rend="bold">--</hi>that is<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">to </hi>himself<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Besides<hi rend="bold">,</hi> at the bottom of their natures<hi rend="bold">,</hi> men<lb/> like Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in many things<hi rend="bold">,</hi> deem the plaudits of<lb/> the public such strong presumptive evidence of mediocrity<lb/> in the object of them<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that it would in some degree<lb/> render them doubtful of their own powers<hi rend="bold">,</hi> did they<lb/> hear much and vociferous braying concerning them in<lb/> the public pastures<hi rend="bold">.</hi> True<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I have been braying myself<lb/> (if you please to be witty enough<hi rend="bold">,</hi> to have it so) but<lb/> then I claim to be the first that has so brayed in<lb/> this particular matter<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and therefore<hi rend="bold">,</hi> while<lb/> pleading guilty to the charge<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/> still claim all the merit due to originality.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>But with whatever motive<hi rend="bold">,</hi> playful or profound<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> Nathaniel Hawthorne has chosen to entitle his pieces<lb/> in the manner he has<hi rend="bold">,</hi> it is certain<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that some of them<lb/> are directly calculated to deceive<hi rend="bold">--</hi>egregiously deceive<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> the superficial skimmer of pages<hi rend="bold">.</hi> To be downright and<lb/> candid once more<hi rend="bold">,</hi> let me cheerfully say<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that two<lb/> of these titles did dolefully dupe no less an eagle-eyed<lb/> reader than myself<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and that<hi rend="bold">,</hi> too<hi rend="bold">,</hi> after I had<lb/> been impressed with a sense of the great depth and<lb/> breadth of this American man<hi rend="bold">.</hi> "Who in the name<lb/> of thunder" <hi rend="bold">(</hi>as the country- people say in this neighborhood<hi rend="bold">)</hi>
               <lb/> "who in the name of thunder<reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z022">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z022">,</reg>
               </hi> would anticipate any<lb/> marvel in a piece entitled "Young Goodman Brown<reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z020">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z020">?</reg>
               </hi> You<lb/> would of course suppose that it was a simple little<lb/> tale<hi rend="bold">,</hi> intended as a supplement to "Goody Two Shoes<reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z017">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z017">.</reg>
               </hi> Whereas<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> it is deep as Dante<hi rend="bold">;</hi> nor can you finish it<hi rend="bold">,</hi> without<lb/> addressing the author in his own words--"It is yours to <reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z012">pene-<lb/>trate</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">,</hi> in every bosom<hi rend="bold">,</hi> the deep mystery of sin<reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z010">"</reg>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <reg change="#StE" facs="#f023_z010">.</reg>
               </hi> And with</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="25">
            <pb facs="#f024"/>
            <p>Young Goodman<hi rend="bold">,</hi> too<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in allegorical pursuit of his Puritan wife<hi rend="bold">,</hi> you cry out in your anguish<hi rend="bold">,--</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">"</hi>'Faith!<hi rend="bold">'</hi> shouted Goodman Brown, in a voice of agony<lb/> and desperation; and the echoes of the forest mocked him, crying--<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">'</hi>Faith! Faith!<hi rend="bold">'</hi> as if bewildered wretches were seeking her all through<lb/> the wilderness."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Now this same piece<hi rend="bold">,</hi> entitled "Young Goodman Brown<hi rend="bold">,</hi>"<lb/> is one of the two that I had not all read yesterday<hi rend="bold">;</hi>
               <lb/> and I allude to it now<hi rend="bold">,</hi> because it is<hi rend="bold">, </hi>in itself<hi rend="bold">,</hi> such a<lb/> strong positive illustration of that blackness in Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> which I had assumed from the mere<hi rend="bold">occasional </hi>shadows of it<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> as revealed in several of the other sketches<hi rend="bold">.</hi> But had I<lb/> previously perused "Young Goodman Brown<hi rend="bold">,</hi>" I should have been<lb/> at no pains to draw the conclusion<hi rend="bold">,</hi> which I came to<hi rend="bold">, </hi>at<lb/> a time<hi rend="bold">,</hi> when I was ignorant that the book contained<lb/> one such direct and unqualified manifestation of it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The other piece of the two referred to<hi rend="bold">,</hi> is entitled "A<lb/> Select Party<hi rend="bold">,</hi>" which<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in my first simplicity upon <reg facs="#f024_z015 #f024_z016">originally </reg>
               <orig facs="#f024_z015 #f024_z016">origin-<lb/>ally </orig>taking hold of the book<hi rend="bold">,</hi> I fancied must treat of some<lb/> pumpkin-pie party in Old Salem<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or some <hi rend="bold">chowder party</hi> on<lb/> Cape Cod<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Whereas<hi rend="bold">,</hi> by all the gods of <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">Peedee!</hi> it is the<lb/> sweetest and sublimest thing that has been written<lb/> since Spencer wrote<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Nay, there is nothing in Spencer that<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">surpasses</hi> it<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">perhaps, nothing that equals it. </hi>And the test is this<hi rend="bold">:</hi> read any canto in<lb/> "The Faery Queen<hi rend="bold">,</hi>" and then read "A Select Party<hi rend="bold">,</hi>" and decide<lb/> which pleases you the most<hi rend="bold">,--</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">that is, if you are qualified to judge. </hi>Do not be frightened<lb/> at this<hi rend="bold">;</hi> for when Spencer was alive<hi rend="bold">,</hi> he was thought of<lb/> very much as Hawthorne is now<hi rend="bold">, --</hi> was generally<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">accounted </hi>just such a "gentle" harmless man<hi rend="bold">.</hi> It may be<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> that to common eyes<hi rend="bold">,</hi> the sublimity of Hawthorne seems<lb/> lost in his sweetness<hi rend="bold">, --</hi> as perhaps in this same "Select Party"<lb/> of his<hi rend="bold">;</hi> for whom<hi rend="bold">,</hi> he has builded so august a dome of<lb/>sunset clouds<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and served them on richer plate<hi rend="bold">,</hi> than</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="26">
            <pb facs="#f025"/>
            <p>Belshazzar's when he banquetted his lords in Babylon<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>But my <hi rend="bold">chief </hi>business now<hi rend="bold">,</hi> is to point out a <lb/>particular page in this piece<hi rend="bold">,</hi> having reference to an honored<lb/>guest<hi rend="bold">,</hi> who <hi rend="bold">under </hi>the name of "The Master Genius"<lb/>but in the guise <hi rend="bold">of </hi>"ayoung man of poor attire<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> with no insignia of rank or acknowledged eminence<hi rend="bold">",</hi>
               <lb/> is introduced to the Man of Fancy<hi rend="bold">,</hi> who is the giver of <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">the </hi>feast<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Now the page having reference to this<lb/> "Master Genius<hi rend="bold">,</hi>" so happily expresses much of what I yesterday<lb/> wrote<hi rend="bold">,</hi> touching the coming of the literary Shiloh of<lb/> America<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that I cannot but be charmed by the<lb/> coincidence<hi rend="bold">;</hi> especially<hi rend="bold">,</hi> when it shows such a parity of idea<hi rend="bold">s</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">,</hi> at <hi rend="bold">least,</hi>in this one <hi rend="bold">point,</hi> between a man<lb/> like Hawthorne and a <hi rend="bold">man</hi>like me<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>And here<hi rend="bold">, </hi>let me throw out another conceit of<lb/> mine touching this American Shiloh<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or "Master Genius<hi rend="bold">,"</hi>
               <lb/> as Hawthorne calls him<hi rend="bold">.</hi> May it not be<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that this<lb/> commanding mind has not been<hi rend="bold">,</hi> is not<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and never will<lb/> be<hi rend="bold">, </hi>individually developed in any one man<hi rend="bold">?</hi> And would<lb/> it<hi rend="bold">,</hi> indeed<hi rend="bold">, </hi>appear so unreasonable to suppose<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that this<lb/> great fullness and overflowing may be<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or may be destined<lb/> to be<hi rend="bold">, </hi>shared by a plurality of men of genius<hi rend="bold">?</hi> Surely<hi rend="bold">,</hi> to<lb/> take the very greatest example on record<hi rend="bold">,</hi> Shakespeare cannot<lb/>be regarded as in himself the concretion of all the genius<lb/> of his time<hi rend="bold">;</hi> nor as so immeasurably beyond Marlow<hi rend="bold">,</hi> Webster<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> Ford<hi rend="bold">,</hi> Beaumont<hi rend="bold">,</hi> Jonson<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that those great men can be<lb/> said to share none of his<hi rend="bold">power?</hi> For one<hi rend="bold">, </hi>I conceive <lb/>that there were dramatists in Elizabeth's day<hi rend="bold">,</hi> between<lb/> whom <reg facs="#f025_z026">and </reg>Shakespeare the distance was by no means great<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Let<lb/> anyone, hitherto little acquainted with those neglected old <lb/>authors<hi rend="bold">, </hi>for the first time read them thoroughly<hi rend="bold">,</hi> or even<lb/> read Charles Lamb's Specimens of them<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and he will</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="27">
            <pb facs="#f026"/>
            <p>be amazed at the wondrous ability of those<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Anaks of </hi>men<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and shocked at this renewed<lb/> example of the fact<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that Fortune has more to do with<lb/> fame than merit, -- though<hi rend="bold">,</hi> without merit<hi rend="bold">, </hi>lasting fame there can be none<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheless<hi rend="bold">,</hi> it would argue too illy of my country<lb/> were this maxim to hold good concerning Nathaniel<lb/> Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">, </hi>a man<hi rend="bold">,</hi> who already<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in some few minds<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/> has shed "such a light<hi rend="bold">,</hi> as never illuminates the earth,<lb/> save when a great heart burns as the household fire<lb/> of a grand intellect."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The words are his,<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>"<hi rend="bold">-- </hi>in the "Select Party<hi rend="bold">";</hi> and they<lb/> are a magnificent setting to a <hi rend="bold">coincident sentiment </hi>of<lb/> my own<hi rend="bold">,</hi> but <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"/>
               <hi rend="bold">ramblingly</hi>expressed yesterday<hi rend="bold">, </hi>in reference to him<lb/>self<hi rend="bold">.</hi> Gainsay it who will<hi rend="bold">,</hi> as I now write<hi rend="bold">, </hi>I am <hi rend="bold">P</hi>osterity<lb/> speaking by proxy<hi rend="bold"> -- </hi>and after times will make it more<lb/> than good<hi rend="bold">,</hi> when I declare <hi rend="bold">--</hi> that the American<hi rend="bold">, </hi>who up<lb/> to the present day<hi rend="bold">,</hi> has evinced<hi rend="bold">,</hi> in Literature<hi rend="bold">,</hi> the largest<lb/> brain <hi rend="bold">with </hi>the largest heart<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that man is Nathaniel<lb/> Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">. </hi>Moreover<hi rend="bold">,</hi> that whatever Nathaniel Hawthorne<lb/> may hereafter write<hi rend="bold">,</hi> "The Mosses from an Old Manse" will<lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">be</hi> ultimately accounted his masterpiece<hi rend="bold">. </hi>For there is<lb/> a sure<hi rend="bold">,</hi> though a secret sign in some works which <lb/>prove the culmination of the powers <hi rend="bold">(only the developable ones, however)</hi> that produced <lb/>them<hi rend="bold">.</hi> But I am by no means desirous of the <lb/>glory of a prophet<hi rend="bold">.</hi> I pray Heaven that Hawthorne may <lb/>yet prove me an impostor in this prediction<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
               <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">Especially, as I somehow cling to the<lb/> strange fancy, that, in all men, hiddenly reside<lb/> certain wondrous, occult properties -- as in some </hi>
               <hi rend="bold">plants <reg facs="#f026_z004">and</reg>
               </hi>
               <hi rend="bold"> minerals -- <lb/>which by some happy but very rare accident (as bronze was <lb/> discovered by the melting of the iron and brass in the burning of Corinth)<lb/> may chance to be called forth here on earth; not entirely <lb/>waiting for their better discovery in the more congenial, <lb/>blessed atmosphere of heaven.<lb/>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more -- for it is hard to be finite<lb/> upon an infinite subject, and all <hi rend="bold">subjects </hi>are infinite.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="leaf" n="28">
            <pb facs="#f027"/>
            <p> By some people<hi rend="bold">,</hi>this entire <lb/>
               <hi rend="bold">scrawl of mine</hi>may be esteemed altogether unnecessary<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
               <lb/>inasmuch<hi rend="bold">, </hi>"as years ago"<hi rend="bold"> (they may say) </hi>"we found out<lb/> the rich and rare stuff in this Hawthorne<hi rend="bold">,</hi> whom<lb/> you now par<hi rend="bold">ade forth</hi>, as if only yourself were<lb/> the discoverer of this <hi rend="bold">Portuguese diamond</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">in our</hi>
               <lb/>Literature." -- But even granting<lb/> all this<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and adding to it, the assumption that the<lb/> books of Hawthorne have sold by the five-thousand<hi rend="bold">,--</hi> what does <hi rend="bold">that</hi>
               <hi rend="bold">signify?--</hi> They should be<lb/> sold by the hundred-thousand<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and read by the<lb/> million<hi rend="bold">;</hi> and admired by every one who is capable <lb/>of admiration.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
