<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>01 - John Marr</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded in TEI XML for the Melville Electronic Library</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>John Marr and Other Sailors</title>
               <author>Herman Melville</author>
               <publisher>The De Vinne Press</publisher>
               <date>1888</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
                  <body>
                     <div type="prose-headnote">
                        <p>JOHN MARR, toward the close of the last cent-
                        ury born in America of a mother unknown, 
                        and from boyhood up to maturity a sailor under 
                        divers flags, disabled at last from further mari-
                        time life by a crippling wound received at close quarters with pirates of the Keys, eventually betakes himself for a livelihood to less active employment ashore. There, too, he transfers his 
                        rambling disposition acquired as a seafarer.
                        After a variety of removals, at first as a sailmaker from sea-port to sea-port, then adventurously inland as a rough bench-carpenter, he, 
                        finally, in the last-named capacity, settles down 
                        about the year 1838 upon what was then a frontier-prairie, sparsely sprinkled with small oak-
                        groves and yet fewer log-houses of a little colony but recently from one of our elder inland States. 
                        Here, putting a period to his rovings, he marries.
                        Ere long a fever, the bane of new settlements 
                        on teeming loam, and whose sallow livery was 
                        certain to show itself, after an interval, in the 
                        complexions of too many of these people, carries 
                        off his young wife and infant child. In one 
                        coffin, put together by his own hands, they are 
                        committed with meager rites to the earth-another mound, though a small one, in the wide 
                        prairie, nor far from where the mound-builders 
                        of a race only conjecturable had left their pottery and bones, one common clay, under a strange terrace serpentine in form.
                        With an honest stillness in his general mien-
                        swarthy and black-browed, with eyes that could 
                        soften or flash, but never harden, yet disclosing 
                        at times a melancholy depth-this kinless man 
                        had affections which, once placed, not readily 
                        could be dislodged or resigned to a substituted 
                        object. Being now arrived at middle-life, he resolves never to quit the soil that holds the only 
                        beings ever connected with him by love in the 
                        family tie. His log-house he lets to a new-comer,
                        one glad enough to get it, and dwells with the 
                        household.</p>
                        
                        <p>While the acuter sense of his bereavement becomes mollified by time, the void at heart abides. 
                        Fain, if possible, would he fill that void by cultivating social relations yet nearer than before with 
                        a people whose lot he purposes sharing to the end 
                        -relations superadded to that mere work-a-day 
                        bond arising from participation in the same outward hardships, making reciprocal helpfulness a 
                        matter of course. But here, and nobody to blame, 
                        he is obstructed.</p>
                        
                        <p>More familiarly to consort, men of a practical 
                        turn must sympathetically converse, and upon 
                        topics of real life. But, whether as to persons or 
                        events, one cannot always be talking about the 
                        present, much less speculating about the future ; 
                        one must needs recur to the past, which, with the 
                        mass of men, where the past is in any personal 
                        way a common inheritance, supplies to most practical natures the basis of sympathetic communion.
                        But the past of John Marr was not the past of 
                        these pioneers. Their hands had rested on the 
                        plow-tail, his upon the ship's helm.  They knew
                        but their own kind and their own usages ;  to him had been revealed something of the checkered 
                        globe. So limited unavoidably was the mental 
                        reach, and by consequence the range of sympathy, 
                        in this particular band of domestic emigrants, 
                        hereditary tillers of the soil, that the ocean, but a 
                        hearsay to their fathers, had now through yet 
                        deeper inland removal become to themselves little 
                        more than a rumor traditional and vague.
                        They were a staid people ;  staid through habituation to monotonous hardship ; ascetics by necessity not less than through moral bias ; nearly all of them sincerely, however narrowly, religious. 
                        They were kindly at need, after their fashion ; 
                        but to a man wonted-as John Marr in his previous homeless sojournings could not but have 
                        been-to the free-and-easy tavern-clubs affording 
                        cheap recreation of an evening in certain old and 
                        comfortable sea-port towns of that time, and yet 
                        more familiar with the companionship afloat of 
                        the sailors of the same period, something was 
                        lacking. That something was geniality, the flower 
                        of life springing from some sense of joy in it, 
                        more or less. This their lot could not give to
                        these hard-working endurers of the dispiriting 
                        malaria,-men to whom a holiday never came,-
                        and they had too much of uprightness and no art 
                        at all or desire to affect what they did not really 
                        feel. At a corn-husking, their least grave of 
                        gatherings, did the lone-hearted mariner seek to 
                        divert his own thoughts from sadness, and in 
                        some degree interest theirs, by adverting to aught 
                        removed from the crosses and trials of their personal surroundings, naturally enough he would 
                        slide into some marine story or picture, but would 
                        soon recoil upon himself and be silent, finding no 
                        encouragement to proceed. Upon one such occasion an elderly man-a blacksmith, and at Sunday 
                        gatherings an earnest exhorter-honestly said to 
                        him, "Friend, we know nothing of that here."
                        Such unresponsiveness in one's fellow-creatures 
                        set apart from factitious life, and by their vocation-in those days little helped by machinery-
                        standing, as it were, next of kin to Nature ;  this, 
                        to John Marr, seemed of a piece with the apathy 
                        of Nature herself as envisaged to him here on a 
                        prairie where none but the perished mound- builders had as yet left a durable mark.</p>
                        
                        <p>The remnant of Indians thereabout-all but exterminated in their recent and final war with regular white troops, a war waged by the Red Men 
                        for their native soil and natural rights-had been 
                        coerced into the occupancy of wilds not very far 
                        beyond the Mississippi-wilds then, but now the 
                        seats of municipalities and States. Prior to that, 
                        the bisons, once streaming countless in processional herds, or browsing as in an endless battle-
                        line over these vast aboriginal pastures, had 
                        retreated, dwindled in number, before the hunters, in main a race distinct from the agricultural 
                        pioneers, though generally their advance-guard. 
                        Such a double exodus of man and beast left the 
                        plain a desert, green or blossoming indeed, but 
                        almost as forsaken as the Siberian Obi.  Save the 
                        prairie-hen, sometimes startled from its lurking-
                        place in the rank grass; and, in their migratory 
                        season, pigeons, high overhead on the wing, in 
                        dense multitudes eclipsing the day like a pass-
                        ing storm-cloud ;  save these-there being no wide 
                        woods with their underwood-birds were strangely few.</p>
                        
                        <p>Blank stillness would for hours reign unbroken
                        on this prairie. "It is the bed of a dried-up sea," 
                        said the companionless sailor-no geologist-to 
                        himself, musing at twilight upon the fixed undulations of that immense  alluvial expanse bounded 
                        only by the horizon, and missing there the stir 
                        that, to alert eyes and ears, animates at all times 
                        the apparent solitudes of the deep.</p>
                        
                        <p>But a scene quite at variance with one's antecedents may yet prove suggestive of them. Hooped 
                        round by a level rim, the prairie was to John Marr 
                        a reminder of ocean.</p>
                        
                        <p>With some of his former shipmates, chums on 
                        certain cruises, he had contrived, prior to this last 
                        and more remote removal, to keep up a little correspondence at odd intervals. But from tidings of anybody or any sort he, in common with the other 
                        settlers, was now cut off ;  quite cut off, except 
                        from such news as might be conveyed over the 
                        grassy billows by the last-arrived prairie-schooner- 
                        the vernacular term, in those parts and times, for 
                        the emigrant-wagon arched high over with sail-
                        cloth and voyaging across the vast champaign. 
                        There was no reachable post-office as yet ;  not even 
                        the rude little receptive box with lid and leather 
                        hinges, set up at convenient intervals on a stout 
                        stake along some solitary green way, affording a 
                        perch for birds, and which, later in the unintermitting advance of the frontier, would perhaps 
                        decay into a mossy monument, attesting yet another successive overleaped limit of civilized life ; a life which in America can to-day hardly be said 
                        to have any western bound but the ocean that 
                        washes Asia. Throughout these plains, now in 
                        places overpopulous with towns overopulent ; 
                        sweeping plains, elsewhere fenced off in every 
                        direction into flourishing farms-pale townsmen 
                        and hale farmers alike, in part, the descendants 
                        of the first sallow settlers ; a region that half a 
                        century ago produced little for the sustenance 
                        of man, but to-day launching its superabundant 
                        wheat-harvest on the world ; -of this prairie, now 
                        everywhere intersected with wire and rail, hardly 
                        can it be said that at the period here written of 
                        there was so much as a traceable road. To the 
                        long-distance traveler the oak-groves, wide apart, 
                        and varying in compass and form ;  these, with 
                        recent settlements, yet more widely separate, offered some landmarks ; but otherwise he steered  by the sun.  In early midsummer, even going but 
                        from one log-encampment to the next, a journey 
                        it might be of hours or good part of a day, travel 
                        was much like navigation.  In some more enriched 
                        depressions between the long, green, graduated 
                        swells, smooth as those of ocean becalmed receiving and subduing to its own tranquillity the voluminous surge raised by some far-off hurricane 
                        of days previous, here one would catch the first 
                        indication of advancing strangers either in the 
                        distance, as a far sail at sea, by the glistening 
                        white canvas of the wagon, the wagon itself wading through the rank vegetation and hidden by it, or, failing that, when near to, in the ears of the team, 
                        peeking, if  not above the tall tiger-lilies, yet above 
                        the yet taller grass.</p>
                        
                        <p>Luxuriant, this wilderness ;  but, to its denizen, a 
                        friend left behind anywhere in the world seemed 
                        not alone absent to sight, but an absentee from 
                        existence.</p>
                        
                        <p>Though John Marr's shipmates could not all 
                        have departed life, yet as subjects of meditation 
                        they were like phantoms of the dead.  As the 
                        growing sense of his environment threw him 
                        more and more upon retrospective musings, these 
                        phantoms, next to those of his wife and child, became spiritual companions, losing something of 
                        their first indistinctness and putting on at last 
                        a dim semblance of mute life ;  and they were lit 
                        by that aureola circling over any object of the 
                        affections in the past for reunion with which an 
                        imaginative heart passionately yearns.</p>
                        
                        <p>He invokes these visionary ones,-striving, as 
                        it were, to get into verbal communion with them, 
                        or, under yet stronger illusion, reproaching them 
                        for their silence :-</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Since as in night's deck-watch ye show,</l>
                           <l>Why, lads, so silent here to me,</l>
                           <l>Your watchmate of times long ago?</l>
                        </lg>
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Once, for all the darkling sea,</l>
                           <l>You your voices raised how clearly,</l>
                           <l>Striking in when tempest sung;</l>
                           <l>Hoisting up the storm-sail cheerly,</l>
                           <l>Life is storm—let storm! you rung.</l>
                        </lg>
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Taking things as fated merely,</l>
                           <l>Child-like though the world ye spanned;</l>
                           <l>Nor holding unto life too dearly,</l>
                           <l>Ye who hold your lives in hand—</l>
                           <l>Skimmers, who on oceans four</l>
                           <l>Petrels were, and larks ashore.</l>
                        </lg>
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>O, not from memory lightly flung,</l>
                           <l>Forgot, like strains no more availing,</l>
                           <l>The heart to music haughtier strung;</l>
                           <l>Nay, frequent near me, never staleing,</l>
                           <l>Whose good feeling kept ye young.</l>
                           <l>Like tides that enter creek or stream,</l>
                           <l>Ye come, ye visit me, or seem</l>
                           <l>Swimming out from seas of faces,</l>
                           <l>Alien myriads memory traces,</l>
                           <l>To enfold me in a dream!</l>
                        </lg>
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>I yearn as ye. But rafts that strain,</l>
                           <l>Parted, shall they lock again?</l>
                           <l>Twined we were, entwined, then riven,</l>
                           <l>Ever to new embracements driven,</l>
                           <l>Shifting gulf-weed of the main!</l>
                           <l>And how if one here shift no more,</l>
                           <l>Lodged by the flinging surge ashore?</l>
                        </lg>
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Nor less, as now, in eve's decline,</l>
                           <l>Your shadowy fellowship is mine.</l>
                           <l>Ye float around me, form and feature:—</l>
                           <l>Tattooings, ear-rings, love-locks curled;</l>
                           <l>Barbarians of man's simpler nature,</l>
                           <l>Unworldly servers of the world.</l>
                           <l>Yea, present all, and dear to me,</l>
                           <l>Though shades, or scouring China's sea.</l>
                        </lg>
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Whither, whither, merchant-sailors,</l>
                           <l>Whitherward now in roaring gales?</l>
                           <l>Competing still, ye huntsman-whalers,</l>
                           <l>In leviathan's wake what boat prevails?</l>
                           <l>And man-of-war's men, whereaway?</l>
                           <l>If now no dinned drum beat to quarters</l>
                           <l>On the wilds of midnight waters—</l>
                           <l>Foemen looming through the spray;</l>
                           <l>Do yet your gangway lanterns, streaming,</l>
                           <l>Vainly strive to pierce below,</l>
                           <l>When, tilted from the slant plank gleaming,</l>
                           <l>A brother you see to darkness go?</l>
                        </lg>
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>But, gunmates lashed in shotted canvas,</l>
                           <l>If where long watch-below ye keep,</l>
                           <l>Never the shrill <quote>“All hands up hammocks!”</quote></l>
                           <l>Breaks the spell that charms your sleep,</l>
                           <l>And summoning trumps might vainly call,</l>
                           <l>And booming guns implore—</l>
                           <l>A beat, a heart-beat musters all,</l>
                           <l>One heart-beat at heart-core.</l>
                           <l>It musters. But to clasp, retain;</l>
                           <l>To see you at the halyards main—</l>
                           <l>To hear your chorus once again!</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
