<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>120 The Deck</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="120-the-deck"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1519948208442-ixff2zeyljl-5c68a0c9315b8b5715d4b719265dfb8e%2FMD_Amer_0599.jpg"/>

			<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 120</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">THE DECK TOWARDS THE END OF THE FIRST NIGHT WATCH.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Ahab standing by the helm. Starbuck approaching him.</hi></head>



</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“<hi rend="smallcaps">We</hi> must send down the main-top-sail yard, sir. The band is working loose, and the lee lift is half-stranded. <ref target="#ref_18632">Shall I strike it, sir</ref><note xml:id="ref_18632">send down the main-top-sail yard . . . band . . . is half-stranded . . . strike it: Starbuck advises lowering (striking) the main-top-sail yard, a heavy spar, which is in danger of falling (and doing much damage) because the unraveling lee-lift (the rope leading from the mast to an iron band around the yardarm, supporting its weight) may let go. Making things worse, the band itself may break loose.</note>?”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Strike nothing; lash it. If I had <ref target="#ref_18624">sky-sail poles</ref><note xml:id="ref_18624">sky-sail poles: the highest parts of masts, supporting the light, fair-weather skysails and their yards.</note>, I’d sway them up now.”
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1519948227541-2twqhaajgvd-5c68a0c9315b8b5715d4b719265dfb8e%2FMD_Amer_0600.jpg"/>
</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Sir?—in God’s name!—sir?”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Well.”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“The anchors are working, sir. Shall I get them inboard?”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Strike nothing, and stir nothing, but lash everything. The wind rises, but it has not got up to my <ref target="#ref_18626">table-lands</ref><note xml:id="ref_18626">table-lands: high plateaus.</note> yet. Quick, and see to it.—By masts and keels! he takes me for the hunchbacked skipper of some <ref target="#ref_18627"><ref type="reference" target="glossary#coasting_smack"><w xml:id="coasting_smack">coasting smack</w></ref></ref><note xml:id="ref_18627"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1122" type="artwork">coasting smack</name>: small fishing boat that stays close to shore.</note>. Send down my main-top-sail yard! Ho, <ref target="#ref_18629">gluepots</ref><note xml:id="ref_18629">gluepots: slang for parson, addressed to Starbuck.</note>! Loftiest trucks were made for wildest winds, and this brain-truck of mine now sails amid the cloud-scud. Shall I strike that? Oh, none but cowards send down their brain-trucks in tempest time. What a <ref target="#ref_18630">hooroosh</ref><note xml:id="ref_18630">hooroosh: wild uproar.</note> aloft there! I would e’en take it for sublime, did I not know that the colic is a noisy malady. Oh, <ref target="#ref_18633">take medicine, take medicine!</ref><note xml:id="ref_18633">take medicine!”: Recalling King Lear 3.4.33, “take physic, pomp.”</note>”</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
