<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>17 The Ramadan</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div   xml:id="ch17-the-ramadan"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 17</head> <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517805107242-1h9re4xss3i-f60020416a919f64f1647d0cf7a5bbfc%2FMD_Amer_0128.jpg"/>
<lb/>
				<head type="sub-head" rend="center">THE RAMADAN.</head>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">As</hi> Queequeg’s <ref target="#ref_21390">Ramadan</ref><note xml:id="ref_21390">Ramadan: Some the earliest observances of Ramadan in the US took place among African slaves. In 1819 Charles Willson Peale painted his  <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1054">Portrait of Yarrow Mamout (Muhammed Yaro)</ref>, of a former slave and community leader in Georgetown, DC.</note><ref target="#MDch17Note1"><hi rend="bold">, or Fasting and Humiliation, </hi></ref><note xml:id="MDch17Note1">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">or Fasting and Humiliation</hi> // Ramadan is the ninth month in the Muslim calendar, and a period devoted to daytime fasting, sexual abstinence, and verbal restraint. Ishmael uses the word figuratively to mean “fasting and humiliation”; however, “humiliation” is not a part of the Islamic rituals related to Ramadan. In the British edition, “or Fasting and Humiliation” has been removed, probably by Melville: the phrase is neither accurate nor in keeping with Ishmael’s subsequent argument for tolerance. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note> <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0149.jpg"/> was to continue all day, I did not choose to disturb him till towards night-fall; for I cherish the greatest respect towards everybody’s religious obligations, never mind how comical, and could not find it in my heart to undervalue even a congregation of ants worshipping a toad-stool; or those other creatures in certain parts of our earth, who with a degree of <ref target="#ref_16202">footmanism</ref><note xml:id="ref_16202">footmanism: servile obedience.</note> quite unprecedented in other planets, bow down before the torso of a deceased landed proprietor merely on account of the inordinate possessions yet owned and rented in his name.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I say, we good Presbyterian Christians should be charitable in these things, and not fancy ourselves so vastly superior to other mortals, pagans and what not, because of their half-crazy conceits on these subjects. There was Queequeg, now, certainly entertaining the most absurd notions about Yojo and his Ramadan;—but what of that? Queequeg thought he knew what he was about, I suppose; he seemed to be content; and there let him rest. All our arguing with him would not avail; let him be, I say: and Heaven have mercy on us all—Presbyterians and Pagans alike—for we are all somehow dreadfully cracked about the head, and sadly need mending.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Towards evening, when I felt assured that all his performances and rituals must be over, I went up to his room and knocked at the door; but no answer. I tried to open it, but it was fastened inside. “Queequeg,” said I softly through the key-hole:—all silent. “I say, Queequeg! why don’t you speak? It’s I—Ishmael.” But all remained still as before. I <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517805129890-v2cktu5bvbc-f60020416a919f64f1647d0cf7a5bbfc%2FMD_Amer_0129.jpg"/> began to grow alarmed. I had allowed him such abundant time; I thought he might have had an <ref target="#ref_16203">apoplectic fit</ref><note xml:id="ref_16203">apoplectic fit: stroke.</note>. I looked through the key-hole; but the door opening into an odd corner of the room, the key-hole prospect was but a crooked and <ref target="#ref_16204">sinister</ref><note xml:id="ref_16204">sinister: leftward, but implying ominous.</note> one. I could only see part of the foot-board of the bed and a line of the wall, but nothing more. I was surprised to behold resting against the wall the wooden shaft of Queequeg’s harpoon, which the landlady the evening previous had taken from him, before our mounting to the chamber. That’s strange, thought I; but at any rate, since the harpoon stands yonder, and he seldom or never goes abroad without it, therefore he must be inside here, and no possible mistake.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Queequeg!—Queequeg!”—all still. Something must have happened. Apoplexy! I tried to burst open the door; but it stubbornly resisted. Running down stairs, I quickly stated my suspicions to the first person I met—the chamber-maid. “La! La!” she cried, “I thought something must be the matter. I went to make the bed after breakfast, and the door was locked; and not a mouse to be heard; and it’s been just so silent ever since. But I thought, may be, you had both gone off and locked your baggage in for safe keeping. La! La, ma’am!—Mistress! murder! Mrs. Hussey! apoplexy!”—and with these cries, she ran towards the kitchen, I following.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Mrs. Hussey soon appeared, with a mustard-pot in one hand and a vinegar-cruet in the other, having just broken away from the occupation of attending to the <ref target="#ref_16205">castors</ref><note xml:id="ref_16205">castors: holders for condiment containers such as the pot and cruet.</note>, and scolding her little black boy meantime.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Wood-house!” cried I, “which way to it? Run for God’s sake, and fetch something to pry open the door—the axe!—the axe!—he’s had a stroke; depend upon it!”—and so saying I was unmethodically rushing up stairs again empty-handed, when Mrs. Hussey interposed the mustard-pot and vinegar-cruet, and the entire castor of her countenance.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“What’s the matter with you, young man?”
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517805150463-02zol58i3ldg-f60020416a919f64f1647d0cf7a5bbfc%2FMD_Amer_0130.jpg"/>
</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Get the axe! For God’s sake, run for the doctor, some one, while I pry it open!”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Look here,” said the landlady, quickly putting down the vinegar-cruet, so as to have one hand free; “look here; are you talking about prying open any of my doors?”—and with that she seized my arm. “What’s the matter with you? What’s the matter with you, shipmate?”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In as calm, but rapid a manner as possible, I gave her to understand the whole case. Unconsciously clapping the <ref target="#MDch17Note2">vinegar-cruet</ref><note xml:id="MDch17Note2">clapping the <hi rend="bold">vinegar-cruet</hi> to one side of her nose: Since Mrs. Hussey has just put the vinegar-cruet down and holds only a mustard-pot, she cannot, in fact, put the vinegar-cruet to her nose. The editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> address this inconsistency by changing “vinegar-cruet” to “mustard-pot.” However, this problem is not easily fixed through textual emendation, for it is just as likely that Melville might have intended Mrs. Hussey to put the mustard-pot down earlier in the scene so that she would clap the more astringent vinegar-cruet to her nose. Rather than try to fix the dilemma one way or the other, MEL leaves the text unaltered.</note> to one side of her nose, she ruminated for an instant; then exclaimed—“No! I haven’t seen it since I put it there.” Running to a little closet under the landing of the stairs, she glanced in, and returning, told me that Queequeg’s harpoon was missing. “He’s killed himself,” she cried. “It’s unfort’nate Stiggs done over again—there goes another counterpane—God pity his poor mother!—it will be the ruin of my house. Has the poor lad a sister? Where’s that girl?—there, Betty, go to Snarles the Painter, and tell him to paint me a sign, with—‘no suicides permitted here, and no smoking in the parlor;’—might as well kill both birds at once. Kill? The Lord be merciful to his ghost! What’s that noise there? You, young man, avast there!”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">And running up after me, she caught me as I was again trying to force open the door.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“I won’t allow it; I won’t have my premises spoiled. Go for the locksmith, there’s one about a mile from here. But avast!” putting her hand in her side-pocket, “here’s a key that’ll fit, I guess; let’s see.” And with that, she turned it in the lock; but, alas! Queequeg’s supplemental bolt remained unwithdrawn within.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Have to burst it open,” said I, and was running down the entry a little, for a good start, when the landlady caught at me, again vowing I should not break down her premises; but I tore from her, and with a sudden bodily rush dashed myself full against the mark.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517805175402-1t071l79odpj-f60020416a919f64f1647d0cf7a5bbfc%2FMD_Amer_0131.jpg"/> With a prodigious noise the door flew open, and the knob slamming against the wall, sent the plaster to the ceiling; and there, good heavens! there sat Queequeg, altogether cool and self-collected; right in the middle of the room; squatting on his hams, and holding Yojo on top of his head. He looked neither one way nor the other way, but sat like a carved image with scarce a sign of active life.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Queequeg,” said I, going up to him, “Queequeg, what’s the matter with you?”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“He hain’t been a sittin’ so all day, has he?” said the landlady.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But all we said, not a word could we drag out of him; I almost felt like pushing him over, so as to change his position, for it was almost intolerable, it seemed so painfully and unnaturally constrained; especially, as in all probability he had been sitting so for upwards of eight or ten hours, going too without his regular meals.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“Mrs. Hussey,” said I, “he’s <hi rend="italic">alive</hi> at all events; so leave us, if you please, and I will see to this strange affair myself.”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Closing the door upon the landlady, I endeavored to prevail upon Queequeg to take a chair; but in vain. There he sat; and all I could do—for all my polite arts and <ref target="#ref_16206">blandishments</ref><note xml:id="ref_16206">blandishments: kind words of persuasion.</note>—he would not move a peg, nor say a single word, nor even look at me, nor notice my presence in any the slightest way.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I wonder, thought I, if this can possibly be a part of his Ramadan; do they fast on their hams that way in his native island. It must be so; yes, it’s part of his creed, I suppose; well, then, let him rest; he’ll get up sooner or later, no doubt. It can’t last for ever, thank God, and his Ramadan only comes once a year; and I don’t believe it’s very punctual then.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I went down to supper. After sitting a long time listening to the long stories of some sailors who had just come from a plum-pudding voyage, as they called it (that is, a short whaling-voyage in a schooner or <ref type="reference" target="glossary#brig"><w xml:id="brig">brig</w></ref>, confined to the north of the <ref target="#ref_16207">line</ref><note xml:id="ref_16207">line: equator.</note>, <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517805211570-8yb4e5l77g7-f60020416a919f64f1647d0cf7a5bbfc%2FMD_Amer_0132.jpg"/> in the Atlantic Ocean only); after listening to these plum-puddingers till nearly eleven o’clock, I went up stairs to go to bed, feeling quite sure by this time Queequeg must certainly have brought his Ramadan to a termination. But no; there he was just where I had left him; he had not stirred an inch. I began to grow vexed with him; it seemed so downright senseless and insane to be sitting there all day and half the night on his hams in a cold room, holding a piece of wood on his head.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“For heaven’s sake, Queequeg, get up and shake yourself; get up and have some supper. You’ll starve; you’ll kill yourself, Queequeg.” But not a word did he reply.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Despairing of him, therefore, I determined to go to bed and to sleep; and no doubt, before a great while, he would follow me. But previous to turning in, I took my heavy bearskin jacket, and threw it over him, as it promised to be a very cold night; and he had nothing but his ordinary <ref target="#ref_16208">round jacket</ref><note xml:id="ref_16208">round jacket: short, tight jacket.</note> on. For some time, do all I would, I could not get into the faintest doze. I had blown out the candle; and the mere thought of Queequeg—not four feet off—sitting there in that uneasy position, stark alone in the cold and dark; this made me really wretched. Think of it; sleeping all night in the same room with a wide awake pagan on his hams in this dreary, unaccountable Ramadan!

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But somehow I dropped off at last, and knew nothing more till break of day; when, looking over the bedside, there squatted Queequeg, as if he had been screwed down to the floor. But as soon as the first glimpse of sun entered the window, up he got, with stiff and grating joints, but with a cheerful look; limped towards me where I lay; pressed his forehead again against mine; and said his Ramadan was over.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Now, as I before hinted, I have no objection to any person’s religion, be it what it may, so long as that person does not kill <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517805245564-jpu4k89i0km-f60020416a919f64f1647d0cf7a5bbfc%2FMD_Amer_0133.jpg"/> or insult any other person, because that other person don’t believe it also. But when a man’s religion becomes really frantic; when it is a positive torment to him; and, in fine, makes this earth of ours an uncomfortable inn to lodge in; then I think it high time to take that individual aside and argue the point with him.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">And just so I now did with Queequeg. “Queequeg,” said I, “get into bed now, and lie and listen to me.” I then went on, beginning with the rise and progress of the primitive religions, and coming down to the various religions of the present time, during which time I labored to show Queequeg that all <ref target="#MDch17Note3"><hi rend="bold">these Lents, Ramadans, and prolonged ham-squattings in cold, cheerless rooms were stark nonsense; bad for the health; useless for the soul; opposed, in short, to the obvious laws of Hygiene and common sense. I told him, too, that he being in other things such an extremely sensible and sagacious savage, it pained me, very badly pained me, to see him now so deplorably foolish about this ridiculous Ramadan of his. Besides, argued I, fasting makes the body cave in; hence the spirit caves in; and all thoughts born of a fast must necessarily be half-starved. This is the reason why most dyspeptic religionists cherish such melancholy notions about their hereafters. In one word, Queequeg, said I, rather digressively; hell is an idea first born on an <ref target="#ref_16209">undigested apple-dumpling</ref><note xml:id="ref_16209">undigested apple-dumpling: the fruit of the forbidden tree in Eden (Genesis 3).</note>; and since then perpetuated through the hereditary <ref target="#ref_16211">dyspepsias</ref><note xml:id="ref_16211">dyspepsias: bouts of indigestion.</note> nurtured by Ramadans.</hi></ref> <note xml:id="MDch17Note3">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">Lents and Ramadans</hi> // Seeing Queequeg as an excessive “religionist” whose devotion to fasting runs counter to common sense and good health, Ishmael argues facetiously that Christian Lent and Islamic Ramadan are “useless for the soul” and that “hell is an idea first born on an undigested apple-dumpling.” Melville’s British editor—no doubt finding the argument both disrespectful of Christian practice (Lent) and dogma (hell) as well as blasphemous in its reduction of Adam and Eve’s eating of the apple and mankind’s consequent damnation to mere indigestion—cut most of this paragraph, revising the final line to read: "during which time I labored to show Queequeg that all these fasts, voluntary or otherwise, were excessively bad for the digestion." The editor’s reason for inserting “voluntary or otherwise” is unclear, suggesting perhaps an invidious contrast between Lent and Ramadan or variations in Christian practice. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note> <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0156.jpg"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I then asked Queequeg whether he himself was ever troubled with dyspepsia; expressing the idea very plainly, so that he could take it in. He said no; only upon one memorable occasion. It was after a great feast given by his father the king, on the gaining of a great battle wherein fifty of the enemy had been killed by about two o’clock in the afternoon, and all cooked and eaten that very evening.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">“No more, Queequeg,” said I, shuddering; “that will do;” for I knew the inferences without his further hinting them. I <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517805268897-x8740qrbk0a-f60020416a919f64f1647d0cf7a5bbfc%2FMD_Amer_0134.jpg"/> had seen a sailor who had visited <ref target="#ref_16210">that very island</ref><note xml:id="ref_16210">that very island: If Queequeg’s island (named Kokovoko in Ch. 12) is based on Nuku Hiva, the Marquesan island where Melville spent a month in 1842 after jumping ship, then a reasonable supposition is that the “sailor” Ishmael alludes to as a witness to cannibalism would be Melville himself. While Melville wrote of the threat of cannibalism in <hi rend="italic">Typee</hi>, which recounts his Marquesan adventure, there is no evidence that he actually witnessed a cannibal feast; in fact, while Polynesians did practice cannibalism, it was only an occasional ritual.</note>, and he told me that it was the custom, when a great battle had been gained there, to barbecue all the slain in the yard or garden of the victor; and then, one by one, they were placed in great wooden trenchers, and garnished round like a <ref target="#ref_16212">pilau</ref><note xml:id="ref_16212">pilau: pilaf; rice with meat and spices.</note>, with breadfruit and cocoanuts; and with some parsley in their mouths, were sent round with the victor’s compliments to all his friends, just as though these presents were so many Christmas turkeys.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">After all, I do not think that my remarks about religion made much impression upon Queequeg. Because, in the first place, he somehow seemed dull of hearing on that important subject, unless considered from his own point of view; and, in the second place, he did not more than one third understand me, couch my ideas simply as I would; and, finally, he no doubt thought he knew a good deal more about the true religion than I did. He looked at me with a sort of condescending concern and compassion, as though he thought it a great pity that such a sensible young man should be so hopelessly lost to <ref target="#ref_16213">evangelical</ref><note xml:id="ref_16213">evangelical: here, faithful to the pagan religion.</note> pagan piety.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">At last we rose and dressed; and Queequeg, taking a prodigiously hearty breakfast of chowders of all sorts, so that the landlady should not make much profit by reason of his Ramadan, we sallied out to board the Pequod, sauntering along, and picking our teeth with halibut bones.
 </p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
