<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>20 All Astir</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="ch20-all-astir"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 20</head> <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517806026629-w7s3yoi750l-cbdf2fba661110dbcf88f6cd9779eef9%2FMD_Amer_0143.jpg"/>
<lb/>
				<head type="sub-head" rend="center">ALL ASTIR.</head>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">A DAY or two passed, and there was great activity aboard the Pequod. Not only were the old sails being mended, but new sails were coming on board, and bolts of canvas, and coils of rigging; in short, everything betokened that the ship’s preparations were hurrying to a close. Captain Peleg seldom or never went ashore, but sat in his wigwam keeping a sharp look-out upon the hands: Bildad did all the purchasing and providing at the stores; and the men employed in the hold and on the rigging were working till long after night-fall.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">On the day following Queequeg’s signing the articles, word was given at all the inns where the ship’s company were stopping, that their chests must be on board before night, for there was no telling how soon the vessel might be sailing. So Queequeg and I <ref target="#ref_16245">got down our traps</ref><note xml:id="ref_16245">got down our traps: put our belongings on board.</note>, resolving, however, to sleep ashore till the last. But it seems they always give very long notice in these cases, and the ship did not sail for several days. But no wonder; there was a good deal to be done, and there is no telling how many things to be thought of, before the Pequod was fully equipped.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Every one knows what a multitude of things—beds, sauce-pans, knives and forks, shovels and tongs, napkins, nut-crackers, and what not, are indispensable to the business of housekeeping. Just so with whaling, which necessitates a three-years’ housekeeping upon the wide ocean, far from all grocers, <ref target="#ref_16246">coster-mongers</ref><note xml:id="ref_16246">coster-mongers: street venders, mainly of fruits and vegetables.</note>, doctors, bakers, and bankers. And though this also holds true of merchant vessels, yet not by any means to the same extent as with <ref target="#ref_16247">whalemen</ref><note xml:id="ref_16247">whalemen: here, whaling vessels.</note>. For besides the great length of the whaling voyage, the numerous articles peculiar to the <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517806052073-lvjl04yx5y-cbdf2fba661110dbcf88f6cd9779eef9%2FMD_Amer_0144.jpg"/> prosecution of the fishery, and the impossibility of replacing them at the remote harbors usually frequented, it must be remembered, that of all ships, whaling vessels are the most exposed to accidents of all kinds, and especially to the destruction and loss of the very things upon which the success of the voyage most depends. Hence, the spare boats, spare spars, and spare lines and harpoons, and spare everythings, almost, but a spare Captain and duplicate ship.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">At the period of our arrival at the Island, the <ref target="#MDch20Note1">heaviest <hi rend="bold">stowage</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDch20Note1">REVISION NARRATIVE: heaviest <hi rend="bold">stowage</hi> // Probably Melville, and not an editor, corrected the American edition typo, “storage,” to the nautical term “stowage” for the British version. The editors of the NN Moby-Dick make the correction, as does MEL. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note> <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0171.jpg"/> of the Pequod had been almost completed; comprising her beef, bread, water, fuel, and iron <ref target="#ref_16248">hoops and staves</ref><note xml:id="ref_16248">hoops and staves: used in making barrels; staves are narrow strips of wood.</note>. But, as before hinted, for some time there was a continual fetching and carrying on board of <ref target="#ref_16249">divers</ref><note xml:id="ref_16249">divers: various, diverse.</note> odds and ends of things, both large and small.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Chief among those who did this fetching and carrying was Captain Bildad’s sister, a lean old lady of a most determined and indefatigable spirit, but withal very kindhearted, who seemed resolved that, if <hi rend="italic">she</hi> could help it, nothing should be found wanting in the Pequod, after once fairly getting to sea. At one time she would come on board with a jar of pickles for the steward’s pantry; another time with a bunch of quills for the chief mate’s desk, where he <ref target="#ref_16251">kept his log</ref><note xml:id="ref_16251">kept his log: Made entries in the ship’s log book, a daily record of navigational and meteorological data, whales seen, chased, and caught, other vessels sighted or met, and shipboard events. See Ahab’s use of log books in Ch. 44.</note>; a third time with a roll of flannel for the small of some one’s rheumatic back. Never did any woman better deserve her name, which was Charity—Aunt Charity, as everybody called her. And like a sister of charity did this charitable Aunt Charity bustle about hither and thither, ready to turn her hand and heart to anything that promised to yield safety, comfort, and consolation to all on board a ship in which her beloved brother Bildad was concerned, and in which she herself owned a score or two of well-saved dollars.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But it was startling to see this excellent hearted Quakeress coming on board, as she did the last day, with a long oil-ladle in one hand, and a still longer whaling lance in the other. Nor was Bildad himself nor Captain Peleg at all backward. As for Bildad, he carried about with him a long list of the articles <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517806074212-i6g7hnhw6t-cbdf2fba661110dbcf88f6cd9779eef9%2FMD_Amer_0145.jpg"/> needed, and at every fresh arrival, down went his mark opposite that article upon the paper. Every once and a while <ref target="#MDch20Note2">Peleg came <hi rend="bold">hobbling</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDch20Note2">REVISION NARRATIVE: The British edition reads “Peleg came running.” It is unlikely that an editor or printer would make such a change, and Melville probably revised the text on the proof sheets he sent to England. The editors of the NN Moby-Dick incorporate the revision into their text; MEL does not. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note> <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0172.jpg"/> out of his whalebone den, roaring at the men down the hatchways, roaring up to the <ref target="#ref_16250">riggers</ref><note xml:id="ref_16250">riggers: workers setting up the ship’s rigging.</note> at the mast-head, and then concluded by roaring back into his wigwam.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">During these days of preparation, Queequeg and I often visited the craft, and as often I asked about Captain Ahab, and how he was, and when he was going to come on board his ship. To these questions they would answer, that he was getting better and better, and was expected aboard every day; meantime, the two Captains, Peleg and Bildad, could attend to everything necessary to fit the vessel for the voyage. If I had been downright honest with myself, I would have seen very plainly in my heart that I did but half fancy being committed this way to so long a voyage, without once laying my eyes on the man who was to be the absolute dictator of it, so soon as the ship sailed out upon the open sea. But when a man suspects any wrong, it sometimes happens that if he be already involved in the matter, he insensibly strives to cover up his suspicions even from himself. And much this way it was with me. I said nothing, and tried to think nothing.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">At last it was given out that some time next day the ship would certainly sail. So next morning, Queequeg and I took a very early start.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
