<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>30 The Pipe</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="ch30-the-pipe"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517975080169-ueift7k0ab-227bd93d49b0988f52746559a7b63165%2FMD_Amer_0178.jpg"/>
				<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 30</head> <lb/>
				<head type="sub-head" rend="center">THE PIPE.</head>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">When</hi> Stubb had departed, Ahab stood for a while leaning over the bulwarks; and then, as had been usual with him of late, calling a sailor of the watch, he sent him below for his ivory stool, and also his pipe. Lighting the pipe at the <ref target="#MDch30Note1">binnacle lamp</ref><note xml:id="MDch30Note1">binnacle lamp: A <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1124" type="artwork">binnacle</name>—generally located at the helm near the wheel—is a casing for a ship's compass or compasses, fitted with magnets to counteract local magnetic influences such as from iron in the ship. Ahab lights his pipe from the flame of the small lamp attached to the binnacle that illuminates the compass. See also "binnacle compasses" in Chs. 48 and 124.</note> and planting the stool on the weather side of the deck, he sat and smoked.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In old Norse times, the thrones of the sea-loving Danish kings were fabricated, saith tradition, of the tusks of the narwhale. How could one look at Ahab then, seated on that tripod of bones, without bethinking him of the royalty it symbolized? For a <ref target="#ref_16389">Khan</ref><note xml:id="ref_16389">Khan: Tartar king, an absolute ruler.</note> of the plank, and a king of the sea, and a great lord of Leviathans was Ahab.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Some moments passed, during which the thick vapor came from his mouth in quick and constant puffs, which blew back again into his face. “How now,” he soliloquized at last, withdrawing the tube, “this smoking no longer soothes. Oh, my pipe! hard must it go with me if thy charm be gone! Here have I been unconsciously toiling, not pleasuring,—aye, and ignorantly smoking to windward all the while; to windward, and with such nervous whiffs, as if, like the dying whale, my final jets were the strongest and fullest of trouble. What business have I with this pipe? This thing that is meant for sereneness, to send up mild white vapors among mild white hairs, not <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1517975096432-gfjja3okuhk-227bd93d49b0988f52746559a7b63165%2FMD_Amer_0179.jpg"/> among torn iron grey locks like mine. I’ll smoke no more—”

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">He tossed the still lighted pipe into the sea. The fire hissed in the waves; the same instant the ship shot by the bubble the sinking pipe made. With slouched hat, Ahab lurchingly paced the planks.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
