<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>34 The Cabin Table</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="ch34-the-cabin-table"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				 <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448729457-6yniqtymzi4-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0199.jpg"/>
				<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 34</head><lb/>
				<head type="sub-head" rend="center">THE CABIN-TABLE.</head>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">It</hi> is noon; and Dough-Boy, the steward, thrusting his pale loaf-of-bread face from the cabin-scuttle, announces dinner <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448794486-9axdvx6yv2s-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0200.jpg"/> to his lord and master; who, sitting in the <ref target="#MDch34Note3">lee quarter-boat</ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note3">lee quarter-boat: Two whaleboats, one on each side, hang from the ship’s quarters (the sections of the sides near the stern). Ahab sits in the one that is at the time on the lee side, sheltered from the wind and using a sextant to take the standard noon sighting of the sun, which allows him to calculate the ship’s latitude. </note>, has just been taking an observation of the sun; and is now mutely reckoning the latitude on the smooth, medallion-shaped tablet, reserved for that daily purpose on the upper part of his ivory leg.  From his complete inattention to the tidings, you would think that moody Ahab had not heard his menial. But presently, catching hold of the mizen shrouds, he swings himself to the deck, and in an even, unexhilarated voice, saying, “Dinner, Mr. Starbuck,” disappears into the cabin.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">When the last echo of his sultan’s step has died away, and Starbuck, the first <ref target="#ref_16475">Emir</ref><note xml:id="ref_16475">Emir: Turkish ruler subordinate to a sultan.</note>, has every reason to suppose that he is seated, then Starbuck rouses from his quietude, takes a few turns along the planks, and, after a grave peep into the binnacle<ref target="#MD34Note9"></ref><note xml:id="MD34Note9"></note>, says, with some touch of pleasantness, “Dinner, Mr. Stubb,” and descends the scuttle. The second Emir lounges about the rigging awhile, and then slightly shaking the <ref target="#ref_16476">main brace</ref><note xml:id="ref_16476">main brace: rope controlling the angle of the mainsail to the wind.</note>, to see whether it be all right with that important rope, he likewise takes up the old <ref target="#ref_16477">burden</ref><note xml:id="ref_16477">burden: refrain of a song.</note>, and with a rapid “Dinner, Mr. Flask,” follows after his predecessors.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But the third Emir, now seeing himself all alone on the quarter-deck, seems to feel relieved from some curious restraint; for, tipping all sorts of knowing winks in all sorts of directions, and kicking off his shoes, he strikes into a sharp but noiseless squall of a <ref target="#ref_16478">hornpipe right over the Grand Turk’s head</ref><note xml:id="ref_16478">hornpipe . . . Grand Turk’s head: lively folk dance, popular among sailors; the Grand Turk was the sultan of Turkey.</note>; and then, by a dexterous sleight, pitching his cap up into the <ref target="#ref_16479">mizen-top</ref><note xml:id="ref_16479">mizen-top: small platform at the top of the lower mizzenmast, the third and rearmost mast.</note> for a shelf, he goes down rollicking, so far at least as he remains visible from the deck, reversing all other processions, by bringing up the rear with music. But ere stepping into the cabin doorway below, he pauses, <ref target="#ref_16480">ships</ref><note xml:id="ref_16480">ships: puts on.</note> a new face altogether, and, then, independent, hilarious little Flask enters King Ahab’s presence, in the character of <ref target="#MDch34Note4">Abjectus, or the Slave</ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note4">Abjectus, or the Slave: This seeming allusion has no source in classical literature.</note>.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It is not the least among the strange things bred by the intense artificialness of sea-usages, that while in the open air of the deck some officers will, upon provocation, bear themselves <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448827230-0h4lpirdp0k8-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0201.jpg"/> boldly and defyingly enough towards their commander; yet, ten to one, let those very officers the next moment go down to their customary dinner in that same commander’s cabin, and straightway their inoffensive, not to say deprecatory and humble air towards him, as he sits at the head of the table; this is marvellous, sometimes most comical. Wherefore this difference? A problem? Perhaps not. To have been <ref target="#MDch34Note5">Belshazzar</ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note5">Belshazzar: As told in Daniel 5.1, this prideful and blasphemous minor king gives a great feast for a thousand, during which mysterious writing inscribed on a wall by a disembodied hand predicts his imminent downfall; see also “Belshazzar’s awful writing” in Ch. 99 and “Mene, Mene, Tekel, Upharsin” in Ch. 119.</note>, King of Babylon; and to have been Belshazzar, not haughtily but courteously, therein certainly must have been some touch of mundane grandeur. But he who in the rightly regal and intelligent spirit presides over his own private dinner-table of invited guests, that man’s unchallenged power and dominion of individual influence for the time; that man’s royalty of state transcends Belshazzar’s, for Belshazzar was not the greatest. Who has but once dined his friends, has tasted what it is to be Cæsar. It is a witchery of social czarship which there is no withstanding. Now, if to this consideration you superadd the official supremacy of a ship-master, then, by inference, you will derive the cause of that peculiarity of sea-life just mentioned.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Over his ivory-inlaid table, Ahab presided like a mute, maned sea-lion on the white coral beach, surrounded by his war-like but still deferential cubs. In his own proper turn, each officer waited to be served. They were as little children before Ahab; and yet, in Ahab, there seemed not to lurk the smallest social arrogance. With one mind, their intent eyes all fastened upon the old man’s knife, as he carved the chief dish before him. I do not suppose that for the world they would have profaned that moment with the slightest observation, even upon so neutral a topic as the weather. No! And when reaching out his knife and fork, between which the slice of beef was locked, Ahab thereby motioned Starbuck’s plate towards him, the mate received his meat as though receiving alms; and cut it tenderly; and a little started if, perchance, the knife grazed against the plate; and chewed it noiselessly; and swallowed it, <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448843869-h31okibvn4o-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0202.jpg"/> not without circumspection. For, like the <ref target="#MDch34Note6">Coronation banquet at Frankfort</ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note6">Coronation banquet at Frankfort: Feast prepared at Frankfurt am Main, Germany, after the election of the Holy Roman Emperor by the “princes of the Empire.”</note>, where the German Emperor profoundly dines with the seven Imperial Electors, so these cabin meals were somehow solemn meals, eaten in awful silence; and yet at table old Ahab forbade not conversation; only he himself was dumb. What a relief it was to choking Stubb, when a rat made a sudden racket in the hold below. And poor little Flask, he was the youngest son, and little boy of this weary family party. His were the shinbones of the saline beef; his would have been the drumsticks. For Flask to have presumed to help himself, this must have seemed to him tantamount to larceny in the first degree. Had he helped himself at that table, doubtless, never more would he have been able to hold his head up in this honest world; nevertheless, strange to say, Ahab never forbade him. And had Flask helped himself, the chances were Ahab had never so much as noticed it. Least of all, did Flask presume to help himself to butter. Whether he thought the owners of the ship denied it to him, on account of its clotting his clear, sunny complexion; or whether he deemed that, on so long a voyage in such marketless waters, butter was at a premium, and therefore was not for him, a subaltern; however it was, Flask, alas! was a butterless man!

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Another thing. Flask was the last person down at the dinner, and Flask is the first man up. Consider! For hereby Flask’s dinner was badly jammed in point of time. Starbuck and Stubb both had the start of him; and yet they also have the privilege of lounging in the rear. If Stubb even, who is but a peg higher than Flask, happens to have but a small appetite, and soon shows symptoms of concluding his repast, then Flask must bestir himself, he will not get more than three mouthfuls that day; for it is against holy usage for Stubb to precede Flask to the deck. Therefore it was that Flask once admitted in private, that ever since he had arisen to the dignity of an officer, from that moment he had never known what <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448861966-inpmd889ssd-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0203.jpg"/> it was to be otherwise than hungry, more or less. For what he ate did not so much relieve his hunger, as keep it immortal in him. Peace and satisfaction, thought Flask, <ref target="#MDch34Note7">have for ever departed from my stomach</ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note7">have for ever departed from my stomach: Not sounding at all like Flask, the phrase instead reflects Melville’s having absorbed a locution in the King James Bible, as in “their defence is <hi rend="bold">departed from them</hi>” (Numbers 14.9), or “God is <hi rend="bold">departed from me</hi>” (Samuel 10.2 and 28.15).</note>.  I am an officer; but, how I wish I could fist a bit of old-fashioned beef in the forecastle, as I used to when I was before the mast. There’s the fruits of promotion now; there’s the vanity of glory: there’s the insanity of life! Besides, if it were so that any mere sailor of the Pequod had a grudge against Flask in Flask’s official capacity, all that sailor had to do, in order to obtain ample vengeance, was to go aft at dinner-time, and get a peep at Flask through the cabin sky-light, sitting silly and dumfoundered before awful Ahab.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Now, Ahab and his three mates formed what may be called the first table in the Pequod’s cabin. After their departure, taking place in inverted order to their arrival, the canvas cloth was cleared, or rather was restored <ref target="#MDch34Note1">to some hurried <hi rend="bold">order</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note1">REVISION NARRATIVE: to some hurried <hi rend="bold">order</hi> // The British text is revised to “to some hurried method,” which seems to be an incomplete revision to the more grammatical “in some hurried method.” Chances are Melville altered “order” to “method” to eliminate the repetition of “order” in the preceding line; however, the necessary revision of “to” to “in” was either not made or not registered by the printer. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note> <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0257.jpg"/> by the pallid steward. And then the three harpooneers were bidden to the feast, they being its <ref target="#ref_16481">residuary legatees</ref><note xml:id="ref_16481">residuary legatees: those who divide whatever is left after the specific bequests of a will have been paid.</note>. They made a sort of temporary servants’ hall of the high and mighty cabin.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In strange contrast to the hardly tolerable constraint and nameless invisible domineerings of the captain’s table, was the entire care-free license and ease, the almost frantic democracy of those inferior fellows the harpooneers. While their masters, the mates, seemed afraid of the sound of the hinges of their own jaws, the harpooneers chewed their food with such a relish that there was a <ref target="#ref_16482">report</ref><note xml:id="ref_16482">report: loud noise.</note> to it. They dined like lords; they filled their bellies like Indian ships all day loading with spices. Such <ref target="#ref_16483">portentous</ref><note xml:id="ref_16483">portentous: huge, prodigious.</note> appetites had Queequeg and Tashtego, that to fill out the vacancies made by the previous repast, often the pale Dough-Boy was fain to bring on a great <ref target="#ref_22391">baron of salt-junk</ref><note xml:id="ref_22391">fain . . . baron of salt-junk: obliged . . . undivided loin of hard salt beef.</note>, seemingly quarried out of the solid ox. And if he were not lively about it, if he did not go with a nim-<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448877672-uy7xfinxdni-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0204.jpg"/>ble hop-skip-and-jump, then Tashtego had an ungentlemanly way of accelerating him by darting a fork at his back, harpoon-wise. And once Daggoo, seized with a sudden humor, assisted Dough-Boy’s memory by snatching him up bodily, and thrusting his head into a great empty wooden trencher, while Tashtego, knife in hand, began laying out the circle preliminary to scalping him. He was naturally a very nervous, shuddering sort of little fellow, this bread-faced steward; the progeny of a bankrupt baker and a hospital nurse. And what with the standing spectacle of the black terrific Ahab, and the periodical tumultuous visitations of these three savages, Dough-Boy’s whole life was one continual lip-quiver. Commonly, after seeing the harpooneers furnished with all things they demanded, he would escape from their clutches into his little pantry adjoining, and fearfully peep out at them through the blinds of <ref target="#MDch34Note2"><hi rend="bold">its door</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note2">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">its door</hi> // Melville, rather than his British copyeditor, probably made the small alteration to “his door,” a phrase that designates Dough-Boy’s private space or hideout from the fearsome harpooneers.To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note>, <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0258.jpg"/> till all was over.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It was a sight to see Queequeg seated over against Tashtego, opposing his filed teeth to the Indian’s: crosswise to them, Daggoo seated on the floor, for a bench would have brought his <ref target="#ref_16485">hearse-plumed head to the low <ref type="reference" target="glossary#carlines"><w xml:id="carlines">carlines</w></ref></ref><note xml:id="ref_16485">hearse-plumed . . . carlines: like the black plumes placed on hearses; carlines are timbers between the ceiling beams.</note>; at every motion of his colossal limbs, making the low cabin framework to shake, as when an African elephant goes passenger in a ship. But for all this, the great negro was wonderfully abstemious, not to say dainty. It seemed hardly possible that by such comparatively small mouthfuls he could keep up the vitality diffused through so broad, baronial, and superb a person. But, doubtless, this noble savage fed strong and drank deep of the abounding element of air; and through his dilated nostrils snuffed in the sublime life of the worlds. Not by beef or by bread, are giants made or nourished. But Queequeg, he had a mortal, barbaric smack of the lip in eating—an ugly sound enough—so much so, that the trembling Dough-Boy almost looked to see whether any marks of teeth lurked in his own lean arms. And when he would hear Tashtego singing out for him to produce himself, <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448893661-5fiqdzt3h65-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0205.jpg"/> that his bones might be picked, the simple-witted Steward all but shattered the crockery hanging round him in the pantry, by his sudden fits of the palsy. Nor did the whetstone which the harpooneers carried in their pockets, for their lances and other weapons; and with which whetstones, at dinner, they would ostentatiously sharpen their knives; that grating sound did not at all tend to tranquillize poor Dough-Boy. How could he forget that in his Island days, Queequeg, for one, must certainly have been guilty of some murderous, convivial indiscretions. Alas! Dough-Boy! hard fares the white waiter who waits upon cannibals. Not a napkin should he carry on his arm, but a <ref target="#ref_16486">buckler</ref><note xml:id="ref_16486">buckler: shield. </note>. In good time, though, to his great delight, the three salt-sea warriors would rise and depart; to his credulous, fable-mongering ears, all their martial bones jingling in them at every step, like Moorish scimetars in scabbards.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But, though these barbarians dined in the cabin, and nominally lived there; still, being anything but sedentary in their habits, they were scarcely ever in it except at meal-times, and just before sleeping-time, when they passed through it to their own <ref target="#ref_16487">peculiar</ref><note xml:id="ref_16487">peculiar: particular; separate.</note> quarters.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In this one matter, Ahab seemed no exception to most American whale captains, who, as a set, rather incline to the opinion that by rights the ship’s cabin belongs to them; and that it is by courtesy alone that anybody else is, at any time, permitted there. So that, in real truth, the mates and harpooneers of the Pequod might more properly be said to have lived out of the cabin than in it. For when they did enter it, it was something as a street-door enters a house; turning inwards for a moment, only to be turned out the next; and, as a permanent thing, residing in the open air. Nor did they lose much hereby; in the cabin was no companionship; socially, Ahab was inaccessible. Though nominally included in the census of Christendom, he was still an alien to it. He lived in the world, as the last of the Grisly Bears lived in settled Missouri. And as when <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1512448910823-104tnyfwkwxm-18050cb5dc2fef20ed70f49d9c987b7a%2FMD_Amer_0206.jpg"/> Spring and Summer had departed, that <ref target="#ref_21831">wild Logan of the woods</ref><note xml:id="ref_21831">wild Logan: Ahab's soul is as alien to the rest of humanity as a hibernating grizzly bear is among people. Ishmael compares the grizzly to a "wild Logan," the eighteenth-century Mingo orator famous for a speech in which he laments the murder of his family by colonists and justifies his revenge.</note>, burying himself in the hollow of a tree, lived out the winter there, <ref target="#MDch34Note8">sucking his own paws</ref><note xml:id="MDch34Note8">sucking his own paws: Bears do suck or lick their paws during hibernation, leading to the common (but false) belief that they get nourishment from doing so.</note>; so, in his inclement, howling old age, Ahab’s soul, shut up in the caved trunk of his body, there fed upon the sullen paws of its gloom!
     </p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
