<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>56 Less Erroneous Pictures of Whales</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="56-less-erroneous-pictures-of-whales"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514498086207-bcjewkgqmb6-277e6b7d5447abf3c32a7d12711b1e19%2FMD_Amer_0335.jpg"/>
			<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 56</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">OF THE LESS ERRONEOUS PICTURES OF WHALES, AND THE TRUE <lb/>PICTURES OF WHALING SCENES.</head>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">IN connexion with the monstrous pictures of whales, I am strongly tempted here to enter upon those still more monstrous stories of them which are to be found in certain books, both ancient and modern, especially in <ref target="#ref_21858">Pliny</ref><note xml:id="ref_21858">Pliny, Purchas, Hackluyt, Harris, Cuvier, &amp;c.: <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:226">Hakluyt, Richard</ref> (1552–1616) was not himself an explorer but compiled important collections of travel writing by British explorers; his associate, <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:259">Purchas, Samuel, 1577?-1626</ref>, published <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:136">Hakluytus Posthumus, or Purchas His Pilgrimes, contaying a History of the World in Sea Voyages and Land Travell by Englishmen and others</ref> (1625) with additional works of the navigators found in Hakluyt’s papers at his death. <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:262">Harris, John, 1666-1719</ref> is noted for his 1705 collection of voyage narratives. (For <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:233">Pliny, the Elder, 23-79 CE</ref>, see Ch. 32; for <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:416">Georges-Frédéric Cuvier (1773 –  1838)</ref> and <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:289">Cuvier, Georges, baron, 1769-1832</ref>, see Chs. 32 and 55.) All are cited in “Extracts.”</note>, Purchas, Hackluyt, Harris, Cuvier, &amp;c. But I pass that matter by.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I know of only four published <ref target="#ref_17189">outlines</ref><note xml:id="ref_17189"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:939" type="artwork">outlines</name>: schematic drawings.</note> of the great Sperm Whale;
<ref target="#ref_21860">Colnett’s</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_21860">Colnett’s, Huggins’s, Frederick Cuvier’s, and Beale’s . . . Huggins’s is far better . . . Beale’s is the best: Melville treats Thomas Beale’s outline renderings of whale depictions by <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:290">James Colnett (1755?-1806)</ref>, Huggins, and <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:416">Georges-Frédéric Cuvier (1773-1838)</ref> in Ch. 55. Here, according to Stuart M. Frank's Herman Melville's Picture Gallery, he also alludes to the well-known 1834 engraving of Huggins’s colored aquatint “<ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:956">South Sea Whale Fishery</ref>.” Melville’s assertion that "Beale’s is the best" refers to <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:953" type="artwork">Beale's outline</name> of a whale showing the pattern that whalers follow in “cutting-in” or flensing, that is peeling away, the blubber. As Frank observes, Melville admired not only the accuracy of Beale’s outline but also his detailed knowledge of the sperm whale’s anatomy (60-61).</note>,

<ref target="#ref_20581"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:957" type="artwork">Huggins</name>’s,</ref>
<note xml:id="ref_20581">Although Melville does not mention this etching <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:957">Beale Vignette</ref>, he does mention Huggins and certainly would have seen this realistic depiction of a sperm whale hunt in Thomas Beale's <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:176">The Natural History of the Sperm Whale</ref>. It derives from a print of an oil painting by <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:427"> William John Huggins (1781-1845)</ref>, the marine painter to King William IV of England.  It became popular and Beale included the etched version without attribution as a vignette to introduce Chapter XII of <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:176">The Natural History of the Sperm Whale</ref>. Although Stuart Frank regards the etching as unacknowledged in <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:246">Herman Melville's Picture Gallery</ref>, Huggins presumably approved of its publication. He is listed as a subscriber in Beale’s book (p. xiv), meaning he agreed to purchase it before it was published, and in the introduction Beale praises Huggins for his “admirable print” (p. 2).  This statement along with the print’s popularity suggests that most readers recognized the source of Beale’s engraving even without attribution.  Beale also praises “the faithful and excellent plate by Huggins, from a drawing made in the South Seas over the dead animal” (13) as a corrective to <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:416">Georges-Frédéric Cuvier (1773 –  1838)</ref>’s complaint about sketching dead whales. <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:304">Beale, Thomas, 1807-1849</ref> did not include this plate in his book.  There is no evidence that Melville saw either Huggins’s painting or its printed version leading scholars to believe that he relied on Beale for the Huggins image as well as those from Cuvier and Colnett.</note>

Frederick Cuvier’s, and Beale’s. In the previous chapter Colnett and Cuvier have been referred to. Huggins’s is far better than theirs; but, by great odds,
Beale’s is the best.  All Beale’s drawings of this whale are good, excepting the <ref target="#ref_21864">middle figure</ref><note xml:id="ref_21864">excepting the middle figure: In his copy of Thomas Beale's <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:176">The Natural History of the Sperm Whale</ref>, Melville noted of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:954" type="artwork">this drawing</name> depicting three whales in various poses that the second figure, a leaping whale, is “wretchedly cropped &amp; dwarfed.”</note>
in the picture of three whales in various attitudes, capping his second chapter. His <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:955" type="artwork">frontispiece</name>, boats attacking Sperm Whales, though no doubt calculated to excite the civil scepticism of some parlor men, is admirably correct and life-like in its general effect. Some of the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:964" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:958" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:962" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:963" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:961" type="artwork"><ref target="#ref_17197">Sperm Whale drawings in J. Ross Browne</ref><note xml:id="ref_17197">Sperm Whale drawings in J. Ross Browne: In his otherwise favorable review of J. Ross Browne’s book, <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:115">Etchings of a Whaling Cruise</ref> (1846), in Literary World (March 6, 1847), Melville remarks that its illustrations are “coarsely or harshly drawn.”

Examples of "wretchedly engraved" images are the following: <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:958">J. Ross Browne, Etchings of a Whaling Cruise</ref>; <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:962">Browne Etching p122</ref>; <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:963">Browne Etching p292</ref>; <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:964">Browne Etching p297</ref>.  However, most of these are superior to the "Erroneous Pictures of Whales" in chapter 55, and one, a steel-cut plate, depicts the harpooning and lancing of the whale fairly accurately along with a reasonably correct drawing of the whale’s tail, jaws, eye, and head.  The spout is perhaps the most unrealistic element in the engraving. <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:961">Browne Etching p121</ref></note></name></name></name></name></name> are pretty correct in contour; but they are wretchedly engraved. That is not his fault though.
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514498106369-5fj2jt7igd-277e6b7d5447abf3c32a7d12711b1e19%2FMD_Amer_0336.jpg"/>
</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Of the Right Whale, the best <ref target="#ref_21865">outline</ref><note xml:id="ref_21865">William Scoresby’s 24 plates are all at the end of volume 2 of <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:182">An Account of the Arctic Regions, with a History and Description of the Northern Whale Fishery</ref> and take up a full page that Stuart Frank, in <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:246">Herman Melville's Picture Gallery</ref>, measures at 8 x 4 ¾ inches.  Melville’s complaint about their “too small a scale” is understandable. In addition to this realistic outline of a right whale, <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:303">Scoresby, William, Jr., 1789-1857</ref> includes three plates of other types of whales.</note> pictures are in Scoresby; but they are drawn on too small a scale to convey a desirable impression. He has but <ref target="#ref_21868">one picture</ref><note xml:id="ref_21868">one picture of whaling scenes . . . is a sad deficiency: William Scoresby’s inaccurate frontispiece in <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:182">An Account of the Arctic Regions, with a History and Description of the Northern Whale Fishery</ref> is taken from James Waddel’s widely reprinted “Dangers of the Whale Fishery.”</note> of whaling scenes, and this is a sad deficiency, because it is by such pictures only, when at all well done, that you can derive anything like a truthful idea of the living whale as seen by his living hunters.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But, taken for all in all, by far the finest, though in some details not the most correct, presentations of whales and whaling scenes to be anywhere found, are two large French engravings, well executed, and taken from paintings by one <ref target="#ref_21874">Garnery</ref><note xml:id="ref_21874">paintings by one Garnery: Engravings of pictures by French marine painter <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:428">Garneray, Louis, 1783-1857</ref> were widely known in the mid-nineteenth century.</note>. Respectively, they represent attacks on the Sperm and Right Whale. In the <ref target="#ref_20589"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:967" type="artwork">first engraving</name></ref><note xml:id="ref_20589"><ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:967">Garneray Sperm Whale; Pêche du Cachalot. Cachalot Fishery.  </ref>

Melville’s precise description indicates that he must have owned copies of this lithograph, probably in black and white rather than color, as here.  In <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:246">Herman Melville's Picture Gallery</ref>, Stuart M. Frank describes the popularity of this print and its reissue in London in 1836 and by Currier &amp; Ives in New York in 1857 (71).</note> a noble Sperm Whale is depicted in full majesty of might, just risen beneath the boat from the profundities of the ocean, and bearing high in the air upon his back the terrific wreck of the stoven planks. The prow of the boat is partially unbroken, and is drawn just balancing upon the monster’s spine; and standing in that prow, for that one single incomputable flash of time, you behold an oarsman, half shrouded by the incensed boiling spout of the whale, and in the act of leaping, as if from a precipice. The action of the whole thing is wonderfully good and true. The half-emptied line-tub floats on the whitened sea; the wooden poles of the spilled harpoons obliquely bob in it; the heads of the swimming crew are scattered about the whale in contrasting expressions of affright; while in the black stormy distance the ship is bearing down upon the scene. Serious fault might be found with the anatomical details of this whale, but let that pass; since, for the life of me, I could not draw so good a one.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:969" type="artwork"><ref target="#ref_20590">second engraving</ref><note xml:id="ref_20590"><ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:969">Garnery Right Whale; Pêche de la Baleine. Whale Cachalot Fishery.  </ref>

Melville’s precise description indicates that he must have owned copies of this lithograph, probably in black and white rather than color, as here.  In <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:246">Herman Melville's Picture Gallery</ref>, Stuart M. Frank describes the popularity of this print and its reissue in London in 1836 and by Currier &amp; Ives in New York in 1857 (73).</note></name>, the boat is in the act of drawing alongside the barnacled flank of a large running Right Whale, that rolls his black weedy bulk in the sea like some mossy rock-slide from the <ref target="#ref_21879">Patagonian</ref><note xml:id="ref_21879">Patagonian cliffs: The reference to <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:284">Patagonia</ref> suggests wildness and inaccessibility.</note> cliffs. His jets are erect, full, and black like soot; so that from so abounding a smoke in the chimney, you would think there must be a brave supper cooking <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514498132600-h7rq20gvqym-277e6b7d5447abf3c32a7d12711b1e19%2FMD_Amer_0337.jpg"/>in the great bowels below. Sea fowls are pecking at the small crabs, shell-fish, and other sea candies and maccaroni, which the Right Whale sometimes carries on his pestilent back. And all the while the thick-lipped leviathan is rushing through the deep, leaving tons of tumultuous white curds in his wake, and causing the slight boat to rock in the swells like a skiff caught nigh the paddle-wheels of an ocean steamer. Thus, the foreground is all raging commotion; but behind, in admirable artistic contrast, is the glassy level of a sea becalmed, the drooping <ref target="#ref_17190">unstarched</ref><note xml:id="ref_17190">unstarched: not smoothed by wind pressure.</note> sails of the powerless ship, and the inert mass of a dead whale, a conquered fortress, with the flag of capture lazily hanging from the <ref target="#ref_21880">whale-pole</ref><note xml:id="ref_21880">whale-pole: pole with small flag to mark ownership of a floating whale carcass; also waif-pole; see Ch. 89.</note>° inserted into his spout-hole.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Who Garnery the painter is, or was, I know not. But my life for it he was either practically conversant with his subject, or else marvellously tutored by some experienced whaleman. The French are the lads for painting action. Go and gaze upon all the paintings of Europe, and where will you find such a gallery of living and breathing commotion on canvas, as in that triumphal hall at <ref target="#ref_21881">Versailles</ref><note xml:id="ref_21881">Versailles . . . the consecutive great battles of France: Melville toured Paris and its environs in December, 1849, as part of his trip to England. During his visit to the Palace of <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:285">Versailles, France</ref> (formerly King Louis XIV’s residence, now and in Melville’s day a museum), he observed “splendid paintings of battles” (NN Journals 33) from all periods, including the Revolution and Napoleonic wars.</note>; where the beholder fights his way, pell-mell, through the consecutive great battles of France; where every sword seems a flash of the Northern Lights, and the successive armed kings and Emperors dash by, like a charge of crowned centaurs? Not wholly unworthy of a place in that gallery, are these sea battle-pieces of Garnery.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The natural aptitude of the French for seizing the picturesqueness of things seems to be peculiarly evinced in what paintings and engravings they have of their whaling scenes. With not one tenth of England’s experience in the fishery, and not the thousandth part of that of the Americans, they have nevertheless furnished both nations with the only finished sketches at all capable of conveying the real spirit of the whale hunt. For the most part, the English and American whale draughtsmen seem entirely content with presenting the mechanical outline of things, such as the vacant profile of the whale; which, so far as <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514498157179-lu66x6vx3br-277e6b7d5447abf3c32a7d12711b1e19%2FMD_Amer_0338.jpg"/>picturesqueness of effect is concerned, is about tantamount to sketching the profile of a pyramid. Even <ref target="#ref_21883">Scoresby</ref><note xml:id="ref_21883">This passage reveals Melville’s thorough scrutiny of the plates in volume 2 of William Scoresby’s <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:182">An Account of the Arctic Regions, with a History and Description of the Northern Whale Fishery</ref>. The  Artwork entries picture narwhales, porpoises, and a Beluga whale. Although Melville does not mention the Beluga, because it is white it is worth reproducing here.  There are four plates with 24 snow crystals each to give Melville his figure of “ninety-six facsimiles” and grounds for a modest joke (Plate 10).  The “boat hooks, chopping knives, and grapnels” are one plate among five that illustrate these and other types of whaling tools (Plate 20; the second X is cut off in the image).</note>, the justly renowned Right whaleman, after giving us a stiff full length of the <ref target="#ref_21885">Greenland whale</ref><note xml:id="ref_21885"><ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:965">Scoresby Right Whale</ref>

Variously named the Baleinus Mysticetus, Right Whale, and Greenland Whale, this species was one of the easiest and most profitable to catch. Consequently, it was almost eliminated in the nineteenth century and is still an endangered species.</note>, and three or four delicate <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:970" type="artwork">miniatures of narwhales</name> and <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:971" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:972" type="artwork">porpoises,</name></name> treats us to a series of classical engravings of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:973" type="artwork">boat hooks</name>, chopping knives, and grapnels; and with the microscopic diligence of a <ref target="#ref_17201">Leuwenhoeck</ref><note xml:id="ref_17201">Leuwenhoeck: Dutch naturalist Anton van Leeuwenhoek (1632–1723), renowned for his work in microscopy.</note> submits to the inspection of a shivering world ninety-six fac-similes of magnified <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:974" type="artwork">Arctic snow crystals</name>. I mean no disparagement to the excellent voyager (I honor him for a veteran), but in so important a matter it was certainly an oversight not to have procured for every crystal a sworn affidavit taken before a Greenland Justice of the Peace.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In addition to those fine engravings from Garnery, there are two other French engravings worthy of note, by some one who subscribes himself “H. <ref target="#ref_21886">Durand</ref><note xml:id="ref_21886">“H. Durand”: Although “Durand” was a pseudonym used by French engravers, Stuart M. Frank in <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:246">Herman Melville's Picture Gallery</ref> identifies French marine artist Henri Durand-Brager (1814–1879) as the painter of the two pictures Melville describes, entitled “Whaler at Anchor” and “French Whaler Fishing.”</note>.” <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:975" type="artwork">One of them,</name> though not precisely adapted to our present purpose, nevertheless deserves mention on other accounts. It is a quiet noon-scene among the isles of the Pacific; a French whaler anchored, inshore, in a calm, and lazily taking water on board; the loosened sails of the ship, and the long leaves of the palms in the background, both drooping together in the breezeless air. The effect is very fine, when considered with reference to its presenting the hardy fishermen under one of their few aspects of oriental repose. <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:976" type="artwork">The other engraving</name> is quite a different affair: the ship hove-to upon the open sea, and in the very heart of the Leviathanic life, with a Right Whale alongside; the vessel (in the act of cutting-in) hove over to the monster as if to a quay; and a boat, hurriedly pushing off from this scene of activity, is <ref target="#ref_17191">about giving</ref><note xml:id="ref_17191">about giving: starting to.</note> chase to whales in the distance. The harpoons and lances lie levelled for use; three oarsmen are just setting the mast in its hole; while from a sudden roll of the sea, the little craft stands half-erect out of the water, like a rearing horse. From the ship, the smoke of the torments of the boiling whale <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514498181713-ijqy9ldbljk-277e6b7d5447abf3c32a7d12711b1e19%2FMD_Amer_0339.jpg"/>is going up like the smoke over a village of <ref target="#ref_17192">smithies</ref><note xml:id="ref_17192">smithies: blacksmith shops.</note>; and to windward, a black cloud, rising up with <ref target="#ref_21887">earnest of squalls</ref><note xml:id="ref_21887">with earnest of squalls: indicating approaching storms</note> and rains, seems to quicken the activity of the excited seamen.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
