<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title> 65 The Whale as a Dish</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div   xml:id="65-the-whale-as-a-dish"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1471213660075-4mapr8rxk5v-06976c236fef4cb8ddd917fb5d819a49%2FMD_Amer_0370.jpg"/>

			<head type="main" rend="center">Chapter 65</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">THE WHALE AS A DISH.</head>


</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">THAT mortal man should feed upon the creature that feeds his lamp, and, like Stubb, eat him by his own light, as you may say; this seems so outlandish a thing that one must needs go a little into the history and philosophy of it.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It is <ref target="#ref_21972">upon record</ref><note xml:id="ref_21972">It is upon record . . . France . . . Henry VIIIth’s time . . . Dunfermline: In their edition of <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:218">Moby-Dick</ref>, Luther S. Mansfield and Howard P. Vincent (757) show that in this paragraph the record for France is William Scoresby's <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:182">An Account of the Arctic Regions, with a History and Description of the Northern Whale Fishery</ref>, while the information about <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:345">Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547</ref>, who reigned as King of England 1502–1547, and Dunfermline (a Benedictine abbey founded in 1072 near <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:543">Edinburgh</ref>, Scotland) comes from Sir Robert Sibbald, <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:140">The History, Ancient and Modern, of the Sheriffdoms of Fife and Kinross</ref>, also cited in “Extracts.”</note>, that three centuries ago the tongue of the Right Whale was esteemed a great delicacy in France, and commanded large prices there. Also, that in <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:345" type="person">Henry VIII</name>th’s time, a certain cook of the court obtained a handsome reward for inventing an admirable sauce to be eaten with barbacued porpoises, which, you remember, are a species of whale. Porpoises, indeed, are to this day considered fine eating. The meat is made into balls about the size of billiard balls, and being well seasoned and spiced might be taken for turtle-balls or veal balls. The old monks of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:301" type="place">Dunfermline</name> were very fond of them. They had a great porpoise grant from the crown.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The fact is, that among his hunters at least, the whale would by all hands be considered a noble dish, were there not so much of him; but when you come to sit down before a meat-pie nearly one hundred feet long, it takes away your appetite. Only the most unprejudiced of men like Stubb, nowadays partake of cooked whales; but the <ref target="#ref_20746">Esquimaux</ref><note xml:id="ref_20746">Esquimaux: The Oxford English Dictionary defines "Eskimo," the singular of "Esquimaux," as: "A member of an aboriginal people inhabiting northern Canada, Alaska, Greenland, and eastern Siberia.In Canada, the word Eskimo has been superseded by Inuit (Innuit n.) with reference to the people. Eskimo, however, is the only term which applies to the people as a whole, and is still widely used, especially in anthropological and archaeological contexts."</note> are not so fastidious. We all know how they live upon whales, and have rare old vintages of prime old train oil. <ref target="#ref_17426">Zogranda</ref><note xml:id="ref_17426">Zogranda: A corruption of Dr. Sangrado in Alain Le Sage’s novel <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:199">Histoire de Gil Blas de Santillane</ref> (1715–1735), suggesting “So grand” for the pompous <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:303">Scoresby, William, 1789-1857</ref>, whom Melville elsewhere mocks as “Snoghead,” “Fogo von Slack,” and “Captain Sleet.”</note>, one of their most famous <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1471213691243-3b586x5jwjv-06976c236fef4cb8ddd917fb5d819a49%2FMD_Amer_0371.jpg"/>doctors, recommends strips of blubber for infants, as being exceedingly juicy and nourishing. And this reminds me that certain Englishmen, who long ago were accidentally left in Greenland by a whaling vessel—that these men actually lived for several months on the mouldy scraps of whales which had been left ashore after trying out the blubber. Among the Dutch whalemen these scraps are called “fritters;” which, indeed, they greatly resemble, being brown and crisp, and smelling something like old Amsterdam housewives’ dough-nuts or oly-cooks, when fresh. They have such an eatable look that the most self-denying stranger can hardly keep his hands off.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But what further depreciates the whale as a civilized dish, is his exceeding richness. He is the great prize ox of the sea, too fat to be delicately good. Look at his hump, which would be as fine eating as the buffalo’s (which is esteemed a rare dish), were it not such a solid pyramid of fat. But the spermaceti itself, how bland and creamy that is; like the transparent, half-jellied, white meat of a cocoanut in the third month of its growth, yet far too rich to supply a substitute for butter. Nevertheless, many whalemen have a method of absorbing it into some other substance, and then partaking of it. In the long <ref target="#ref_17423">try watches</ref><note xml:id="ref_17423">try watches: turns of duty at the tryworks. A watch while underway was usually four hours, but watches while trying out a whale were extended to six hours.</note> of the night it is a common thing for the seamen to dip their ship-biscuit into the huge oil-pots and let them fry there awhile. Many a <ref target="#ref_21973">good supper</ref><note xml:id="ref_21973">Many a good supper have I thus made: According to Luther S. Mansfield and Howard P. Vincent in their edition of <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:218">Moby-Dick</ref> (757), the source for the description of frying ship biscuit and whale brains in this paragraph and the next is J. Ross Browne,  <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:115">Etchings of a Whaling Cruise: With Notes of a Sojourn on the Island of Zanzibar, To Which is Appended a Brief History of the Whale Fishery, Its Past and Present Condition </ref>.</note> have I thus made.
In the case of a small Sperm Whale the brains are accounted a fine dish. The casket of the skull is broken into with an axe, and the two plump, whitish lobes being withdrawn (precisely resembling two large puddings), they are then mixed with flour, and cooked into a most delectable mess, in flavor somewhat resembling calves’ head, which is quite a dish among some epicures; and every one knows that some young <ref target="#ref_17424">bucks</ref><note xml:id="ref_17424">bucks: stylish fellows, dandies.</note> among the epicures, by continually dining upon calves’ brains, by and by get to have a little brains of their own, so as to be able to tell a calf’s head from their own heads; which, indeed, requires <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1471213712714-hxuuorzyb7r-06976c236fef4cb8ddd917fb5d819a49%2FMD_Amer_0372.jpg"/>uncommon discrimination. And that is the reason why a young buck with an intelligent looking calf’s head before him, is somehow one of the saddest sights you can see. The head looks a sort of reproachfully at him, with an <ref target="#ref_17428">“Et tu Brute!”</ref><note xml:id="ref_17428">“Et tu Brute!”: Caesar’s famous dying words, meaning “And you too, Brutus!” to his friend and assassin, in <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:200">Julius Caesar, in The Dramatic Works of William Shakespeare</ref> 3.1.77.</note> expression.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It is not, perhaps, entirely because the whale is so excessively unctuous that landsmen seem to regard the eating of him with abhorrence; that appears to result, in some way, from the consideration before mentioned: i. e. that a man should eat a newly murdered thing of the sea, and eat it too by its own light. But no doubt the first man that ever murdered an ox was regarded as a murderer; perhaps he was hung; and if he had been put on his trial by oxen, he certainly would have been; and he certainly deserved it if any murderer does. Go to the meat-market of a Saturday night and see the crowds of live bipeds staring up at the long rows of dead quadrupeds. Does not that sight take a tooth out of the cannibal’s jaw? Cannibals? who is not a cannibal?

<ref target="#ref_27533"><hi rend="bold">I tell you it will be more tolerable for the Fejee that salted down a lean missionary in his cellar against a coming famine; it will be more tolerable for that provident Fejee, I say, in the day of judgment, than for thee, civilized and enlightened gourmand, who nailest geese to the ground and feastest on their bloated livers in thy <ref target="#ref_19901">paté-de-foie-gras</ref></hi></ref>
<note xml:id="ref_19901">pâté de foie gras: a delicacy made from the livers of geese who are force fed, on a treadmill, until their livers nearly burst.</note>.
<note xml:id="ref_27533">REVISION NARRATIVE:
Providence and Pâté de Foie // In “The Whale as a Dish,” Ishmael considers the “history and philosophy” of eating whale meat and extends his pantheism, or belief that divinity resides in all things, to the comic but not necessarily absurd conclusion that eating whale is a form of cannibalism. The preceding question “who is not a cannibal?”  echoes the query “Who ain’t a slave?” in “Loomings” (Ch. 1) and recalls the image of “the universal cannibalism of the sea” in “Brit” (Ch. 58); it also anticipates the more frightful scene of “The Shark Massacre” in the following chapter. Here, however, Ishmael brings cannibalism to the dinner table and with a religious zeal that prompted his British editor to expurgate. It would have been one thing to let stand Ishmael’s stereotype of the Feejee Islander salting down a missionary, but Melville pushes the image, calling the Feejee “provident” (which here means nothing more than economical, but also suggests God’s providential favor), and he pushes further when he finds the “provident Feejee” in better standing at “the day of judgment” than the “civilized and enlightened gourmand” who feasts on pâté de foie gras, a delicacy made from the livers of geese who are force fed until their livers nearly burst. Though Melville makes a good case for vegetarianism, his British editor expurgated this entire sentence.</note><ref target="#ref_20747">Fejee</ref><note xml:id="ref_20747">Fejee: A native of the island of <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:12">Fiji</ref> in the South Pacific; the Fijians had a reputation, warranted or not, in the nineteenth century as cannibals.</note>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But Stubb, he eats the whale by its own light, does he? and that is adding insult to injury, is it? Look at your knife-handle, there, my civilized and enlightened gourmand dining off that roast beef, what is that handle made of?—what but the bones of the brother of the very ox you are eating? And what do you pick your teeth with, after devouring that fat goose? With a feather of the same fowl. And with what quill did the Secretary of the Society for the Suppression of Cruelty to Ganders formally indite his circulars? It is only within the last month or two that that society passed a resolution to patronize nothing but steel pens.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">


</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">




</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
