<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>66 The Shark Massacre</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="66-the-shark-massacre"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514503649101-sgrq3gjqx8-2eb7280a917cf16f82a00a3a1436b934%2FMD_Amer_0373.jpg"/>

			<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 66</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">THE SHARK MASSACRE.</head>


</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">When</hi> in the Southern Fishery, a captured Sperm Whale, after long and weary toil, is brought alongside late at night, it is not, as a general thing at least, customary to proceed at once to the business of cutting him in. For that business is an exceedingly laborious one; is not very soon completed; and requires all hands to set about it. Therefore, the common usage is to take in all sail; <ref target="#ref_21982">lash the helm a’lee</ref><note xml:id="ref_21982">lash the helm a’lee: tie the tiller to the leeward side, which will cause the ship to point into the wind and thus keep it relatively still.</note>; and then send every one below to his hammock till daylight, with the reservation that, until that time, <ref target="#ref_17433"><ref type="reference" target="glossary#anchor-watch"><w xml:id="anchor-watch">anchor-watches</w></ref></ref><note xml:id="ref_17433">anchor-watches: reduced guard duties. Named by analogy to the practice on non-whaling vessels that assign such duties when at anchor.</note> shall be kept; that is, two and two, for an hour each couple, the crew in rotation shall mount the deck to see that all goes well.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But sometimes, especially upon <ref target="#ref_17431">the Line</ref><note xml:id="ref_17431"> the Line: the Equator.</note> in the Pacific, this plan will not answer at all; because such incalculable hosts of sharks gather round the moored carcase, that were he left so for six hours, say, on a stretch, little more than the skeleton would be visible by morning. In most other parts of the ocean, however, where these fish do not so largely abound, their wondrous voracity can be at times considerably diminished, by vigorously stirring them up with sharp whaling-spades, a procedure notwithstanding, which, in some instances, only seems to tickle them into still greater activity. But it was not thus in the present case with the Pequod’s sharks; though, to be sure, any man unaccustomed to such sights, to have looked over her side that night, would have almost thought the whole round sea was one huge cheese, and those sharks the maggots in it.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Nevertheless, upon Stubb setting the anchor-watch after his supper was concluded; and when, accordingly, Queequeg and <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514503661111-b9j5qefhcsh-2eb7280a917cf16f82a00a3a1436b934%2FMD_Amer_0374.jpg"/> a forecastle seaman came on deck, no small excitement was created among the sharks; for immediately suspending the <ref target="#ref_17432">cutting stages</ref><note xml:id="ref_17432">cutting stages: narrow platforms hung over the side for men to stand on while cutting into the whale.</note> over the side, and lowering three lanterns, so that they cast long gleams of light over the turbid sea, these two mariners, darting their long whaling-spades, kept up an incessant murdering of the sharks,* by striking the keen steel deep into their skulls, seemingly their only vital part. But in the foamy confusion of their mixed and struggling hosts, the marksmen could not always hit their mark; and this brought about new revelations of the incredible ferocity of the foe. They viciously snapped, not only at each other’s disembowelments, but like flexible bows, bent round, and bit their own; till those entrails seemed swallowed over and over again by the same mouth, to be oppositely voided by the gaping wound. Nor was this all. It was unsafe to meddle with the corpses and ghosts of these creatures. A sort of generic or <ref target="#ref_17434">Pantheistic vitality</ref><note xml:id="ref_17434">Pantheistic vitality: Universal life force separate from a specific life; see also notes on "Pantheistic" and "Pantheists" in Ch. 35.</note> seemed to lurk in their very joints and bones, after what might be called the individual life had departed. Killed and hoisted on deck for the sake of his skin, one of these sharks almost took poor Queequeg’s hand off, when he tried to shut down the dead lid of his murderous jaw.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><ref target="#ref_17435"><hi rend="bold">“Queequeg no care what god made him shark,” said the savage, agonizingly lifting his hand up and down; “wedder Fejee god or Nantucket god; but de god wat made shark must be one dam Ingin.”</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_17435">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">“Queequeg no care what god made him shark,” said the savage, agonizingly lifting his hand up and down; “wedder Fejee god or Nantucket god; but de god wat made shark must be one dam Ingin.”</hi>: Dark-skinned Queequeg, though himself called a “devil” in Ch. 13, uses the derogatory term "Ingin" (for Indian, though pronounced like "engine") to attribute relentless ferocity or evil to God. Melville's irreverent humor, equating the Christian maker of creation to a savage, did not sit well with his British editor, and the entire line was expurgated. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note> <pb facs="/images/md-british-v2/MD_Brit_v2_0192.jpg"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<l>______________________________________________________</l>
* [Melville's Note] The whaling-spade used for cutting-in is made of the very best steel; is about the bigness of a man’s spread hand; and in general shape, corresponds to the garden implement after which it is named; only its sides are perfectly flat, and its upper end considerably narrower than the lower. This weapon is always kept as sharp as possible; and when being used is occasionally honed, just like a razor. In its socket, a stiff pole, from twenty to thirty feet long, is inserted for a handle.
<l>_________________________________________</l>
</p>
</div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
