<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>67 Cutting In</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="67-cutting-in"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514503745620-iaror3qae5-56de5b1620b25183508bc80d46fc703b%2FMD_Amer_0375.jpg"/>

			<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 67</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">CUTTING IN.</head>


</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">It</hi> was a Saturday night, and such a Sabbath as followed! <ref target="#ref_21994">Ex officio professors</ref><note xml:id="ref_21994">Ex officio professors of Sabbath breaking: Because of their occupation (ex officio), whalemen usually worked a seven-day week, violating the commandment to keep the Sabbath day holy. Here, professors are those who profess or publicly acknowledge a belief; thus, to profess Sabbath breaking is ironic. The uneasy negotiation between work and religion for Quaker whalers appears in Bildad’s “Don’t whale it too much a’ Lord’s days, men; but don’t miss a fair chance either, that’s rejecting Heaven’s good gifts” (Ch. 22).</note> of Sabbath breaking are all whalemen. The ivory Pequod was turned into what seemed a <ref target="#ref_17438">shamble</ref><note xml:id="ref_17438">shamble: slaughterhouse.</note>; every sailor a butcher. You would have thought we were offering up ten thousand <ref target="#ref_21995">red oxen</ref><note xml:id="ref_21995">offering up ten thousand red oxen to the sea gods: In their religious observances, ancient Egyptians sacrificed red oxen.</note> to the sea gods.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In the first place, the enormous <ref target="#ref_17439">cutting tackles</ref><note xml:id="ref_17439">cutting tackles: multiple rope and pulley system (block and tackle) with large hooks for lifting blubber stripped from the whale.</note>, among other ponderous things comprising a cluster of blocks generally painted green, and which no single man can possibly lift—this vast bunch of grapes was <ref target="#ref_17440">swayed up to the main-top</ref><note xml:id="ref_17440">swayed up to the main-top: hoisted to the platform at the top of the main lower mast, the ship's stoutest and strongest mast.</note> and firmly lashed to the lower mast-head, the strongest point anywhere above a ship’s deck. The end of the <ref target="#ref_17441">hawser-like</ref><note xml:id="ref_17441">hawser-like: very thick, like the rope used to tow a vessel.</note> rope winding through these intricacies, was then conducted to the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1098" type="artwork"><ref target="#ref_20749">windlass</ref><note xml:id="ref_20749">windlass: a horizontal winch.</note></name>, and the huge lower block of the tackles was swung over the whale; to this block the great blubber hook, weighing some one hundred pounds, was attached. And now suspended in stages over the side, Starbuck and Stubb, the mates, armed with their long spades, began <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1099" type="artwork">cutting a hole</name> in the body for the insertion of the hook just above the nearest of the two side-fins. This done, a broad, semicircular line is cut round the hole, the hook is inserted, and the main body of the crew striking up a wild chorus, now commence <ref target="#ref_20750">heaving</ref><note xml:id="ref_20750">heaving: pushing, the opposite of hauling (pulling). The men heave up and down on wooden bars to turn the windlass.</note> in one dense crowd at the windlass. When instantly, the entire ship careens over on her side; every bolt in her starts like the nail-heads of an old house in frosty weather; she trembles, quivers, and nods her frighted mast-heads to the sky. More and more she leans over to the whale, while every gasping heave of the windlass is answered by a helping heave from the billows; till at last, a swift, startling snap is heard; with a great swash the ship rolls <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514503763190-ztwmk4flme9-56de5b1620b25183508bc80d46fc703b%2FMD_Amer_0376.jpg"/> upwards and backwards from the whale, and the triumphant tackle rises into sight dragging after it the disengaged semicircular end of the first strip of blubber. Now as the blubber envelopes the whale precisely as the rind does an orange, so is it stripped off from the body precisely as an orange is sometimes stripped by spiralizing it. For the strain constantly kept up by the windlass continually keeps the whale rolling over and over in the water, and as the blubber in one strip uniformly peels off along the line called the “scarf,” simultaneously cut by the spades of Starbuck and Stubb, the mates; and just as fast as it is thus peeled off, and indeed by that very act itself, it is all the time being hoisted higher and higher aloft till its upper end grazes the main-top; the men at the windlass then cease heaving, and for a moment or two the prodigious blood-dripping mass sways to and fro as if let down from the sky, and every one present must take good heed to dodge it when it swings, else it may box his ears and pitch him headlong overboard.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">One of the attending harpooneers now advances with a long, keen weapon called a <ref type="reference" target="glossary#boarding-sword"><w xml:id="boarding-sword">boarding-sword</w></ref>, and watching his chance he dexterously slices out a considerable hole in the lower part of the swaying mass. Into this hole, the end of the second alternating great tackle is then hooked so as to retain a hold upon the blubber, in order to prepare for what follows. Whereupon, this accomplished swordsman, warning all hands to stand off, once more makes a scientific dash at the mass, and with a few sidelong, desperate, lunging slicings, severs it completely in twain; so that while the short lower part is still fast, the long upper strip, called a <ref target="#ref_20752">blanket-piece</ref><note xml:id="ref_20752"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1096" type="artwork">blanket-piece</name>: This large piece can weigh as much as a ton.</note>, swings clear, and is all ready for lowering. The heavers forward now resume their song, and while the one tackle is peeling and hoisting a second strip from the whale, the other is slowly slackened away, and down goes the first strip through the main hatchway right beneath, into an unfurnished parlor called the blubber-room. Into this twilight apartment sundry nimble hands keep coiling away the long blanket-<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514503778904-gysjxwi4f18-56de5b1620b25183508bc80d46fc703b%2FMD_Amer_0377.jpg"/>piece as if it were a great live mass of plaited serpents. And thus the work proceeds; the two tackles hoisting and lowering simultaneously; both whale and windlass heaving, the heavers singing, the blubber-room gentlemen coiling, the mates scarfing, the ship straining, and all hands swearing occasionally, by way of assuaging the general friction.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
