<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>77 The Great Heidelburgh Tun</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="77-the-great-heidelburgh-tun"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514571702640-gedw5823m7c-f266808706244bcbd6c3fb530dd86f45%2FMD_Amer_0414.jpg"/>
			<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 77</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">THE GREAT HEIDELBURGH TUN.</head>


</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">Now</hi> comes <ref target="#ref_22290">the Baling of the Case</ref><note xml:id="ref_22290">the Baling of the Case: According to Mansfield and Vincent in their edition of <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> (772), Melville’s description echoes Thomas Beale, <hi rend="italic">The Natural History of the Sperm Whale</hi>.</note>. But to comprehend it aright, you must know something of the curious internal structure of the thing operated upon.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Regarding the Sperm Whale’s head as a solid oblong, you may, on an inclined plane, sideways divide it into two quoins,* whereof the lower is the bony structure, forming the cranium and jaws, and the upper an unctuous mass wholly free from bones; its broad forward end forming the expanded vertical apparent forehead of the whale. At the middle of the forehead horizontally subdivide this upper quoin, and then you have two
<l>__________________________________________________</l>
* [Melville's Note] Quoin is not a <ref target="#ref_20795">Euclidean term</ref><note xml:id="ref_20795">Euclidean term: a term that comes from the Greek mathematician Euclid in his textbook on geometry, <hi rend="italic">Elements</hi>. In other words, it is not an accepted mathematical term but one that Melville has humorously  invented as "pure nautical mathematics."</note>. It belongs to the pure nautical mathematics. I know not that it has been defined before. A quoin is a solid which differs from a wedge in having its sharp end formed by the steep inclination of one side, instead of the mutual tapering of both sides.
<l>_______________________________________</l>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514571747448-5ywj7bgr5d9-f266808706244bcbd6c3fb530dd86f45%2FMD_Amer_0415.jpg"/> almost equal parts, which before were naturally divided by an internal wall of a thick tendinous substance.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The lower subdivided part, called the junk, is one immense honeycomb of oil, formed by the crossing and re-crossing, into ten thousand infiltrated cells, of tough elastic white fibres throughout its whole extent. The upper part, known as the Case, may be regarded as the <ref target="#ref_22291">great Heidelburgh Tun</ref><note xml:id="ref_22291">the great Heidelburgh Tun . . . that famous great tierce is mystically carved in front: The <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1113" type="artwork">Heidelburgh Tun</name>, a huge wine cask, or tun, in Germany’s Heidelberg Castle held 49,000 gallons, or about 1400 barrels—obviously an exaggerated comparison to the whale’s spermaceti case, which might yield as much as 80 barrels. A tierce holds 42 gallons but here means simply a large barrel. The "mystical" carvings on the front of the Tun depicted wine-drinking.</note> of the Sperm Whale. And as that famous great tierce is mystically carved in front, so the whale’s vast plaited forehead forms innumerable strange devices for the emblematical adornment of his wondrous tun. Moreover, as that of Heidelburgh was always replenished with the most excellent of the wines of the <ref target="#ref_17644">Rhenish valleys</ref><note xml:id="ref_17644">Rhenish valleys: Valleys in the Rhine River region, famous for their wine.</note>, so the tun of the whale contains by far the most precious of all his oily vintages; namely, the highly-prized spermaceti, in its absolutely pure, limpid, and odoriferous state. Nor is this precious substance found unalloyed in any other part of the creature. Though in life it remains perfectly fluid, yet, upon exposure to the air, after death, it soon begins to concrete; sending forth beautiful crystalline shoots, as when the first thin delicate ice is just forming in water. A large whale’s case generally yields about five hundred gallons of sperm, though from unavoidable circumstances, considerable of it is spilled, leaks, and dribbles away, or is otherwise irrevocably lost in the ticklish business of securing what you can.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I know not with what fine and costly material the Heidelburgh Tun was coated within, but in superlative richness that coating could not possibly have compared with the silken pearl-colored membrane, like the lining of a fine <ref target="#ref_17622">pelisse</ref><note xml:id="ref_17622">pelisse: long coat or cloak.</note>, forming the inner surface of the Sperm Whale’s case.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It will have been seen that the Heidelburgh Tun of the Sperm Whale embraces the entire length of the entire top of the head; and since—as has been elsewhere set forth—the head embraces one third of the whole length of the creature, then setting that length down at eighty feet for a good sized whale, you have more <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1514571773216-jscq0369zu-f266808706244bcbd6c3fb530dd86f45%2FMD_Amer_0416.jpg"/> than twenty-six feet for the depth of the tun, when it is lengthwise hoisted up and down against a ship’s side.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As in decapitating the whale, the operator’s instrument is brought close to the spot where an entrance is subsequently forced into the spermaceti <ref target="#ref_17629">magazine</ref><note xml:id="ref_17629">magazine: storage compartment.</note>; he has, therefore, to be uncommonly heedful, lest a careless, untimely stroke should invade the sanctuary and wastingly let out its invaluable contents. It is this decapitated end of the head, also, which is at last elevated out of the water, and retained in that position by the enormous cutting tackles, whose hempen combinations, on one side, make quite a wilderness of ropes in that quarter.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Thus much being said, attend now, I pray you, to that marvellous and—in this particular instance—almost fatal operation whereby the Sperm Whale’s great Heidelburgh Tun is tapped.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
