<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>83 Jonah Historically Regarded</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="83-jonah-historically-regarded"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518706970842-5tcwlynzlgx-82a8cf8d8851a8171495080d28eebccd%2FMD_Amer_0443.jpg"/>
			<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 83</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">JONAH HISTORICALLY REGARDED.</head>


</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">Reference</hi> was made to the historical story of Jonah and the whale in <ref target="#MDch83Note1">the preceding chapter</ref><note xml:id="MDch83Note1">the preceding chapter: Ishmael’s reference here to the preceding chapter, along with similar internal references in Chs. 88, 89, and 90, hints at Melville’s writing process: he may have composed some chapters in clusters.</note>. Now some Nantucketers rather distrust this historical story of Jonah and the whale. But then there were some sceptical Greeks and Romans, who, standing out from the orthodox pagans of their times, equally doubted the story of Hercules and the whale, and <ref target="#ref_18062">Arion and the dolphin</ref><note xml:id="ref_18062">Arion and the dolphin: Legendary Greek poet and musician Arion was forced by greedy sailors to jump overboard from his ship, but his lyre music had so charmed the dolphins that one of them carried him to shore. His lyre and the dolphin became the constellations Lyra and Delphinus. In <hi rend="italic">The Shipwreck</hi> (1762), quoted in “Extracts,” William Falconer uses Arion as a name for himself, while both Pierre Bayle in his <hi rend="italic">Historical and Critical Dictionary</hi> and John Kitto in his <hi rend="italic">Cyclopedia of Biblical Literature</hi> also allude to Arion in their remarks on Jonah.</note>; and yet their doubting those traditions did not make those traditions one whit the less facts, for all that.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">One old Sag-Harbor whaleman’s chief reason for questioning the Hebrew story was this:—He had one of those quaint old-fashioned Bibles, embellished with curious, unscientific plates; one of which represented Jonah’s whale with two spouts in his head—a peculiarity only true with respect to a species of the Leviathan (the Right Whale, and the varieties of that order), concerning which the fishermen have this saying, “A <ref target="#ref_18060">penny roll</ref><note xml:id="ref_18060">penny roll: bread roll costing one cent.</note> would choke him;” his swallow is so very small. But, to this, <ref target="#ref_21444">Bishop Jebb</ref><note xml:id="ref_21444">Bishop Jebb: John Jebb (1775–1833), Protestant bishop of Limerick, Ireland, wrote a well-known biblical commentary. Mansfield and Vincent's edition of <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> (780-81) shows that this paragraph and the next are adapted from Kitto.</note>’s anticipative answer is ready. It is not necessary, hints the Bishop, that we consider Jonah as tombed in the whale’s belly, but as temporarily lodged in some part of his mouth. And this seems reasonable enough in the good Bishop. For truly, the Right Whale’s mouth would accommodate a couple of <ref target="#ref_18061">whist-tables</ref><note xml:id="ref_18061">whist-tables: card tables.</note>, and comfortably seat all the players. Possibly, too, Jonah might have ensconced himself in a hollow tooth; but, on second thoughts, the Right Whale is toothless.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Another reason which Sag-Harbor (he went by that name) urged for his want of faith in this matter of the prophet, was something obscurely in reference to his incarcerated body and <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518706986451-i0uz2wr7t4s-82a8cf8d8851a8171495080d28eebccd%2FMD_Amer_0444.jpg"/> the whale’s gastric juices. But this objection likewise falls to the ground, because a German exegetist supposes that Jonah must have taken refuge in the floating body of a <hi rend="italic">dead</hi> whale—even as the French soldiers in the Russian campaign <ref target="#ref_21445">turned their dead horses into tents</ref><note xml:id="ref_21445">turned their dead horses into tents: During Napoleon’s retreat from his disastrous invasion of Russia in 1812, some of his troops attempted to survive the bitter winter weather by killing their horses, cutting them open, and crawling inside the still warm carcasses.</note>, and crawled into them. Besides, it has been divined by other continental commentators, that when Jonah was thrown overboard from the Joppa ship, he straightway effected his escape to another vessel near by, some vessel with a whale for a figure-head; and, I would add, possibly called “The Whale,” as some craft are nowadays christened the “Shark,” the “Gull,” the “Eagle.” Nor have there been wanting learned exegetists who have opined that the whale mentioned in the book of Jonah merely meant a life-preserver—an inflated bag of wind—which the endangered prophet swam to, and so was saved from a watery doom. Poor Sag-Harbor, therefore, seems worsted all round. But he had still another reason for his want of faith. It was this, if I remember right: Jonah was swallowed by the whale in the Mediterranean Sea, and after three days he was vomited up somewhere within three days’ journey of Nineveh, a city on the Tigris, very much more than three days’ journey across from the nearest point of the Mediterranean coast. How is that?

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But was there no other way for the whale to land the prophet within that short distance of Nineveh? Yes. He might have carried him round by the way of the Cape of Good Hope. But not to speak of the passage through the whole length of the Mediterranean, and another passage up the Persian Gulf and Red Sea, such a supposition would involve the complete circumnavigation of all Africa in three days, not to speak of the Tigris waters, near the site of Nineveh, being too shallow for any whale to swim in. Besides, this idea of Jonah’s weathering the Cape of Good Hope at so early a day would wrest the honor of the discovery of that great headland from <ref target="#MDch83Note2">Bartholomew Diaz</ref><note xml:id="MDch83Note2">Bartholomew Diaz: Portuguese mariner and explorer Bartolomeu Dias (ca. 1450-1500) was the first European navigator to round the southern tip of Africa, demonstrating a practical sea route between Europe and Asia.</note>, its reputed discoverer, and so make modern history a liar.
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518706992063-5v6011ft0pf-82a8cf8d8851a8171495080d28eebccd%2FMD_Amer_0445.jpg"/>
</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But all these foolish arguments of old Sag-Harbor only evinced his foolish pride of reason—a thing still more reprehensible in him, seeing that he had but little learning except what he had picked up from the sun and the sea. I say it only shows his foolish, impious pride, and abominable, devilish rebellion against the reverend clergy. For by a <ref target="#ref_18066">Portuguese Catholic priest</ref><note xml:id="ref_18066">Portuguese Catholic priest: Cited in Bayle but unidentified.</note>, this very idea of Jonah’s going to Nineveh viâ the Cape of Good Hope was advanced as a signal magnification of the general miracle. And so it was. Besides, to this day, the highly enlightened Turks devoutly believe in the historical story of Jonah. And some three centuries ago, an English traveller in old <ref target="#ref_21446">Harris’s Voyages</ref><note xml:id="ref_21446">English traveller in old Harris’s Voyages: According to Howard Vincent in <hi rend="italic">The Trying-out of Moby-Dick</hi> (285), Melville read the Englishman’s report not in Harris’s collection of voyages (cited in “Extracts” and Ch. 77) but in Bayle.</note>, speaks of a Turkish Mosque built in honor of Jonah, in which mosque was a miraculous lamp that burnt without any oil.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
