<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>92 Ambergris</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="92-ambergris"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1471319670876-762d5dzr8po-acda26cf95a79648ba132e1ed01b14cb%2FMD_Amer_0492.jpg"/>
			<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 92</head>
			<lb/>
			<head type="sub-head" rend="center">AMBERGRIS.</head>


</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">Now</hi> this ambergris is a very curious substance, and so important as an article of commerce, that in 1791 a certain <ref target="#ref_20160">Nantucket-born Captain Coffin</ref><note xml:id="ref_20160">Nantucket-born Captain Coffin: For Ch. 92, Melville borrowed directly from Thomas Beale’s chapter on “Ambergris” in <hi rend="italic">Natural History of the Sperm Whale</hi>. Melville’s copy of Beale (Sealts 52), purchased in July 1850, is heavily marked (see MMO). Melville also added details from Henry T. Cheever, <hi rend="italic">The Whale and His Captors</hi>. In this sentence quoted from Beale, Melville added "Nantucket-born."</note> was examined at the bar of the English House of Commons on that subject. For at that time, and indeed until a comparatively late day, the precise origin of ambergris remained, like <ref target="#ref_20161">amber</ref><note xml:id="ref_20161">amber: translucent, yellow-brown, fossilized sap. </note> itself, a problem to the learned. Though the word ambergris is but the French compound for grey amber, yet the two substances are quite distinct. For amber, though at times found on the sea-coast, is also dug up in some far inland soils, whereas ambergris is never found except upon the sea. Besides, amber is a hard, transparent, brittle, odorless substance, used for mouth-pieces to pipes, for beads and ornaments; but ambergris is soft, waxy, and so highly fra-<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1471319683944-an0g945ocpn-acda26cf95a79648ba132e1ed01b14cb%2FMD_Amer_0493.jpg"/>grant and spicy, that it is largely used in perfumery, in <ref target="#ref_20116">pastiles</ref><note xml:id="ref_20116">pastiles: usually sweet or medicinal lozenges, but here, deodorizing tablets.</note>, precious candles, hair-powders, and <ref target="#ref_20115">pomatum</ref><note xml:id="ref_20115">pomatum: pomade, hair ointment.</note>. The Turks use it in cooking, and also carry it to Mecca, for the same purpose that frankincense is carried to St. Peter’s in Rome. Some wine merchants drop a few grains into claret, to flavor it.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Who would think, then, that such fine ladies and gentlemen should regale themselves with an essence found in the inglorious bowels of a sick whale! Yet so it is. By some, ambergris is supposed to be the cause, and by others the effect, of the dyspepsia in the whale. How to cure such a dyspepsia it were hard to say, unless by administering three or four boat loads of <ref target="#ref_20114">Brandreth’s pills</ref><note xml:id="ref_20114">Brandreth’s pills: a brand of laxative.</note>, and then running out of harm’s way, as laborers do in blasting rocks.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I have forgotten to say that there were found in this ambergris, certain hard, round, bony plates, which at first Stubb thought might be sailors’ trousers buttons; but it afterwards turned out that they were nothing more than pieces of small squid bones embalmed in that manner.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Now that the incorruption of this most fragrant ambergris should be found in the heart of such decay; is this nothing? Bethink thee of that saying of St. Paul in Corinthians, about <ref target="#ref_20162">corruption and incorruption</ref><note xml:id="ref_20162">corruption and incorruption: Melville is echoing 1 Corinthians 15.42–43: “So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption; it is raised in incorruption: It is sown in dishonour; it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness; it is raised in power."</note>; how that we are sown in dishonor, but raised in glory. And likewise call to mind that saying of <ref target="#ref_20163">Paracelsus</ref><note xml:id="ref_20163">Paracelsus: Swiss alchemist, physician, and astrologer <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:403">Theophrastus von Hohenheim</ref> (ca. 1493-1541), known as Paracelsus, is quoted in Sir Thomas Browne as saying that the best musk (odorous substance used in making perfumes) comes from “ordure” (excrement). Melville likely got this passage (as well as his quotation from Browne in “Extracts” and the epigraph for Ch. 91) from Thomas Beale who, in <hi rend="italic">Natural History of the Sperm Whale</hi>, quotes all three passages on one page. See also note on "Paracelsan superstition" in Ch. 94.</note> about what it is that maketh the best musk. Also forget not the strange fact that of all things of ill-savor, Cologne-water, in its rudimental manufacturing stages, is the worst.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I should like to conclude the chapter with the above appeal, but cannot, owing to my anxiety to repel a charge often made against whalemen, and which, in the estimation of some already biased minds, might be considered as indirectly substantiated by what has been said of the Frenchman’s two whales. <ref target="#ref_20113">Elsewhere in this volume</ref><note xml:id="ref_20113">Elsewhere in this volume: See Ch. 98.</note> the slanderous aspersion has been disproved, that the vocation of whaling is throughout a slatternly, untidy business. But there is another thing to rebut. They hint that <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1471319694530-rybsld7kaw-acda26cf95a79648ba132e1ed01b14cb%2FMD_Amer_0494.jpg"/> all whales always smell bad. Now how did this odious stigma originate?

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I opine, that it is plainly traceable to the first arrival of the Greenland whaling ships in London, more than two centuries ago. Because those whalemen did not then, and do not now, <ref target="#ref_20112">try out</ref><note xml:id="ref_20112">try out: extract oil from blubber by boiling.</note> their oil at sea as the Southern ships have always done; but cutting up the fresh blubber in small bits, thrust it through the bung holes of large casks, and carry it home in that manner; the shortness of the season in those Icy Seas, and the sudden and violent storms to which they are exposed, forbidding any other course. The consequence is, that upon breaking into the hold, and unloading one of these whale cemeteries, in the Greenland dock, a savor is given forth somewhat similar to that arising from excavating an old city grave-yard, for the foundations of a <ref target="#ref_20111">Lying-in</ref><note xml:id="ref_20111">Lying-in: maternity.</note> Hospital.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">I partly surmise also, that this wicked charge against whalers may be likewise imputed to the existence on the coast of Greenland, in former times, of a Dutch village called Schmerenburgh or Smeerenberg, which latter name is the one used by the learned <ref target="#ref_20164">Fogo Von Slack</ref><note xml:id="ref_20164">Fogo Von Slack: Another teasing name for, and jab at, William Scoresby, whose <hi rend="italic">Account of the Arctic Regions</hi> comments on the smell of whale oil and also defines Smeerenberg exactly as Melville does here. See Mansfield and Vincent (795).</note>, in his great work on Smells, a text-book on that subject. As its name imports (smeer, fat; berg, to put up), this village was founded in order to afford a place for the blubber of the Dutch whale fleet to be tried out, without being taken home to Holland for that purpose. It was a collection of furnaces, fat-kettles, and oil sheds; and when the works were in full operation certainly gave forth no very pleasant savor. But all this is quite different with a South Sea Sperm Whaler; which in a voyage of four years perhaps, after completely filling her hold with oil, does not, perhaps, consume fifty days in the business of boiling out; and in the state that it is casked, the oil is nearly scentless. The truth is, that living or dead, if but decently treated, whales as a species are by no means creatures of ill odor; nor can whalemen be recognised, as the people of the middle ages affected to <ref target="#ref_20165">detect a Jew</ref><note xml:id="ref_20165">to detect a Jew: Among the many medieval libels about Jews is the myth of a “foetor judaicus” (Jewish smell).</note> in the <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1471319719829-6zn5ocm9snn-acda26cf95a79648ba132e1ed01b14cb%2FMD_Amer_0495.jpg"/> company, by the nose. Nor indeed can the whale possibly be otherwise than fragrant, when, as a general thing, he enjoys such high health; taking abundance of exercise; always out of doors; though, it is true, seldom in the open air. I say, that the motion of a Sperm Whale’s flukes above water dispenses a perfume, as when a musk-scented lady rustles her dress in a warm parlor. What then shall I liken the Sperm Whale to for fragrance, considering his magnitude? Must it not be to <ref target="#ref_20166">that famous elephant</ref><note xml:id="ref_20166">that famous elephant: Indian princes gave many such elephants to Greek conqueror Alexander the Great (356-323 BCE).</note>, with jewelled tusks, and redolent with <ref target="#MDch92Note1">myrrh</ref><note xml:id="MDch92Note1">myrrh: an aromatic resin from certain trees.</note>, which was led out of an Indian town to do honor to Alexander the Great?
</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
