<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>94 A Squeeze of the Hand</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="94-a-squeeze-of-the-hand"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518929071879-bg0tg8zq38m-cf6cab8b122bb5babe9893759f499981%2FMD_Amer_0500.jpg"/>

							<head type="main" rend="center">CHAPTER 94</head>
							<lb/>
							<head type="sub-head" rend="center">A SQUEEZE OF THE HAND.</head>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><hi rend="smallcaps">That</hi> whale of Stubb’s, so dearly purchased, was duly brought to the Pequod’s side, where all those cutting and hoisting operations previously detailed, were regularly gone through, even to the baling of the Heidelburgh Tun, or Case.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">While some were occupied with this latter duty, others were employed in dragging away the larger tubs, so soon as filled with the sperm; and when the proper time arrived, this same sperm was carefully manipulated ere going to the <ref target="#ref_18263">try-works</ref><note xml:id="ref_18263">try-works: brick furnace with iron cauldrons in which oil is boiled out of blubber.</note>, of which anon.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It had cooled and crystallized to such a degree, that when, with several others, I sat down before a large <ref target="#ref_18268">Constantine’s bath</ref><note xml:id="ref_18268">Constantine’s bath: Constantine the Great (272–337 CE) was the first Christian Roman emperor. His public baths, which would have included the kind of massive tub Ishmael refers to, were constructed on Quirinal hill in 315 CE but <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1072" type="artwork">fell into ruin</name> two centuries later. The Palazzo Rospigliosi, which Melville visited in 1857, stands on the site. See also Mansfield and Vincent (531–32).</note> of it, I found it strangely concreted into lumps, here and there rolling about in the liquid part. It was our business to squeeze these lumps back into fluid. A sweet and unctuous duty! No wonder that in old times this sperm was such a favorite cosmetic. Such a clearer! such a sweetener! such a softener! such a delicious mollifier! After having my hands in it for only a few minutes, my fingers felt like eels, and began, as it were, to serpentine and spiralize.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As I sat there at my ease, cross-legged on the deck; after the bitter exertion at the windlass; under a blue tranquil sky; the <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518929083307-imwhkw7xne9-cf6cab8b122bb5babe9893759f499981%2FMD_Amer_0501.jpg"/> ship under indolent sail, and gliding so serenely along; as I bathed my hands among those soft, gentle globules of infiltrated tissues, woven almost within the hour; as they richly broke to my fingers, and discharged all their opulence, like fully ripe grapes their wine; as I snuffed up that uncontaminated aroma,—literally and truly, like the smell of spring violets; I declare to you, that for the time I lived as in a musky meadow; I forgot all about our horrible oath; in that inexpressible sperm, I washed my hands and my heart of it; I almost began to credit the old <ref target="#ref_21665">Paracelsan superstition</ref><note xml:id="ref_21665">Paracelsan superstition: The Swiss alchemist Theophrastus von Hohenheim (ca. 1493-1541), also known as Paracelsus, practiced magic and medicine throughout Europe, was considered a quack, but is also credited as the founder of chemistry. Melville’s source for this "superstition" that "sperm is of rare virtue in allaying the heat of anger" is unknown. See also note on Paracelsus in Ch. 92.</note> that sperm is of rare virtue in allaying the heat of anger: while bathing in that bath, I felt divinely free from all ill-will, or petulance, or malice, of any sort whatsoever.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Squeeze! squeeze! squeeze! all the morning long; I squeezed that sperm till I myself almost melted into it; I squeezed that sperm till a strange sort of insanity came over me; and I found myself unwittingly squeezing my co-laborers’ hands in it, mistaking their hands for the gentle globules. Such an abounding, affectionate, friendly, loving feeling did this avocation beget; that at last I was continually squeezing their hands, and looking up into their eyes sentimentally; as much as to say,—Oh! my dear fellow beings, why should we longer cherish any social acerbities, or know the slightest ill-humor or envy! Come; let us squeeze hands all round; nay, let us all squeeze ourselves into each other; let us squeeze ourselves universally into the very milk and sperm of kindness.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Would that I could keep squeezing that sperm for ever! For now, since by many prolonged, repeated experiences, I have perceived that in all cases man must eventually lower, or at least shift, his conceit of attainable felicity; not placing it anywhere in the intellect or the fancy; but in the wife, the heart, the bed, the table, the saddle, the fire-side, the country; now that I have perceived all this, I am ready to squeeze case eternally. <ref target="#ref_18266">In thoughts of the visions of the night</ref><note xml:id="ref_18266">In thoughts of the visions of the night: Melville revises a passage from the Book of Job: “In thoughts from the visions of the night, when deep sleep falleth on men, Fear came upon me, and trembling, which made all my bones to shake” (4.13). The audacious revision creates a mixture of peace, joy, and implicit sexuality.</note>, I saw long rows <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518929088388-9xljwx2n3d7-cf6cab8b122bb5babe9893759f499981%2FMD_Amer_0502.jpg"/> of angels in paradise, each with his hands in a jar of spermaceti.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0; *

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Now, while discoursing of sperm, it behooves to speak of other things akin to it, in the business of preparing the sperm whale for the try-works.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">First comes white-horse, so called, which is obtained from the tapering part of the fish, and also from the thicker portions of his flukes. It is tough with congealed tendons—a wad of muscle—but still contains some oil. After being severed from the whale, the white-horse is first cut into portable oblongs ere going to the mincer. They look much like blocks of Berkshire marble.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Plum-pudding is the term bestowed upon certain fragmentary parts of the whale’s flesh, here and there adhering to the blanket of blubber, and often participating to a considerable degree in its unctuousness. It is a most refreshing, convivial, beautiful object to behold. As its name imports, it is of an exceedingly rich, mottled tint, with a bestreaked <ref target="#ref_21666">snowy and golden ground</ref><note xml:id="ref_21666">snowy and golden ground, dotted with spots of the deepest crimson and purple: The phrase suggests the technique of British painter J.M.W. Turner, who applied such a ground (base coat) to his canvases, later adding strokes of color. (See Robert K. Wallace, <hi rend="italic">Melville and Turner</hi>.)</note>, dotted with spots of the deepest crimson and purple. It is plums of rubies, in pictures of <ref target="#ref_18272">citron</ref><note xml:id="ref_18272">citron: yellowish fruit.</note>. Spite of reason, it is hard to keep yourself from eating it. I confess, that once I stole behind the foremast to try it. It tasted something as I should conceive a royal cutlet from the thigh of <ref target="#ref_18264">Louis le Gros</ref><note xml:id="ref_18264">Louis le Gros: <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:404">Louis VI of France</ref> (1081-1137), known as le Gros (the Fat).</note> might have tasted, supposing him to have been killed the first day after the venison season, and that particular venison season contemporary with an unusually fine vintage of the vineyards of Champagne.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">There is another substance, and a very singular one, which turns up in the course of this business, but which I feel it to be very puzzling adequately to describe. It is called slobgollion; an appellation original with the whalemen, and even so is the nature of the substance. It is an ineffably oozy, stringy affair, most frequently found in the tubs of sperm, after a prolonged <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518929094683-n7xl12bgb5-cf6cab8b122bb5babe9893759f499981%2FMD_Amer_0503.jpg"/> squeezing, and subsequent decanting. I hold it to be the wondrously thin, ruptured membranes of the case, coalescing.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Gurry, so called, is a term properly belonging to right whalemen, but sometimes incidentally used by the sperm fishermen. It designates the dark, glutinous substance which is scraped off the back of the Greenland or right whale, and much of which covers the decks of those inferior souls who hunt that ignoble Leviathan.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Nippers. Strictly this word is not indigenous to the whale’s vocabulary. But as applied by whalemen, it becomes so. A whaleman’s nipper is a short firm strip of tendinous stuff cut from the tapering part of Leviathan’s tail: it averages an inch in thickness, and for the rest, is about the size of the iron part of a hoe. Edgewise moved along the oily deck, it operates like a leathern <ref target="#ref_18271">squilgee</ref><note xml:id="ref_18271">squilgee: squeegee.</note>; and by nameless blandishments, as of magic, allures along with it all impurities.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But to learn all about these recondite matters, your best way is at once to descend into the blubber-room, and have a long talk with its inmates. This place has <ref target="#ref_18270">previously been mentioned</ref><note xml:id="ref_18270">previously been mentioned: see Ch. 67.</note> as the receptacle for the blanket-pieces, when stript and hoisted from the whale. When the proper time arrives for cutting up its contents, this apartment is a scene of terror to all tyros, especially by night. On one side, lit by a dull lantern, a space has been left clear for the workmen. They generally go in pairs,—a pike-and-gaff-man and a spade-man. The whaling-pike is similar to a frigate’s boarding-weapon of the same name. The gaff is something like a boat-hook. With his gaff, the gaffman hooks on to a sheet of blubber, and strives to hold it from slipping, as the ship pitches and lurches about. Meanwhile, the spade-man stands on the sheet itself, perpendicularly chopping it into the portable <ref target="#ref_18269">horse-pieces</ref><note xml:id="ref_18269">horse-pieces: blocks of blubber about 10 inches wide and 2 feet long.</note>. This spade is sharp as hone can make it; the spademan’s feet are shoeless; the thing he stands on will sometimes irresistibly slide away from him, like a sledge. If he cuts off one of his own toes, or one <pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1518929103226-3kvhslqhgz-cf6cab8b122bb5babe9893759f499981%2FMD_Amer_0504.jpg"/> of his assistant’s, would you be very much astonished? Toes are scarce among veteran blubber-room men.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
