<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>Extracts</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body>
			<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212165223-4ni9kaqxt4n-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0023.jpg"/>
			<head type="main" rend="center">EXTRACTS.</head>
			<lb/>
<head type="sub-head" rend="center">(<hi rend="smalcaps"><hi rend="bold">Supplied by a Sub-Sub-Librarian</hi></hi>.)</head>

<p>It will be seen that this mere painstaking burrower and grub-worm of a poor devil of a Sub-Sub appears to have gone through the long <ref target="#ref_19454">Vaticans</ref><note xml:id="ref_19454">Vaticans: great libraries, such as the Vatican's in Vatican City</note> and street-stalls of the earth, picking up whatever random allusions to whales he could anyways find in any book whatsoever, sacred or profane. Therefore you must not, in every case at least, take the higgledy-piggledy whale statements, however authentic, in these extracts, for veritable gospel cetology. Far from it. As touching the ancient authors generally, as well as the poets here appearing, these extracts are solely valuable or entertaining, as affording a glancing bird’s eye view of what has been <ref target="#ref_19455">promiscuously</ref><note xml:id="ref_19455">promiscuously: diversely; unsystematically. </note> said, thought, fancied, and sung of <ref target="#ref_19456">Leviathan</ref><note xml:id="ref_19456">Leviathan: biblical sea creature, not necessarily a whale.</note>, by many nations and generations, including our own.</p>
<p>So fare thee well, poor devil of a Sub-Sub, whose commentator I am. Thou belongest to that hopeless, sallow tribe which no wine of this world will ever warm; and for whom even Pale Sherry would be too rosy-strong; but with whom one sometimes loves to sit, and feel poor-devilish, too; and grow convivial upon tears; and say to them bluntly, with full eyes and empty glasses, and in not altogether unpleasant sadness—Give it up, Sub-Subs! For by how much the more pains ye take to please the world, by so much the more shall ye for ever go thankless! Would that I could clear out <ref target="#ref_19457">Hampton Court and the Tuileries</ref><note xml:id="ref_19457"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1008" type="artwork">Hampton Court</name> and the Tuileries: royal residences in London and Paris.</note> for ye! But gulp down your tears and hie aloft to the <ref target="#ref_19458">royal-mast</ref><note xml:id="ref_19458">royal-mast: highest part of the mast.</note> with your hearts; for your friends who have gone before are clearing out the <ref target="#ref_19459">seven-storied heavens</ref><note xml:id="ref_19459">seven-storied heavens: in Jewish and Islamic traditions, Heaven has seven levels.</note>, and making refugees of long-pampered
<ref target="#ref_20840">Gabriel, Michael, and Raphael, against your coming</ref><note xml:id="ref_20840">Gabriel, <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:143">Michael</ref>, and Raphael, against your coming: three principal archangels. Here, "against" means preparing for.</note>. Here ye strike but splintered hearts together—there, ye shall strike unsplinterable glasses!</p>
<lb/>
<head type="main" rend="center"><ref target="#MDextractsNote1">E X T R A C T S</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote1">Extracts: Melville assembled this collection of quotations from works he consulted while writing <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>. The British edition places both “Etymology” and “Extracts” as an appendix at the end of <hi rend="italic">The Whale</hi>; it also omits the epilogue (in which Ishmael tells of his survival), and scholars speculate that the epilogue may have been inadvertently dropped when “Etymology” and “Extracts” were appended (see NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>, 677–80). According to NN editor G. Thomas Tanselle, Melville fashioned “Extracts” by borrowing directly from sources, but also indirectly by quoting source quotations as they appeared in other books, in particular Beale’s <hi rend="italic">Natural History of the Sperm Whale</hi>, J. Ross Browne’s <hi rend="italic">Etchings of a Whaling Cruise</hi>, John Harris’s <hi rend="italic">Compleat Collection of Voyages and Travels</hi>, and Charles Richardson’s <hi rend="italic">New Dictionary of the English Language</hi> (NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>, 813–30). In addition, some of Melville’s extracts vary from their original sources, either due to errors in transcription or because Melville revised them intentionally. The individual notes listed below by source author or title draw upon Tanselle’s work and discuss Melville’s likely revision of his sources.</note>.</head> <pb facs="/images/md-american/MD_Amer_0024.jpg"/>
<p rend="center">“And God created great whales.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
	<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:104" type="text"><hi rend="italic"> Genesis</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>

<p rend="center">“Leviathan maketh a path to shine after him;  One would think the deep to be hoary.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote2"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:105" type="text"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Job</hi></hi></name></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote2">Melville revised “He maketh” in Job 41:32 to “Leviathan maketh.”</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Now the Lord had prepared a great fish to swallow up <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:930" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:219" type="person">Jonah</name></name>.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:106" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Jonah</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“There go the ships; there is that Leviathan whom thou hast made to play therein.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:107" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Psalms</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“In that day, the Lord with his sore, and great, and strong sword, shall punish Leviathan the piercing serpent, even Leviathan that crooked serpent; and he shall slay the dragon that is in the sea.”</p>	<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:108" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Isaiah</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“And what thing soever besides cometh within the chaos of this monster’s mouth, be it beast, boat, or stone, down it goes all incontinently that foul great swallow of his, and perisheth in the bottomless gulf of his paunch.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:231" type="person">Holland</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:232" type="person">Plutarch</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:109" type="text">Morals</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:18" type="place">Indian Sea</name> breedeth the most and the biggest fishes that are: among which the Whales and Whirlpooles called Balæne, take up as much in length as four acres or arpens of land.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:112" type="text"><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:231" type="person">Holland</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:233" type="person">Pliny</name></hi></name>.</p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212264819-7f1uaiiaapt-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0025.jpg"/><p>“Scarcely had we proceeded two days on the sea, when about sunrise a great many Whales and other monsters of the sea, appeared. Among the former, one was of a most monstrous size.   *   *   This came towards us, open-mouthed, raising the waves on all sides, and beating the sea before him into a foam.”</p>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote3"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:235" type="person">Tooke</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:234" type="person">Lucian</name></hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote3">Melville revised the original “monsters of the deep” to “monsters of the sea,” and “enormous” to “monstrous.”</note>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">“<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:113" type="text">The True History</name>.”</hi></p>
<lb/>

<p>“He visited this country also with a view of catching horse-whales, which had bones of very great value for their teeth, of which he brought some to the king.   *   *   *   The best whales were catched in his own country, of which some were forty-eight, some fifty yards long. He said that he was one of six who had killed sixty in two days.”</p>

<p><ref target="#ref_19502"><hi rend="italic">Other or Octher’s verbal narrative taken down from his mouth by King Alfred. A. D. 890.</hi></ref></p>

<note xml:id="ref_19502">Norwegian chieftain <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:251">Other or Octher (also spelled Ohthere or Ottar)</ref> presented <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:240">English King Alfred (849-899)</ref> with an account of his travels. Melville may not have been aware of the complicated history of "Octher's verbal narrative." The travel account of
Ohthere or Ottar was included in a 9th-century volume containing a translation of a 5th-century historical work by <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:252">Paulus Orosius</ref>, called <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:121">Seven Books of History Against the Pagans</ref>. As a codifier of English law and collector of histories, Alfred commissioned an Anglo-Saxon translation of Orosius and included Ohthere's travel narrative as well. It is likely that Melville found this passage in <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:115">J. Ross Browne's Etchings of a Whaling Cruise</ref>.</note>
<lb/>

<p>“And whereas all the other things, whether beast or vessel, that enter into the dreadful gulf of this monster’s (whale’s) mouth, are immediately lost and swallowed up, the sea-gudgeon retires into it in great security, and there sleeps.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:241" type="person"><hi rend="smallcaps">Montaigne</hi></name>.<hi rend="italic">—Apology for Raimond Sebond.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“Let us fly, let us fly! Old Nick take me if it is not Leviathan described by the noble prophet Moses in the life of patient <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:105" type="person">Job</name>.”</p>	<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:242" type="person"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:117" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Rabelais</hi></name></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“This whale’s liver was two cart-loads.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:243" type="person">Stowe</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:118" type="text">Annals</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The great Leviathan that maketh the seas to seethe like boiling pan.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lord <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:244" type="person">Bacon</name>’s Version of the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:119" type="text">Psalms</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Touching that monstrous bulk of the whale or ork we have received nothing certain. They grow exceeding fat, insomuch that an incredible quantity of oil will be extracted out of one whale.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:244" type="person"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi></name>.</p>
				<p>“<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:120" type="text"><hi rend="italic">History of Life and Death</hi></name>.”</p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212298194-mvlh3z265xg-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0026.jpg"/><p>“The sovereignest thing on earth is parmacetti for an inward bruise.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:122" type="text"><hi rend="italic">King Henry</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Very like a whale.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:123" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Which to secure, no skill of leach’s art</l>
<l rend="4em">Mote him availle, but to returne againe</l>
<l rend="4em">To his wound’s worker, that with lowly dart,</l>
<l rend="4em">Dinting his breast, had bred his restless paine,</l>
<l rend="4em">Like as the wounded whale to shore flies thro’ the maine.”</l>
</lg>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:124" type="text"><hi rend="italic">The Fairie Queen</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Immense as whales, the motion of whose vast bodies can in a peaceful calm trouble the ocean till it boil.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sir <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:247" type="person">William Davenant</name>. Preface to <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:125" type="text">Gondibert</name>.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“What spermacetti is, men might justly doubt, since the learned Hofmannus in his work of thirty years, saith plainly, Nescio quid sit.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sir T. <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:112" type="person">Browne</name>. Of Sperma Ceti and the Sperma Ceti Whale. Vide his <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:126" type="text">V. E.</name></hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Like Spencer’s Talus with his modern flail</l>
<l rend="4em">He threatens ruin with his ponderous tail.</l>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*</l>
<l rend="4em">Their fixed jav’lins in his side he wears,</l>
<l rend="4em">And on his back a grove of pikes appears.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote4"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:253" type="person">Waller</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:129" type="text">Battle of the Summer Islands</name></hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote4">In his poem, Edmund Waller has “iron flail” not “modern flail.” Taking this as an error in transcription, the editors of the NN Moby-Dick emend the text to “iron”; however, MEL retains “modern” as a possibly intentional revision of the source. In quoting, Melville also brought two widely separated couplets together and altered “her” twice in the second couplet to “his” to make the pronouns agree in gender with those in the first couplet.</note>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“By art is created that great Leviathan, called a Commonwealth or State—(in Latin, Civitas) which is but an artificial man.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Opening sentence of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:254" type="person">Hobbes</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:130" type="text">Leviathan</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Silly Mansoul swallowed it without chewing, as if it had been a sprat in the mouth of a whale.”	<ref target="#ref_19461"><hi rend="bold">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19461">REVISION NARRATIVE: Quotation, Source, and Attribution // <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:131">Pilgrim's Progress</ref> is <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:255">John Bunyan</ref>'s 1678 Christian allegory; however, Melville's quoted passage is actually from Bunyan's <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:132">The Holy War</ref> (1682), which Melville drew upon from the slightly reworded version from The Holy War quoted by Henry Cheever in his Whale and His Captors. The American edition incorrectly attributes the passage to Bunyan’s Pilgrim’s Progress, whereas the British edition correctly attributes it to The Holy War. Melville may have made the correction himself in the proofs he sent to England, or an alert editor may have caught the mistake. The editors of the NN Moby-Dick emend the attribution to The Holy War; however, in keeping with its policy of not correcting Melville’s errors of fact, MEL retains Pilgrim’s Progress, calling attention to the error through textual annotation. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note>. <pb facs="/images/md-british-v3/MD_Brit_v3_0330.jpg"/>
</p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212353470-hm13lzp9cor-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0027.jpg"/><lg>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;“That sea beast</l>
<l rend="4em">Leviathan, which God of all his works</l>
<l rend="4em">Created hugest that swim the ocean stream.”</l>
</lg>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:133" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;—— “There Leviathan,</l>
<l rend="4em">Hugest of living creatures, in the deep</l>
<l rend="4em">Stretched like a promontory sleeps or swims,</l>
<l rend="4em">And seems a moving land; and at his gills</l>
<l rend="4em">Draws in, and at his breath spouts out a sea.”</l>
	</lg>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote5"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Ibid</hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote5">REVISION NARRATIVE: Extract and Epigraph // <hi rend="bold">Ibid.</hi> is the standard but now rarely used Latin abbreviation in bibliography for "ibidem" that refers the reader to the previously cited source, in this case Milton's Paradise Lost. In this second passage (from Book VII, lines 412–16), Melville revised Milton: he gives “<hi rend="bold">in</hi> the deep” instead of Milton’s original "<hi rend="bold">on</hi> the deep” (although this may be a typo) and “his <hi rend="bold">breath</hi> spouts out a sea” instead of Milton’s “his <hi rend="bold">trunk</hi> spouts out a sea.” Both changes, neither one corrected by British editors, may reflect Melville’s scorn (addressed in Ch. 55) for erroneous renderings of whales, which, of course, do not have “trunks” nor sleep “on” the deep. Melville’s British editor used Melville’s modified passage as an epigraph appearing on the title page of each of the British edition’s three volumes. The American edition has no epigraph. To view Melville’s Miltonic passage as both Extract and Epigraph, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note>. <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0012.jpg"/>
</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The mighty whales which swim in a sea of water, and have a sea of oil swimming in them.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:257" type="person">Fuller</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:135" type="text">Profane and Holy State</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="2em">“So close behind some promontory lie</l>
<l rend="4em">The huge Leviathans to attend their prey,</l>
<l rend="2em">And give no chace, but swallow in the fry,</l>
<l rend="4em">Which through their gaping jaws mistake the way.”</l>
</lg>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:256" type="person">Dryden</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:134" type="text">Annus Mirabilis</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“While the whale is floating at the stern of the ship, they cut off his head, and tow it with a boat as near the shore as it will come; but it will be aground in twelve or thirteen foot water.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:258" type="person">Thomas Edge</name>’s Ten Voyages to <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:922" type="artwork">Spitzbergen</name>, in <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:259" type="person"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:136" type="text">Purchass</name></name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“In their way they saw many whales sporting in the ocean, and in wantonness fuzzing up the water through their pipes and vents, which nature has placed on their shoulders.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sir <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:261" type="person">T. Herbert</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:137" type="text">Voyages into Asia and Africa</name>. <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:262" type="person">Harris</name> <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:138" type="text">Coll</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Here they saw such huge troops of whales, that they were forced to proceed with a great deal of caution for fear they should run their ship upon them.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:263" type="person">Schouten</name>’s Sixth Circumnavigation</hi>.</p>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212389524-6eh8q6a0ko6-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0028.jpg"/>
<p>“We set sail from the Elbe, wind N. E. in the ship called The Jonas-in-the-Whale.   *   *   * </p>
<p>Some say the whale can’t open his mouth, but that is a fable.   *   *   * </p>
<p>They frequently climb up the masts to see whether they can see a whale, for the first discoverer has a ducat for his pains.   *   *   * </p>
<p>I was told of a whale taken near Shetland, that had above a barrel of herrings in his belly.   *   *   * </p>
<p>One of our harpooneers told me that he caught once a whale in Spitzbergen that was white all over.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:139" type="text"><ref target="#ref_19538"><hi rend="italic">A Voyage to Greenland, A.D.1671</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19538">A Voyage to Greenland: The author of this text is <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:264">Friedrich Martens (1635-1699)</ref>.</note></name>.</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:138" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Harris Coll</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Several whales have come in upon this coast (Fife). Anno 1652, one eighty feet in length of the whale-bone kind came in, which, (as I was informed) besides a vast quantity of oil, did afford 500 weight of baleen. The jaws of it stand for a gate in the garden of Pitfirren.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:265" type="person">Sibbald</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:140" type="text">Fife and Kinross</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Myself have agreed to try whether I can master and kill this Sperma-ceti whale, for I could never hear of any of that sort that was killed by any man, such is his fierceness and swiftness.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:141" type="text">Richard Stafford’s Letter from the Bermudas. Phil. Trans. A. D.1668</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em"> “Whales in the sea</l>
<l rend="4em">God’s voice obey.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:931" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:142" type="text"><hi rend="italic">N. E. Primer</hi></name></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“We saw also abundance of large whales, there being more in those southern seas, as I may say, by a hundred to one; than we have to the northward of us.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:266" type="person">Captain Cowley</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:143" type="text">Voyage round the Globe</name>. A. D. 1729.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; “and the breath of the whale is frequently attended with such an insupportable smell, as to bring on a disorder of the brain.”</p>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote6"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:267" type="person">Ulloa</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:144" type="text">South America</name></hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote6">REVISION NARRATIVE: The original source speaks of the “insupportable smell” of a fish. Melville essentially adapts the observation, applying it to whales, to create an “extract” of his own.</note>.</p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431182144603-k5tqa81z1nb-70e1a0d5897d5bd0a0feac2a628413ef%2F000005737_0029.jpg"/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“To fifty chosen sylphs of special note,</l>
<l rend="4em">We trust the important charge, the petticoat.</l>
<l rend="4em">Oft have we known that seven-fold fence to fail,</l>
<l rend="4em">Tho’ stuffed with hoops and armed with ribs of whale.”</l>
</lg>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:149" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Rape of the Lock</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“If we compare land animals in respect to magnitude, with those that take up their abode in the deep, we shall find they will appear contemptible in the comparison. The whale is doubtless the largest animal in creation.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:936" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:275" type="person">Goldsmith</name></name>, <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:150" type="text"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:936" type="artwork">Nat. His</name>.</name></hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“If you should write a fable for little fishes, you would make them speak like great whales.”</p>
<p><ref target="#ref_19569"><hi rend="italic">Goldsmith to Johnson</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19569">Goldsmith to Johnson: This line appears in the <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:151">Life of Samuel Johnson</ref> by <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:277">James Boswell</ref>, who is paraphrasing a remark by <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:275">Oliver Goldsmith</ref> to <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:276">Johnson</ref>.</note>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“In the afternoon we saw what was supposed to be a rock, but it was found to be a dead whale, which some Asiatics had killed, and were then towing ashore. They seemed to endeavor to conceal themselves behind the whale, in order to avoid being seen by us.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:222" type="person">Cook</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:152" type="text">Voyages</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The larger whales, they seldom venture to attack. They stand in so great dread of some of them, that when out at sea they are afraid to mention even their names, and carry dung, <ref target="#MDextractsNote7">lime-stone</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote7">lime-stone: Melville’s word “lime-stone,” appearing in both American and British editions, is “brim-stone” in the original Von Troil source and may be a mis-transcription on Melville’s part. The editors of the NN Moby-Dick emend “lime-stone” to “brim-stone,” but in keeping with its principle of not correcting Melville’s errors, MEL makes no change but records the difference through annotation.</note>, juniper-wood, and some other articles of the same nature in their boats, in order to terrify and prevent their too near approach.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:153" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Uno Von Troil’s Letters on Banks’s and Solander’s Voyage to Iceland in 1772</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The Spermacetti Whale found by the Nantuckois, is an active, fierce animal, and requires vast address and boldness in the fishermen.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:278" type="person">Thomas Jefferson</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:154" type="text">Whale Memorial to the French minister in 1778</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“And pray, sir, what in the world is equal to it?”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:279" type="person">Edmund Burke</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:155" type="text">reference in Parliament to the Nantucket Whale-Fishery</name></hi>.</p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212727586-3uz4m9d8esq-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0030.jpg"/><p>“Spain—a great whale stranded on the shores of Europe.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Edmund Burke. (somewhere.)</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“A tenth branch of the king’s ordinary revenue, said to be grounded on the consideration of his guarding and protecting the seas from pirates and robbers, is the right to royal fish, which are whale and sturgeon. And these, when either thrown ashore or caught near the coast, are the property of the king.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:156" type="text"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:280" type="person"><hi rend="italic">Blackstone</hi></name></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Soon to the sport of death the crews repair:</l>
<l rend="4em">Rodmond unerring o’er his head suspends</l>
<l rend="4em">The barbed steel, and every turn attends.”</l>
</lg>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:285" type="person">Falconer</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:158" type="text">Shipwreck</name></hi>.</p>
<lg>
<lb/>
<l rend="4em">“Bright shone the roofs, the domes, the spires,</l>
<l rend="6em">And rockets blew self driven,</l>
<l rend="4em">To hang their momentary fires</l>
<l rend="6em">Around the vault of heaven.</l>
<lb/>
<l rend="4em">“So fire with water to compare,</l>
<l rend="6em">The ocean serves on high,</l>
<l rend="4em">Up-spouted by a whale in air,</l>
<l rend="6em">To express unwieldy joy.”</l>
</lg>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:286" type="person">Cowper</name>, <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:159" type="text">on the Queen’s Visit to London</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Ten or fifteen gallons of blood are thrown out of the heart at a stroke, with immense velocity.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:287" type="person">John Hunter</name>’s account of the dissection of a whale. (A small sized one.)</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“The aorta of a whale is larger in the bore than the main pipe of the water-works at <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:857" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:32" type="place">London Bridge</name></name>, and the water roaring in its passage through that pipe is inferior in impetus and velocity to the blood gushing from the whale’s heart.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:288" type="person">Paley</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:160" type="text">Theology</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The whale is a mammiferous animal without hind feet.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Baron <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:161" type="text"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:289" type="person">Cuvier</name></name></hi>.</p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212915636-05l2jmnwou7f-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0031.jpg"/>
<p>“In 40 degrees south, we saw Spermacetti Whales, but did not take any till the first of May, the sea being then covered with them.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:935" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:290" type="person">Colnett</name></name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:162" type="text">Voyage for the Purpose of Extending the Spermacetti Whale Fishery</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“In the free element beneath me swam,</l>
<l rend="4em">Floundered and dived, in play, in chace, in battle,</l>
<l rend="4em">Fishes of every color, form, and kind;</l>
<l rend="4em">Which language cannot paint, and mariner</l>
<l rend="4em">Had never seen; from dread Leviathan</l>
<l rend="4em">To insect millions peopling every wave:</l>
<l rend="4em">Gather’d in shoals immense, like floating islands,</l>
<l rend="4em">Led by mysterious instincts through that waste</l>
<l rend="4em">And trackless region, though on every side</l>
<l rend="4em">Assaulted by voracious enemies,</l>
<l rend="4em">Whales, sharks, and monsters, arm’d in front or jaw,</l>
<l rend="4em">With swords, saws, spiral horns, or hooked fangs.”</l>
</lg>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:291" type="person">Montgomery</name>’s</hi> <ref target="#ref_19462"><hi rend="italic">World before the Flood</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19462"><ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:163">The World Before the Flood</ref>: the source is actually "<ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:164">The Pelican Island</ref>" by <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:291">James Montgomery</ref></note>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="6em">“Io! Pæan! Io! sing,</l>
<l rend="6em">To the finny people’s king.</l>
<l rend="6em">Not a mightier whale than this</l>
<l rend="6em">In the vast <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:33" type="place">Atlantic</name> is;</l>
<l rend="6em">Not a fatter fish than he,</l>
<l rend="6em">Flounders round the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:386" type="place">Polar Sea</name>."</l>
</lg>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:292" type="person">Charles Lamb</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:166" type="text">Triumph of the Whale</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“In the year 1690 some persons were on a high hill observing the whales spouting and sporting with each other, when one observed; there—pointing to the sea—is a green pasture where our children’s grand-children will go for bread.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:293" type="person">Obed Macy</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:167" type="text">History of Nantucket</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“I built a cottage for Susan and myself and made a gateway in the form of a Gothic Arch, by setting up a whale’s jaw bones.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1010" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:250" type="person">Hawthorne</name></name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:168" type="text">Twice Told Tales</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“She came to bespeak a monument for her first love, who had been killed by a whale in the Pacific ocean, no less than forty years ago.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212982802-zl18jabz7op-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0032.jpg"/><p>“No, Sir, ’tis a Right Whale,” answered Tom; “I saw his spout; he threw up a pair of as pretty rainbows as a Christian would wish to look at. He’s a raal oil-butt, that fellow!”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:294" type="person">Cooper</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:169" type="text">Pilot</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The papers were brought in, and we saw in the <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:36" type="place">Berlin</name> Gazette that whales had been introduced on the stage there.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:295" type="person">Eckermann</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:170" type="text">Conversations with Goethe</name></hi>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“My God! Mr. Chace, what is the matter?” I answered, “we have been stove by a whale.”</p>
<p>“<ref target="#MDextractsNote8"><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:171" type="text">Narrative of the Shipwreck of the Whale Ship Essex </name>of Nantucket, which was attacked and finally destroyed by a large Sperm Whale in the Pacific Ocean.” By <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:296" type="person">Owen Chace</name> of Nantucket, first mate of said vessel. New York. 1821</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote8">Owen Chace: The editors of the NN Moby-Dick correct the spelling of “Chace” to “Chase,” as it appears in Chase’s book; MEL retains the American edition’s spelling since it is a variant of the name and one Melville himself used in annotating his copy of Chase’s narrative. In the title cited for this extract, Melville has dropped “Most Extraordinary and Distressing” as adjectives for “Shipwreck” and reduced the original “Spermaceti-Whale” to “Sperm Whale.”</note></p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“A mariner sat in the shrouds one night,</l>
<l rend="6em">The wind was piping free;</l>
<l rend="4em">Now bright, now dimmed, was the moonlight pale,</l>
<l rend="4em">And the phospher gleamed in the wake of the whale,</l>
<l rend="6em">As it floundered in the sea.”</l>
</lg>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote9"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:297" type="person"><hi rend="italic">Elizabeth Oakes Smith</hi></name></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote9">Elizabeth Oakes Smith: Melville’s quotation is from Smith's poem <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:172" type="text">“The Drowned Mariner”</name> and varies from the original in two places: He has “in the shrouds” rather than “on the shrouds” and “it floundered” rather than “he floundered.” The NN edition emends “in” to “on.” MEL retains both of Melville’s alterations, in particular the nautically correct usage, “in the shrouds.”</note>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The quantity of line withdrawn from the different boats engaged in the capture of this one whale, amounted altogether to 10,440 yards or nearly six English miles.”  *  *  *</p>
<p>“Sometimes the whale shakes its tremendous tail in the air, which, cracking like a whip, resounds to the distance of three or four miles.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:303" type="person"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:966" type="artwork"><hi rend="italic">Scoresby</hi></name></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Mad with the agonies he endures from these fresh attacks, the infuriated Sperm Whale rolls over and over; he rears his enormous head, and with wide expanded jaws snaps at everything around him; he rushes at the boats with his head; they are propelled before him with vast swiftness, and sometimes utterly destroyed.</p>
<p>&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; It is a matter of great astonishment that the consideration of the habits of so interesting, and, in a commercial
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213000609-gyi6njhico5-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0033.jpg"/>point of view, of so important an animal (as the Sperm Whale) should have been so entirely neglected, or should have excited so little curiosity among the numerous, and many of them competent observers, that of late years must have possessed the most abundant and the most convenient opportunities of witnessing their habitudes.”</p>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote10"><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:955" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:304" type="person">Thomas Beale</name></name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:176" type="text">History of the Sperm Whale</name>, 1839.</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote10">Thomas Beale: Melville made minor changes to his extract from Beale: he pluralized “agony,” revised “sea beast” to “Sperm Whale,” altered “jaw” to “jaws,” added “him” to give “around him,” and inserted the parenthetical phrase “(as the Sperm Whale).” The NN edition alters “jaws” back to “jaw”; MEL retains “jaws” and all other variants.</note></p>
<lb/>
<p>“The Cachalot” (Sperm Whale) “is not only better armed than the True Whale” (Greenland or Right Whale) “in possessing a formidable weapon at either extremity of its body, but also more frequently displays a disposition to employ these weapons offensively, and in a manner at once so artful, bold, and mischievous, as to lead to its being regarded as the most dangerous to attack of all the known species of the whale tribe.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:184" type="text">Frederick Debell Bennett’s Whaling Voyage Round the Globe</name>. 1840.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>October 13. “There she blows,” was sung out from the mast-head.</p>
<p>“Where away?” demanded the captain.</p>
<p>“Three points off the lee bow, sir.”</p>
<p>“Raise up your wheel. Steady!”</p>
<p>“Steady, sir.”</p>
<p>“Mast-head ahoy! Do you see that whale now?”</p>
<p>“Ay ay, sir! A shoal of Sperm Whales! There she blows! There she breaches!”</p>
<p>“Sing out! sing out every time!”</p>
<p>“Ay ay, sir! There she blows! there—there—thar she blows—bowes—bo-o-o-s!”</p>
<p>“How far off?”</p>
<p>“Two miles and a half.”</p>
<p>“Thunder and lightning! so near! Call all hands!”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:239" type="person"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:958" type="artwork">J. Ross Browne</name></name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:115" type="text">Etchings of a Whaling Cruize</name>. 1846.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“The Whale-ship Globe, on board of which vessel occurred the horrid transactions we are about to relate, belonged to the island of Nantucket.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">“<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:185" type="text">Narrative of the Globe Mutiny</name>,” by Lay and Hussey survivors. A. D. 1828.</hi></p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213023618-35d415uv3xt-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0034.jpg"/>
<p>“Being once pursued by a whale which he had wounded, he parried the assault for some time with a lance; but the furious monster at length rushed on the boat; himself and comrades only being preserved by leaping into the water when they saw the onset was inevitable.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:186" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Missionary Journal of Tyerman and Bennet</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Nantucket itself,” said Mr. Webster, “is a very striking and peculiar portion of the National interest. There is a population of eight or nine thousand persons, living here in the sea, adding largely every year to the National wealth by the boldest and most persevering industry.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:187" type="text">Report</name> of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:375" type="person">Daniel Webster</name>’s Speech in the U. S. Senate, on the application for the Erection of a Breakwater at Nantucket. 1828.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“The whale fell directly over him, and probably killed him in a moment.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">“<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:175" type="text">The Whale and his Captors</name>, or The Whaleman’s Adventures and the Whale’s Biography, gathered on the Homeward Cruise of the Commodore Preble.” By <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:175" type="person">Rev. Henry T. Cheever</name>.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“If you make the least damn bit of noise,” replied Samuel, “I will send you to hell.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:188" type="text">Life of Samuel Comstock</name> (the mutineer), by his brother, William Comstock. Another Version of the whale-ship Globe narrative.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“The voyages of the Dutch and English to the Northern Ocean, in order, if possible, to discover a passage through it to India, though they failed of their main object, laid open the haunts of the whale.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">McCulloch’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:189" type="text">Commercial Dictionary</name>.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“These things are reciprocal; the ball rebounds, only to bound forward again; for now in laying open the haunts of the whale, the whalemen seem to have indirectly hit upon new clews to that same mystic North-West Passage.”</p>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote11"><hi rend="italic">From “Something” unpublished</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote11">Most certainly a bit of writing cut from Moby-Dick.</note></p>
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213068273-2fja0fancys-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0035.jpg"/><p>“It is impossible to meet a whale-ship on the ocean without being struck by her mere appearance. The vessel under short sail, with look-outs at the mast-heads, eagerly scanning the wide expanse around them, has a totally different air from those engaged in a regular voyage.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Currents and Whaling. <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:190" type="text">U. S. Ex. Ex</name>.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“Pedestrians in the vicinity of <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/place:32" type="place">London</name> and elsewhere may recollect having seen large curved bones set upright in the earth, either to form arches over gateways, or entrances to alcoves, and they may perhaps have been told that these were the ribs of whales.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:191" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Tales of a Whale Voyager to the Arctic Ocean</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“It was not till the boats returned from the pursuit of these whales, that the whites saw their ship in bloody possession of the savages enrolled among the crew.”</p>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote12"><hi rend="italic">Newspaper Account of the Taking and Retaking of the Whale-ship Hobomack</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote12">Newspaper Account: In using the word “Hobomack” (with an “a”) to identify the whaler Hobomok (with an “o”) as the scene of maritime violence, Melville perpetuates an error he initiated in his first book, Typee, where he refers to the “Hobomak” (with an “a”). In fact, no mutiny or massacre occurred on the Hobomok. This extract, then, is something of an invention, although Melville had surely read newspaper accounts of massacres on other ships in the South Pacific. The NN edition emends the American and British editions’ spelling of “Hobomack” to “Hobomock” to bring the word closer to the ship’s name, Hobomok; however, MEL retains Melville’s original “Hobomack.”</note>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“It is generally well known that out of the crews of Whaling vessels (American) few ever return in the ships on board of which they departed.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:192" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Cruise in a Whale Boat</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“Suddenly a mighty mass emerged from the water, and shot up perpendicularly into the air. It was the whale.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:177" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Miriam Coffin or the Whale Fisherman</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“The Whale is harpooned to be sure; but bethink you, how you would manage a powerful unbroken colt, with the mere appliance of a rope tied to the root of his tail.”</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:181" type="text"><hi rend="italic">A Chapter on Whaling in Ribs and Trucks</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<p>“On one occasion I saw two of these monsters (whales) probably male and female, slowly swimming, one after the other, within less than a stone’s throw of the shore” (<ref target="#MDextractsNote13">Tierra</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote13">Tierra: In the American and British editions, Melville’s parenthetical insertion of “(Terra Del Fuego)” gives the Portuguese “Terra” instead of the proper Spanish, “Tierra.” Since Melville’s 1846 edition of Darwin’s classic voyage of the Beagle spells the word properly, the word “Terra” is probably a typo, and MEL corrects to “Tierra.”</note> Del Fuego), “over which the beech tree extended its branches.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:305" type="person">Darwin</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:193" type="text">Voyage of a Naturalist</name>.</hi></p>
<lb/>
<p>“‘Stern all!’ exclaimed the mate, as upon turning his head, he saw the distended jaws of a large Sperm Whale close to the
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213089747-6b70fik7kle-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0036.jpg"/> head of the boat, threatening it with instant destruction;—‘Stern all, for your lives!”’</p>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:194" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Wharton the Whale Killer</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“So be cheery, my lads, let your hearts never fail,</l>
<l rend="4em">While the bold harpooneer is striking the whale!”</l>
</lg>
<p><ref target="#MDextractsNote14"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:195" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Nantucket Song</hi></name></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote14">These lines seem to be a conflation of two renderings of a song quoted twice in different versions in Browne’s Etchings. (See Frank, “Two Songs,” MSEx 63: 4-7.)</note>.</p>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Oh, the rare old Whale, mid storm and gale</l>
<l rend="6em">In his ocean home will be</l>
<l rend="4em">A giant in might, where might is right,</l>
<l rend="6em">And King of the boundless sea.”</l>
</lg>
<p><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:196" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Whale Song</hi></name>.</p>

</body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
