<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>Extracts</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body>
			<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212165223-4ni9kaqxt4n-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0023.jpg"/>
			<head type="main" rend="center">EXTRACTS.</head>
			<lb/>
<head type="sub-head" rend="center">(<hi rend="smalcaps"><hi rend="bold">Supplied by a Sub-Sub-Librarian</hi></hi>.)</head>

<p>It will be seen that this mere painstaking burrower and grub-worm of a poor devil of a Sub-Sub appears to have gone through the long <ref target="#ref_19454">Vaticans</ref><note xml:id="ref_19454">Vaticans: great libraries, such as the Vatican's in Vatican City</note> and street-stalls of the earth, picking up whatever random allusions to whales he could anyways find in any book whatsoever, sacred or profane. Therefore you must not, in every case at least, take the higgledy-piggledy whale statements, however authentic, in these extracts, for veritable gospel cetology. Far from it. As touching the ancient authors generally, as well as the poets here appearing, these extracts are solely valuable or entertaining, as affording a glancing bird’s eye view of what has been <ref target="#ref_19455">promiscuously</ref><note xml:id="ref_19455">promiscuously: diversely; unsystematically. </note> said, thought, fancied, and sung of <ref target="#ref_19456">Leviathan</ref><note xml:id="ref_19456">Leviathan: biblical sea creature, not necessarily a whale. Throughout "Extracts," Melville consistently capitalizes "Leviathan," even though the word appears in his source, the King James Bible, only in lower-case. In the rest of his novel, Melville uses the word 109 times (in 37 chapters), capitalizing it only 58% of the time. Both upper and lower-case spellings appear in ten of the 37 chapters. The British edition of <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> shows no evidence of regularizing the spelling.</note>, by many nations and generations, including our own.</p>
<p>So fare thee well, poor devil of a Sub-Sub, whose commentator I am. Thou belongest to that hopeless, sallow tribe which no wine of this world will ever warm; and for whom even Pale Sherry would be too rosy-strong; but with whom one sometimes loves to sit, and feel poor-devilish, too; and grow convivial upon tears; and say to them bluntly, with full eyes and empty glasses, and in not altogether unpleasant sadness—Give it up, Sub-Subs! For by how much the more pains ye take to please the world, by so much the more shall ye for ever go thankless! Would that I could clear out <ref target="#ref_19457">Hampton Court and the Tuileries</ref><note xml:id="ref_19457"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:1008" type="artwork">Hampton Court</name> and the Tuileries: royal residences in London and Paris.</note> for ye! But gulp down your tears and hie aloft to the <ref target="#ref_19458">royal-mast</ref><note xml:id="ref_19458">royal-mast: highest part of the mast.</note> with your hearts; for your friends who have gone before are clearing out the <ref target="#ref_19459">seven-storied heavens</ref><note xml:id="ref_19459">seven-storied heavens: in Jewish and Islamic traditions, Heaven has seven levels.</note>, and making refugees of long-pampered
<ref target="#ref_20840">Gabriel, Michael, and Raphael, against your coming</ref><note xml:id="ref_20840">Gabriel, <ref type="reference" target="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:143">Michael</ref>, and Raphael, against your coming: three principal archangels. Here, "against" means preparing for.</note>. Here ye strike but splintered hearts together—there, ye shall strike unsplinterable glasses!</p>
<lb/>
<p rend="center"><ref target="#MDextractsNote1">E X T R A C T S</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote1">Extracts: Melville assembled this collection of quotations from works he consulted while writing <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>. The British edition places both “Etymology” and “Extracts” as an appendix at the end of <hi rend="italic">The Whale</hi>; it also omits the epilogue (in which Ishmael tells of his survival).
One explanation for the placement of these two sections as an appendix is that Melville sent these pages to England some time after sending the the bulk of the novel's text, and after the British printer had already set the opening pages. Scholars also speculate that the epilogue may have been inadvertently dropped when “Etymology” and “Extracts” were appended (see NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>, 677–80). According to NN editor G. Thomas Tanselle, Melville fashioned “Extracts” by borrowing directly from sources, but also indirectly by quoting source quotations as they appeared in other books, in particular Beale’s <hi rend="italic">Natural History of the Sperm Whale</hi>, J. Ross Browne’s <hi rend="italic">Etchings of a Whaling Cruise</hi>, John Harris’s <hi rend="italic">Compleat Collection of Voyages and Travels</hi>, and Charles Richardson’s <hi rend="italic">New Dictionary of the English Language</hi> (NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>, 813–30).
<lb/>
<lb/>
The wordings of some extracts vary from their original sources, either due to errors in transcription or because Melville revised them intentionally. MEL's reading text retains such source variants, marking them in bold and correcting only those that if left unemended might confuse readers. All variants—i.e. Melville's putative errors and revisions—are discussed where they occur in MEL's "Extracts" annotations, which draw upon, update, and augment source scholarship found in the NN explanatory notes.</note>.</p> <pb facs="/images/md-american/MD_Amer_0024.jpg"/>

<p rend="center">“And God created great whales.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote18"><hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote18"><hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi>: First book of the Hebrew Bible, recounting the creation, the temptation of Adam and Eve, Cain's murder of Abel, and the flood. See Genesis 1:21.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p rend="center">“<ref target="#MDextractsNote2"><hi rend="bold">Leviathan</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote2">REVISION NARRATIVE: Leviathan maketh // Comparing his power to Leviathan, the Lord concludes, “He maketh a path to shine after him” (Job 41:32). Melville revises "He" to "Leviathan."</note> maketh a path to shine after him;  One would think the deep to be hoary.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote17"><hi rend="italic">Job</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote17"><hi rend="italic">Job</hi>: In this book of the Hebrew Bible, Satan claims that Job, without his wealth, would reject God, and God afflicts Job to test his faith.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Now the Lord had prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote19"><hi rend="italic">Jonah</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote19"><hi rend="italic">Jonah</hi>: In the book of Jonah (1:17) in the Hebrew Bible, the prophet Jonah takes to the sea to avoid delivering God's awful message of destruction to the Ninevites. God has a "great fish" swallow Jonah and later vomit him back onto land. See also "The Sermon" (Ch. 9). </note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“There go the ships; there is that Leviathan whom thou hast made to play therein.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote20"><hi rend="italic">Psalms</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote20"><hi rend="italic">Psalms</hi>: A collection of 150 songs of praise in the Hebrew Bible. See Psalm 104:26. See also Extract 13, "Lord Bacon's Version of the Psalms," below.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“In that day, the Lord with his sore, and great, and strong sword, shall punish Leviathan the piercing serpent, even Leviathan that crooked serpent; and he shall slay the dragon that is in the sea.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote21"><hi rend="italic">Isaiah</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote21"><hi rend="italic">Isaiah</hi>: Prophetic book in the Hebrew Bible; the extract is from Isaiah 27:1.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“And what thing soever besides cometh within the chaos of this monster’s mouth, be it beast, boat, or stone, down it goes all incontinently that foul great swallow of his, and perisheth in the bottomless gulf of his paunch.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote15"><hi rend="italic">Holland’s Plutarch’s Morals</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote15"><hi rend="italic">Holland’s Plutarch’s Morals</hi>: Philemon Holland (1532-1637) was the prolific British translator of Greek and Latin classics. The Greek biographer, historian, and essayist Plutarch (49-119 CE) wrote a compendium of reflections on Greek and Roman life and manners titled <hi rend="italic">Moralia</hi> (ca. 100 CE). Holland published his English translation of Plutarch’s <hi rend="italic">Morals</hi> in 1603.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The Indian Sea breedeth the most and the biggest fishes that are: among which the Whales and Whirlpooles called Balæne, take up as much in length as four acres or arpens of land.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote16"><hi rend="italic">Holland’s Pliny</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote16"><hi rend="italic">Holland’s Pliny</hi>: For Holland, see above. Roman naturalist Pliny the Elder (23-79 CE) published his <hi rend="italic">Naturalis Historia</hi> in 77 CE. Holland’s English translation, titled <hi rend="italic">The Historie of the World</hi>, but known as <hi rend="italic">The Natural History of Pliny</hi>, appeared in 1601.
	See <ref target="http://penelope.uchicago.edu/holland/index.html" type="reference">http://penelope.uchicago.edu/holland/index.html</ref>.</note>.</p>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212264819-7f1uaiiaapt-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0025.jpg"/>

<p>“Scarcely had we proceeded two days on the sea, when about sunrise a great many Whales and other <ref target="#MDextractsNote3">monsters of the <hi rend="bold">sea</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote3">REVISION NARRATIVE: monsters of the <hi rend="bold">sea</hi> // Tooke's original wording, “monsters of the deep,” is changed in the American version, and probably by Melville, to “monsters of the sea."</note>, appeared. Among the former, one was of
<ref target="#MDextractsNote22">a most <hi rend="bold">monstrous</hi> size</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote22">REVISION NARRATIVE: a most <hi rend="bold">monstrous</hi> size // Tooke's original “enormous size” appears here as “monstrous size.” The change may be the result of a printer's "eye-skip"; that is, he confused the original "enormous" with "monsters" in the line directly above and came up with "monstrous." Or, Melville may have made the change, which underscores monstrosity in the extract.</note>.   *   *   This came towards us, open-mouthed, raising the waves on all sides, and beating the sea before him into a foam.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote23"><hi rend="italic">Tooke’s Lucian</hi></ref>.</l>
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote23"><hi rend="italic">Tooke’s Lucian</hi>: Cleric, historian, and writer William Tooke (1744-1820) translated the works of Greek satirist Lucian in his two-volume <hi rend="italic">Lucian of Samosata</hi> in 1820. Lucian (125-ca. 180 CE) composed highly-popular prose fantasies and mock dialogues lampooning society and philosophers.</note>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote24">"<hi rend="italic">The True History</hi>.”</ref></l><note xml:id="MDextractsNote24"><hi rend="italic">The True History</hi>: Tooke calls Lucian's fantastical two-part series of tall tales "the prototype of all the <hi rend="italic">Voyages Imaginaires</hi>" (2.79n), such as <hi rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels</hi> and Munchausen's tales. The extract is taken from an episode in which the narrator is swallowed by a 300-mile long whale whose belly holds a forested and populated island.</note>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“He visited this country also with a view of catching horse-whales, which had bones of very great value for their teeth, of which he brought some to the king.   *   *   *   The best whales were catched in his own country, of which some were forty-eight, some fifty yards long. He said that he was one of six who had killed sixty in two days.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#ref_19502"><hi rend="italic">Other or Octher’s verbal narrative taken down</hi></ref></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#ref_19502"><hi rend="italic">from his mouth by King Alfred. A. D. 890.</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19502"><hi rend="italic">Other or Octher</hi>: This Norwegian chieftain (more commonly known as Ohthere or Ottar) presented a “verbal narrative” of his travels to English King Alfred (849-899), who commissioned an Anglo-Saxon translation, which appeared in Haklyut’s compendium. However, Melville found this passage in J. Ross Browne's <hi rend="italic">Etchings of a Whaling Cruise</hi>.</note></l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“And whereas all the other things, whether beast or vessel, that enter into the dreadful gulf of this monster’s (whale’s) mouth, are immediately lost and swallowed up, the sea-gudgeon retires into it in great security, and there sleeps.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote30"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Montaigne</hi>.<hi rend="italic">—Apology for Raimond Sebond.</hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote30"><hi rend="smallcaps">Montaigne</hi>.<hi rend="italic">—Apology for Raimond Sebond.</hi>: Michel de Montaigne (1533-1592), French philosopher and author of <hi rend="italic">Essais</hi> (1580). In “Apology for Raymond Sebond”—considered his finest essay—Montaigne defends Christian skepticism. Melville made only routine modifications to clarify this passage, which he took from Hazlitt’s 1842 edition of Montaigne's writings. He added the parenthetical “(whale’s)” after “monster’s” and replaced “this little fish” with its antecedent “the sea-gudgeon.” He also added “And” at the beginning.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“Let us fly, let us fly! Old Nick take me if it is not Leviathan described by the noble prophet Moses in the life of patient Job.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote31"><hi rend="italic">Rabelais</hi>.</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote31"><hi rend="italic">Rabelais</hi>: François Rabelais (ca. 1490-1553) was a French monk, scholar, and physician. The passage is from Book 4, Ch. 33 of <hi rend="italic">Gargantua and Pantagruel</hi> (originally in 4 vols., 1532-1552), an erudite, satrirical, vulgar, often grotesque work ranging from philosophical novel to epic parody.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“This whale’s liver was two cart-loads.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote32"><hi rend="italic">Stowe’s Annals</hi>.</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote32"><hi rend="italic">Stowe’s Annals</hi>: John Stow(e) (1525-1605) wrote <hi rend="italic">The Chronicles</hi> [later <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi>] <hi rend="italic">of England from Brute unto this Present Yeare of Christ. 1580</hi>. Melville based this extract on information in Stow’s entry for 9 July 1574.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The great Leviathan that maketh the seas to seethe like boiling pan.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote33"><hi rend="italic">Lord Bacon’s Version of the Psalms</hi>.</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote33"><hi rend="italic">Lord Bacon’s Version of the Psalms</hi>: Philosopher and scientist Francis Bacon (Lord Verulam, 1561-1626). The extract is from lines 91-92 of Psalm 104 in his 1625 <hi rend="italic">Translation of Certaine Psalmes into English Verse</hi>. Melville calls Bacon’s slim collection of six psalms a “Version of the  Psalms," and, indeed, Bacon’s 60 couplets for Psalm 104 are an adaptive revision of the King James Version’s 35 lines. The lines selected from Bacon, which stress the whale’s fury, are the same reprinted from the biblical version that depicts the whale at "play" in the fourth Extract, above.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“Touching that monstrous bulk of the whale or ork we have received nothing certain. They grow exceeding fat, insomuch that an incredible quantity of oil will be extracted out of one whale.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>. "<ref target="#MDextractsNote34"><hi rend="italic">History of Life and Death</hi></ref>."<note xml:id="MDextractsNote34"><hi rend="italic">Ibid. History of Life and Death</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> is the standard but now rarely used Latin abbreviation in bibliography for "ibidem," which refers the reader to the previously cited source, but in this case, Melville means only the author, Bacon. The source cited here, <hi rend="italic">History Naturall and Experimentall of Life and Death</hi> (1638), originally appeared as <hi rend="italic">Historia Vitae et Mortis</hi>. The two sentences in the extract are drawn from items 48 and 41, respectively, in Topic 3, featuring the life expectancy  of animals.</note></p>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212298194-mvlh3z265xg-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0026.jpg"/>
<p>“The sovereignest thing on earth <ref target="#MDextractsNote27"><hi rend="bold">is</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote27">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">is</hi> // In Shakespeare’s <hi rend="italic">Henry IV, Part 1</hi>, Hotspur complains to Henry of a perfumed and dandified “lord,” who has spoken to him indifferently of the dead on the battlefield, and who has advised him on how to dress a deep wound, saying “the sovereignest thing on Earth / Was parmacety for an inward bruise” (Act 1, Sc. 3, ll. 59-60). Melville’s revision of “Was” to “is” in his extract universalizes the remedy. The lord also appears, in Hotspur’s words, as “Fresh as a bridegroom,” a description echoed in Melville’s treatment of newly-washed whalemen, “fresh and all aglow, as bridegrooms” in “Stowing Down and Clearing Up” (Ch. 98).</note> parmacetti for an inward bruise.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote35"><hi rend="italic">King Henry</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote35"><hi rend="italic">King Henry</hi>: Henry the Fourth, Part 1, by William Shakespeare (1564-1616), was written in 1596.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Very like a whale.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote28"><hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote28"><hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi>: In Shakespeare's tragedy, written in 1599 or 1600, Polonius contemplates a cloud to humor the prince, in Act 3, Sc. 2, l. 382.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Which to <hi rend="bold">secure</hi>, no skill of leach’s art</l>
<l rend="4em">Mote him availle, but to returne againe</l>
<l rend="4em">To his wound’s worker, that with <hi rend="bold">lowly</hi> dart,</l>
<l rend="4em">Dinting his breast, had bred his restless paine,</l>
<l rend="4em">Like as the wounded whale to shore flies <hi rend="bold">thro’</hi> the maine.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote29"><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">The Fairie Queen</hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote29">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">The Fairie Queen</hi></hi> // In Book VI of the 1590 allegorical epic,<hi rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</hi>, by Edmund Spenser (1552/53-1599), Sir Calidore feels the pain of his love for Pastorella, which like a stinging dart cannot be cured unless he returns to her, like a wounded whale beaching itself. In Melville’s extract, taken from Canto 10, stanza 31, three key words have been changed. Spenser’s original “Which to recure” (meaning to remedy or restore) appears as “Which to secure”; “lovely dart” (like Cupid’s love arrows) becomes “lowly dart,” and “from the maine” (or sea) becomes “thro’ the maine.” The editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> (818) “correct” these changes to reflect Spenser’s original, as reprinted in Melville’s actual source, the article on "Whale" in Richardson’s <hi rend="italic">New Dictionary</hi>. But since the variants are not indisputable errors or confusing, MEL retains them, noting here their problematic status as either misquotation or revision.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Immense as whales, the motion of whose vast bodies can in a peaceful calm trouble the ocean till it boil.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote37"><hi rend="italic">Sir William Davenant. Preface to Gondibert.</hi></ref>
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote37"><hi rend="italic">Sir William Davenant. Preface to Gondibert</hi>: Playwright and poet laureate William D’Avenant (1606-1668), wrote the epic poem <hi rend="italic">Gondibert</hi> (1651), which, in four-line stanzas, depicts the complicated loves of two privileged couples in Britain and France. Melville draws his extract from the poem’s prose Preface, which explains D'Avenant's poetics in combining epic and dramatic forms (analogous to Melville's attempts in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>) and discusses the politics of the English Civil War. (The Preface is dedicated to D’Avenant’s “Honour’d Friend Mr. Hobs,” the political philosopher Thomas Hobbes, whose treatise <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> is also extracted below.) Melville’s accurate quotation is taken out of context from D’Avenant’s more particularized observation regarding military leaders’ envious but disapproving view of statesmen as “immense as <hi rend="italic">Whales</hi>.” Melville marked this line with a marginal check in his copy of <hi rend="italic">The Works of Sr William D’Avenant Kt</hi> (1673), which he procured during his 1849 trip to London and read during his 1850 passage home. The volume’s marginalia also suggest Melville returned to D’Avenant as he composed  <hi rend="italic">Clarel</hi>, his own epic poem of 1876. See Steven Olsen-Smith and Dennis Marnon, “Melville’s Marginalia in The Works of Sir William D’Avenant: A Transcription. <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> 6.1 (March 2004): 79-102. See also MMO.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“What spermacetti is, men might justly doubt, since the learned Hofmannus in his work of thirty years, saith plainly, Nescio quid sit.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote38"><hi rend="italic">Sir T. Browne. Of Sperma Ceti and the</hi></ref>
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote38"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:112" type="person">Sir Thomas Browne</name> (1605-1682), writer on science, medicine, religion, and esoterica, is mentioned by name in "Cetology" (Ch. 32) and quoted in the epigraph to "The Pequod meets the Rose-Bud" (Ch. 91). Browne’s <hi rend="italic">Pseudodoxia Epidemica</hi>, addressing false beliefs, was better-known as <hi rend="italic">Vulgar Errors</hi>; hence, Melville’s “Vide” citation  “V. E.” (See <ref target=" https://penelope.uchicago.edu/pseudodoxia/pseudo326.html#note1" type="reference"> https://penelope.uchicago.edu/pseudodoxia/pseudo326.html#note1</ref>.) In Melville’s extract, from Book 3, Ch. 26, Browne draws upon the work of the “learned Hofmannus,” or German physician Caspar Hofmann (1572-1648), whose Latin statement means “I do not know what it is.” Both Browne and Hofmann seem to doubt the folk belief that spermaceti, the oil from the sperm whale's head, is semen or what Browne calls "seminal humor" and Ishmael calls “quickening humor” in "Cetology" (Ch. 32). Evidently, Melville misread “Hofmannus” as “Hosmannus,” and the error, appearing in both American and British editions, has been corrected in NN, Longman, and MEL.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Like writers of the Romantic period, in particular Charles Lamb, Melville was drawn to Browne for his style, rationalism, and metaphysics. In February 1848, he borrowed a copy of the 1836 Wilkin edition of Sir Thomas Browne’s Works (Sealts 89) from Evert Duyckinck, and his reading of Browne is evident in the 1849 <hi rend="italic">Mardi</hi> (Foley 266-270). During his visit to London the following year, he purchased a 1686 folio edition of the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (Sealts 90) for his own library. Melville's "Hosmannus" error suggests he quoted from his own older edition rather than a modernized source because in seventeenth-century typography the letter "f" and the "long-s" are easily confused. For further instances of Browne’s influence, see extract from Thomas Edge, below, and the note on “Trumpa whale” in Ch. 32.</note></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote38"><hi rend="italic">Sperma Ceti Whale. Vide his V. E.</hi></ref></l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Like Spencer’s Talus with his <ref target="#MDextractsNote25"><hi rend="bold">modern flail</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote25">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">modern flail</hi> // Waller's original wording, "iron flail,” based on Spenser’s “yron flale” in Book 5 of <hi rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</hi> (see Waller’s Battle, below), appears as "modern flail” in both the American and British editions. Taking this change to be a printer’s error, the editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> emend their reading text to Waller’s original “iron flail.” However, the implied modernity of iron in Melville’s altered phrasing has a certain historical logic. As an ancient agricultural tool, the flail—a wooden pole with a smaller wooden slat dangling at one end—was used in threshing grain. However, by the sixteenth century, peasants had adapted the wooden tool for combat by substituting an iron bar for the loose wooden slat. Arguably, Talus’s “yron flale” was a powerful modern contrivance. Melville describes the “violent flailing” and “terrible flailings” of the whale’s tail, in Chs. 87 and 100, respectively, and contemplates its power to annihilate in “The Tail” (Ch. 86). Since “modern” is unlikely to be an error, MEL retains “modern flail."</note></l>
<l rend="4em">He threatens ruin with his ponderous tail.</l>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;*</l>
<l rend="4em">Their fixed jav’lins in <ref target="#MDextractsNote26"><hi rend="bold">his</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote26">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">his</hi> // In quoting, from Edmund Waller's "Battle of the Summer Islands," Melville brought two widely separated couplets together, separated them with a line of asterisks, and altered “her” twice in the second couplet to “his” to make the possessive pronouns here and in the last line agree in gender with those in the first couplet. See also "modern flail," above.</note> side he wears,</l>
<l rend="4em">And on <hi rend="bold">his</hi> back a grove of pikes appears.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote4"><hi rend="italic">Waller’s Battle of the Summer Islands</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote4"><hi rend="italic">Waller’s Battle of the Summer Islands</hi>: Edmund Waller (1606-1687), English poet and sometime royalist, sometime republican during the English Civil War, wrote this mock-heroic poem of 1645 about islanders battling over stranded whales in the Bermudas. In describing the power of the whale’s tail, Waller has borrowed from Edmund Spenser’s iron-clad and iron-like Talus, who metes out terrible justice against sinners in Book 5 of <hi rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</hi>, with his “yron flale” (Canto 1, stanza 12, ll. 8-9). Waller’s original wording, “iron flail,” updates Spenser’s spelling. The change to “modern flail” in Melville’s extract may be a revision as well; see “modern flail,” above.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“By art is created that great Leviathan, called a Commonwealth or State—(in Latin, Civitas) which is but an artificial man.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote39"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="italic">Opening sentence of Hobbes’s Leviathan</hi></hi></ref>.
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote39"><hi rend="italic">Opening sentence of Hobbes’s Leviathan</hi>: In his <hi rend="italic">Leviathan or The Matter, Forme and Power of a Commonwealth Ecclesiasticall and Civil</hi> (1651), Thomas Hobbes (1588-1679), English philosopher and prolific author on many subjects, argues that a monarch’s governmental authority derives from a “social contract” with the people. His title is derived from “leviathan” in the Book of Job (41:33). Melville’s extract—taken from Hobbes’s opening paragraph (not its first sentence)—asserts that just as God governs life through Nature, so do humans, who manufacture “Automata” such as engines and watches, create commonwealths to govern themselves. Melville echoes Hobbes’s “artificial man” in Ahab’s “constitutional condition of the manufactured man” (Ch. 47) and in his “order” that the carpenter, no mere “automaton,” make a “complete man” (Chs. 107, 108). Hobbes also wrote a reply to his friend William D’Avenant’s Preface to <hi rend="italic">Gondibert</hi> (see above).</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“Silly Mansoul swallowed it without chewing, as if it had been a sprat in the mouth of a whale.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#ref_19461"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19461">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> // As it appears in the American version, the source of this extract is not John Bunyan’s 1678 Christian allegory, <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, but, in fact, Bunyan’s 1682 <hi rend="italic">The Holy War</hi>. Melville may have corrected the attribution when he sent the additional set of "Etymology" and "Extracts" pages to England. Or a British copy-editor may have corrected the mistake for the British version. The editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> emend the attribution to "<hi rend="italic">Holy War</hi>"; however, in keeping with its policy of not correcting Melville’s errors of fact, MEL retains <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, calling attention to the error through this revision annotation. To compare American and British pages, click the thumbnails in the right margin.
<lb/>
<lb/>
This misattribution aside, Melville borrowed his extract not directly from Bunyan but as he found it quoted in Henry T. Cheever’s 1849 <hi rend="italic">The Whale and His Captors</hi>. In Bunyan’s <hi rend="italic">Holy War</hi>, the town of Mansoul (soul of man) has been seized by Diabolus (the devil), and its too-compliant citizens have adopted a loyalty oath without hesitation, as if they were a whale swallowing a “sprat,” or tiny fish. In his description of the right whale’s method of feeding on tiny fish, Cheever paraphrases Bunyan and adds two direct quotes, though he reverses Bunyan’s original order, which is “as if it had been a sprat in the mouth of a whale, they swallowed it without any chewing.” Melville’s extract removes Cheever’s paraphrase but retains his reverse-order quotation.</note>.
<pb facs="/images/md-british-v3/MD_Brit_v3_0330.jpg"/>
</p>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212353470-hm13lzp9cor-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0027.jpg"/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;“That sea beast</l>
<l rend="4em">Leviathan, which God of all his works</l>
<l rend="4em">Created hugest that swim the ocean stream.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote40"><hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote40"><hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>: Book I, lines 200-202 of the Christian epic by John Milton (1608-1674). Melville’s source may have been Cheever’s fuller quotation (p. 52) from Milton.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;—— “There Leviathan,</l>
<l rend="4em">Hugest of living creatures, <hi rend="bold">in</hi> the deep</l>
<l rend="4em">Stretched like a promontory sleeps or swims,</l>
<l rend="4em">And seems a moving land; and at his gills</l>
<l rend="4em">Draws in, and at his <hi rend="bold">breath</hi> spouts out a sea.”</l>
	</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote5"><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote5">REVISION NARRATIVE: Extract and Epigraph // In this second Extract from <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> (Book VII, ll. 412–16), Melville revised Milton. He gives “<hi rend="bold">in</hi> the deep” instead of Milton’s original "<hi rend="bold">on</hi> the deep” (although this may be a typo) and “his <hi rend="bold">breath</hi> spouts out a sea” instead of Milton’s “his <hi rend="bold">trunk</hi> spouts out a sea.” Both changes, neither one corrected by British editors, reflect Melville’s scorn (addressed in Ch. 55) for erroneous renderings of whales, which, of course, do not have “trunks” nor sleep “on” the deep. The editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> return Melville's wording to Milton's original; however, MEL retains the changes as an instance of Melville's adaptive revision of Milton. In addition, Melville’s British editor used Melville’s modified passage as an epigraph appearing on the title page of each of the British edition’s three volumes. (The American edition has no epigraph.) To view Melville’s revised Miltonic passage as both Extract and Epigraph, click the thumbnails in the right margin.</note>. <pb facs="/images/md-british-v1/MD_Brit_v1_0012.jpg"/>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The mighty whales which swim in a sea of water, and have a sea of oil swimming in them.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote41"><hi rend="italic">Fuller’s Profane and Holy State</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote41"><hi rend="italic">Fuller’s Profane and Holy State</hi>: <hi rend="italic">The Holy State, and the Profane State</hi> (1642, 1648, 1652, 1663) was a popular collection of character sketches and short biographies of historical figures, by English clergyman, sermonizer, and historian Thomas Fuller (1608-1661).
Melville’s extract is taken from Book 2, Ch. 21, which paints an optimistic portrait of “The good Sea-Captain” type, who like all sailors, Fuller implies, is necessarily mindful of God’s gifts. Melville had already extracted an epigraph from this chapter for his 1850 <hi rend="italic">White-Jacket</hi>, a sentence that urges us to “conceive” of a well-appointed captain of a man-of-war and “see how he acquits himself.” In light of Melville’s sea narratives, none of the captains he served under acquitted themselves well, and the epigraph is particularly ironic in <hi rend="italic">White-Jacket</hi>. The wording for the Fuller extract in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> is from James Nichols’s modernized edition of 1841, which Melville borrowed in April 1849 from Evert Duyckinck (Sealts 221). Nichols emended Fuller’s original text to follow the more accessible, regularized grammar and “orthography” of the London edition of 1663 (p. xiii); in doing so, Nichols also altered Fuller’s original “whales who swim” to the “whales which swim” phrasing that Melville quotes.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="2em">“So close behind some promontory lie</l>
<l rend="4em">The huge Leviathans to attend their prey,</l>
<l rend="2em">And give no chace, but swallow in the fry,</l>
<l rend="4em">Which through their gaping jaws mistake the way.”</l>
</lg>
</p>

<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote42"><hi rend="italic">Dryden’s Annus Mirabilis</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote42"><hi rend="italic">Dryden’s Annus Mirabilis</hi>: John Dryden (1631-1700), England’s first Poet Laureate, was the pre-eminent poet and literary critic of his time. His poem <hi rend="italic">Annus Mirabilis, The Year of Wonders, 1666</hi> commemorates English naval victories and the Great Fire of London, all occurring in 1666. Dryden adopted the four-line stanza from D’Avenant’s <hi rend="italic">Gondibert</hi> (cited above). Melville’s extract, stanza 203, imagines the English fleet devouring their foes, like whales feeding on “fry” or new-born fish. For a similar image, see the extract erroneously cited as “Pilgrim’s Progress,” above.  Melville quotes accurately from an unidentified edition, similar to the 1854 Routledge edition that he gave to Sarah Morewood (Sealts 191), which modernizes Dryden’s spelling and uses “to attend” instead of Dryden’s metrically correct elision “t’attend.”</note></p>

<lb/>

<p>“While the whale is floating at the stern of the ship, they cut off his head, and tow it with a boat as near the shore as it will come; but it will be aground in twelve or thirteen <hi rend="bold">foot</hi> water.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote43"><hi rend="italic">Thomas Edge’s Ten Voyages to Spitzbergen, in Purchass</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote43"><hi rend="italic">Thomas Edge’s Ten Voyages to Spitzbergen, in Purchass</hi>: Edge (1587/88-1624) was an English merchant, sealer, and whaler, whose narrative first appeared in Samuel Purchas’s collection of voyages, <hi rend="italic">Purchas His Pilgrimes</hi> (1625).  However, the wording of Melville’s extract more precisely matches Edge’s text as reprinted in John Harris’s 1705 collection of travel narratives (see Herbert extract, below). Some typographical patterns in Melville’s extract—his spelling of “aground” as one word and use of words not numbers for 12 and 13—suggest that he consulted both sources. One irregularity is that both American and British versions of the extract give “feet water” instead of the Purchas and Harris wording, “foot water.” Because “feet” may be a typo, and would appear incorrect if left to stand, the NN edition emends to “foot,” as do Longman and MEL.
<lb/>
<lb/>
Melville made his first acquaintance with Thomas Edge in Thomas Browne’s chapter on “Sperma-Ceti” in <hi rend="italic">Vulgar Errors</hi>, extracted above, though the evidence appears later in “Cetology” (Ch. 32). In that chapter, Ishmael reports that the sperm whale is “among the English of old vaguely known as the Trumpa whale.” By “English of old,” Melville is referring to old Thomas Browne, who identifies the sperm whale as “the Trumpa . . . according to the account of our <hi rend="italic">Greenland</hi> describers in <hi rend="italic">Purchas</hi>” [meaning the even older Thomas Edge]. Using the index to Harris’s collection to find all references to “whale” (Gretchko 309), Melville found “Trumpa,” which enabled him to identify Thomas Edge as one of Browne’s “Greenland describers in Purchas” and thereby quote Edge in this extract and later refer to him as an Englishman “of old” in Ch. 32. For Melville’s further use of Browne and Edge in his cetological research, see “Trumpa whale” in Ch. 32.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“In their way they saw many whales sporting in the ocean, and in wantonness fuzzing up the water through their pipes and vents, which nature has placed on their shoulders.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote44"><hi rend="italic">Sir T. Herbert’s Voyages into Asia and Africa</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote44"><hi rend="italic">Sir T. Herbert’s Voyages into Asia and Africa. Harris Coll.</hi>: Sir Thomas Herbert recorded his travels as England’s ambassador to Persia in <hi rend="italic">Some Yeares Travels into Divers Parts of Asia and Afrique</hi> (1638); however, Melville drew this precisely quoted extract from Harris’s differently worded version. John Harris (1666-1719)—clergyman, scientist, historian, and member of the Royal Society—assembled in 1705 his two-volume “compleat collection” of over 600 travel narratives—titled <hi rend="italic">Navigantium atque Itinerantium Bibliotheca</hi>—to trace “the rise and progress of the art of navigation.” Melville’s use of the Harris Collection is explicit in "Extracts" and evident in unattributed information found elsewhere in the novel (Gretchko). For instance, Herbert’s observation, following directly after Melville’s extracted passage—that whales “engender by applying Belly to Belly, and bring forth but one at a Birth, like Elephants”—appears in Ishmael’s footnote in “The Grand Armada” on whale procreation and their “producing but one at a time” (Ch. 87).</note></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote44"><hi rend="italic">Harris Coll</hi></ref>.</l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Here they saw such huge troops of whales, that they were forced to proceed with a great deal of caution for fear they should run their ship upon them.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote45"><hi rend="italic">Schouten’s Sixth Circumnavigation</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote45"><hi rend="italic">Schouten’s Sixth Circumnavigation</hi>: Willem Corneliszoon Schouten (1567?-1625), Dutch navigator, named Cape Horn after his home town and discovered its “Drake Passage” between the Atlantic and Pacific during his only circumnavigation. The English version of his Dutch <hi rend="italic">Journael</hi>—<hi rend="italic">The Relation of a Wonderfull Voiage made by Willem Cornelison Schouten of Horne</hi> (1619)—first appeared in Purchas, but Melville read it in the Harris collection (see Herbert, above), which lists it as the sixth historical circumnavigation. The extracted passage (Harris 1.38) is exact except for a deleted reference to Penguins.</note></p>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212389524-6eh8q6a0ko6-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0028.jpg"/>

<p>“We set sail from the Elbe, wind N. E. in the ship called The Jonas-in-the-Whale.   *   *   * </p>
<p>Some say <hi rend="bold">the whale</hi> can’t open his mouth, but that is a fable.   *   *   * </p>
<p>They frequently climb up the masts to see whether they can see a whale, for the first discoverer has a ducat for his pains.   *   *   * </p>
<p>I was told of a whale taken near <hi rend="bold">Shetland</hi>, that had above a barrel of herrings in his belly.   *   *   * </p>
<p>One of our harpooneers told me that he caught once a whale in Spitzbergen that was white all over.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#ref_19538"><hi rend="italic">A Voyage to Greenland, A.D. 1671</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19538"><hi rend="italic">A Voyage to Greenland, A.D. 1671</hi>: The original excerpts for this extract are from Friedrich Martens, <hi rend="italic">Voyage into Spitzbergen and Greenland . . . 1671</hi>, as it first appeared in Tancred Robinson’s <hi rend="italic">An Account of Several Late Voyages and Discoveries to the South and North</hi> (London 1694). However, as with the previous extracts, Melville’s wording corresponds to the version of Martens found in Melville's stated source, the Harris collection (see above). Melville made two significant changes to the Harris version. In the second excerpt, he substituted “the whale” for Martens’s original “he” and, in the fourth excerpt, “Shetland” for “Hitland.”  Hypothesizing that the change to “Shetland” may have been due to a misreading of Melville's handwriting, the NN editors emend their text to Martens’s “Hitland.” However, since "Hitland" is a now-obsolete Dutch name for "Shetland," Melville may have revised for clarity; therefore, MEL makes no change. The third excerpt’s reward of a “ducat” for the “first discoverer” of a whale prefigures, and may have suggested to Melville, Ahab’s use, in “The Quarter-Deck” (Ch. 36), of a gold coin or doubloon to stimulate vigilance in the search for Moby Dick.</note>.</l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;<ref target="#ref_19538"><hi rend="italic">Harris Coll</hi></ref>.
</l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Several whales have come in upon this coast <hi rend="bold">(Fife)</hi>. Anno 1652, one eighty <hi rend="bold">feet</hi> in length of the whale-bone kind came in, which, (as I was informed) <hi rend="bold">besides</hi> a vast quantity of oil, did afford 500 weight of baleen. The jaws of it stand for a gate in the garden of <hi rend="bold">Pitfirren</hi>.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote46"><hi rend="italic">Sibbald’s Fife and Kinross</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote46"><hi rend="italic">Sibbald’s Fife and Kinross</hi>: Scottish physician, geographer, and whale taxonomist <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:265" type="person">Sir Robert Sibbald</name> (1641-1722) authored <hi rend="italic">The History Ancient and Modern of the Sheriffdoms of Fife and Kinross</hi> (1710). The passage is extracted from Part 4, sec 1 with only minor changes. Melville inserted “(Fife)” and changed Sibbald’s “foot” and “beside” to “feet” and “besides,” respectively. Melville’s misspelling, “Pitferren” has been corrected to “Pitfirren” in NN, Longman, and MEL.  Melville’s ancestors on his father’s side hailed from Fife, and Sibbald’s <hi rend="italic">History</hi> was likely in the family’s library (see note in Ch. 55 on “Prodromus whales”).</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>"<hi rend="bold">Myself</hi> have agreed to try whether <hi rend="bold">I</hi> can master and kill this Sperma-ceti whale, for I could never hear of any of that sort that was killed by any man, such is <hi rend="bold">his</hi> fierceness and swiftness.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote47"><hi rend="italic">Richard <hi rend="bold">Stafford’s</hi> Letter from the Bermudas</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote47"><hi rend="italic">Richard <hi rend="bold">Stafford’s</hi> Letter from the Bermudas</hi>: The extract is from a letter by a “Mr. Richard Stafford” printed in a 1668 issue of the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society</hi>. However, Melville may have found the passage quoted in his copy of Beale. Melville also made several small changes with significant impact. He changed the original’s “Myself, and about twenty others” and “we” to the first person singular “Myself” and “I,” respectively, and  Stafford’s reference to whales (“their”) from plural to singular (“his”). In short, the revisions singularize the conflict to one whaler and one whale, thereby prefiguring Ahab’s personal quest and Moby Dick’s particular fierceness. Both the American and British editions identify the letter writer as “Strafford”; the NN, Longman, and MEL editions correct to “Stafford.”</note></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote47"><hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans. A. D. 1668</hi></ref>.</l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="12em">“Whales in the sea</l>
<l rend="12em">God’s voice obey.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote48"><hi rend="italic">N. E. Primer</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote48"><hi rend="italic">N. E. Primer</hi>: <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:931" type="artwork"><hi rend="italic">The New England Primer</hi></name>, first published in 1687, was a widely-used introduction to reading; most of its selections were from the King James Bible. Melville’s signature in his own copy (an 1830s reprint; Sealts #384), in which this passage appears on p. 13, is dated March 6, 1851.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“We saw also abundance of large whales, there being more in <hi rend="bold">those</hi> southern seas, as I may say, by a hundred to one; than we have to the northward of us.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote49"><hi rend="italic">Captain Cowley’s Voyage round the Globe. A. D. 1729</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote49"><hi rend="italic">Captain Cowley’s Voyage round the Globe. A. D. 1729.</hi>: A seventeenth-century English buccaneer and naturalist, William Ambrosia Cowley mapped the Galápagos Islands during a 1683-86 circumnavigation under several captains and published his <hi rend="italic">Voyage round the Globe</hi> in a 1699 compendium edited by William Hacke and printed by John Knapton. However, the wording and late dating (“1729”) of this extract identifies it as coming from Vol. 4 of <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Voyages</hi>, published by John and James Knapton (see Gretchko, 304), which also includes narratives by buccaneers William Dampier and his friend Lionel Wafer; see also Bercaw #176 and 187a. Melville’s extract removes eighteen words from Cowley’s original and changes his “these” to “those.” Although Cowley does not reappear in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>, Ishmael refers to Dampier in “The Affidavit” (Ch. 45), where he offers an anecdote from Wafer.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; “and the breath of the whale is frequently attended with such <ref target="#MDextractsNote6"><hi rend="bold">an insupportable smell</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote6">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="bold">an insupportable smell</hi>// Ulloa (see below) uses this phrase twice, to describe first guano (2.101) and then the green vomit (not breath) of a kind of armored catfish (not whale) called “cope” (2.331-332), and never in relation to whales. Although Ulloa records several whale sightings, describing, for instance, their playful behavior (2.308) and how spouting whales at a distance appear to be breakers (2.234), Melville chose not to adapt these veracious observations into his concocted extract but instead dwells on the "insupportable" notion that the whale’s “breath” (i.e. spout) smells so strong as to induce mental disorder. For similar mystifications, see Ishmael’s discussion of the whale’s spout in “The Fountain” (Ch. 85).</note>, as to bring on a disorder of the brain.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote50"><hi rend="italic">Ulloa's South America</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote50"><hi rend="italic">Ulloa's South America</hi>: Melville's extract is from the two-volume 1758 London version of the 1749 <hi rend="italic">Voyage to South-America</hi> by Spanish naval officer and scientist Antonio de Ulloa (1716-1795). With the exception of "an insupportable smell" (see Revision Narrative above), the quotation is fabricated.</note></p>
<lb/>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431182144603-k5tqa81z1nb-70e1a0d5897d5bd0a0feac2a628413ef%2F000005737_0029.jpg"/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“To fifty chosen sylphs of special note,</l>
<l rend="4em">We trust the important charge, the petticoat.</l>
<l rend="4em">Oft have we known that seven-fold fence to fail,</l>
<l rend="4em">Tho’ <hi rend="bold">stuffed</hi> with hoops and armed with ribs of whale.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote51"><hi rend="italic">Rape of the Lock</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote51"><hi rend="italic">Rape of the Lock</hi>: The Roman Catholic and satirical poet Alexander Pope (1688-1744) wrote the mock-heroic “The Rape of the Lock” (final form 1717), based on an actual event, the surreptitious cutting of a lock of a lady’s hair. In researching sources for his whale and whaling references in "Extracts," Melville read works that, like Pope’s satiric epic, mixed genres (see Rabelais and Waller, above), which may have inspired <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>’s experiments in mixing such literary forms as fiction, drama, natural history, and meditation. In Pope’s original, the lady’s petticoat is not “stuffed” but “stiff with hoops and armed with ribs of whale.” By “ribs,” Pope means the flexible slats of “whalebone” from the mouths of baleen whales, which were used commercially for corsets and hoop skirts; see “Cetology” (Ch. 32). In the British version, “stuffed” appears as “stiff,” and thereby restores Pope’s wording. That Melville made the change seems likely, especially given Ishmael’s further discussion of the use of baleen as “stiffening contrivances” in women’s wear in “The Right Whale’s Head—Contrasted View” (Ch. 75). However, since the word “stuffed” works metrically and semantically, it may be a revision of Pope rather than an accident, with interpretive consequences; that is, the petticoats are stuffed, like the pretentious ladies wearing them. Assuming that “stuffed” was a mis-transcription of Melville’s handwritten “stiff” and that Melville (not an editor) made the restoration, the NN editors emend their text to “stiff.”  But since such a mixing of versions obscures the possibility of revision, MEL retains “stuffed,” noting the editorial options here.</note>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“If we compare land animals in respect to magnitude, with those that take up their abode in the deep, we shall find they will appear contemptible <hi rend="bold">in</hi> the comparison. The whale is doubtless the largest animal in creation.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote52"><hi rend="italic">Goldsmith, Nat. His</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote52"><hi rend="italic">Goldsmith, Nat. His.</hi>: <hi rend="italic">The History of the Earth and Animated Nature</hi>, a highly popular book by Anglo-Irish playwright and poet Oliver Goldsmith (1728-1774), first appeared in 1774. However, Melville’s extract combines the opening sentences of two paragraphs in ”Of the Whale” from an 1807 abridgment “<hi rend="italic">by Mrs. Pilkington</hi>.” In "Monstrous Pictures of Whales" (Ch. 55), Melville also refers to this specific abridgment and scorns its engraving of a whale as “an amputated sow.” The extract gives “contemptible in” instead of Goldsmith’s “contemptible by.”</note>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“If you should write a fable for little fishes, you would make them <hi rend="bold">speak</hi> like <hi rend="bold">great</hi> whales.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#ref_19569"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Goldsmith to Johnson</hi></hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19569">REVISION NARRATIVE: <hi rend="italic">Goldsmith to Johnson</hi> // Melville’s extract is not a direct quotation but an adaptive revision of a conversation between Irish writer Oliver Goldsmith and English lexicographer and essayist Samuel Johnson, as recorded by Scottish biographer James Boswell in an April 1773 entry in his <hi rend="italic">Life of Samuel Johnson</hi>. Goldsmith remarked that to ”write a good fable”—such as the one about the little fishes who envy the flight of birds—one must have the characters “talk like little fishes.” The observation made Johnson laugh, either over the absurdity of fish speaking or Goldsmith’s attempt to give them voice. Thinking he was being ridiculed, Goldsmith responded: “Why, Dr. Johnson, this is not so easy as you seem to think; for if you were to make little fishes talk, they would talk like <hi rend="smallcaps">whales</hi>.” Goldsmith’s retort teases and admires: Johnson was a gifted writer and a large man, and both features are hinted in Goldsmith's play on "whales" and in Boswell’s “small caps” form of the word <hi rend="smallcaps">whales</hi>. Melville’s revision compresses Goldsmith’s original concern—the writing of a good fable—with the problem of giving voice to animal characters. By substituting “speak” for “talk” and adding “great” to modify his lower-case “whales,” he also de-contextualizes Goldsmith’s famous line and generalizes the anecdote into a statement on creating a narrative. See, for instance, Ishmael’s line “To produce a mighty book, you must choose a mighty theme,” in “The Fossil Whale” (Ch. 104), as well as the revision narrative on "huge quarto edition of Johnson" in the same chapter.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“In the afternoon we saw what was supposed to be a rock, but it was found to be a dead whale, which some Asiatics had killed, and were then towing ashore. They seemed to endeavor to conceal themselves behind the <hi rend="bold">whale</hi>, in order to avoid being seen by us.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote53"><hi rend="italic">Cook's Voyages</hi></ref>.<note xml:id="MDextractsNote53"><hi rend="italic">Cook's Voyages</hi>: Captain James Cook (1728-1779), famed British naval officer and cartographer, made three voyages of exploration to the Pacific, and his narratives first appeared in the three-volume <hi rend="italic">A Voyage to the Pacific Ocean</hi> of 1784. However, Melville’s extract, titled “Cook’s Voyages,” quotes from the 1790 six-volume <hi rend="italic">Collection of Voyages round the World . . . Containing a complete historical account of CAPTAIN COOK’S VOYAGES</hi> (Bercaw 159). The only variations in the extract, taken from Cook’s third and final voyage, are Melville’s omission of “about one o’clock” (after “afternoon”) and “first” (before “supposed”), and the revision of “fish” for the second iteration of “whale” (Vol. 5, 1869). Cook’s “Asiatics” are inhabitants of the Pacific shores of Russia.</note>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The larger <hi rend="bold">whales</hi>, they seldom venture to attack. They stand in so great dread of some of them, that when out at sea they are afraid to mention even their names, and carry dung, <ref target="#MDextractsNote7"><hi rend="bold">lime-stone</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote7">REVISION NARRATIVE: lime-stone // Melville’s word “lime-stone,” appearing in both American and British editions, is “brimstone” in the original von Troil source (see below) and is a likely mis-transcription on Melville’s part. The editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> emend “lime-stone” to “brim-stone,” adding a hyphen to von Troil's "brimstone." MEL makes no change but records the differences here.</note>, juniper-wood, and some other articles of the same nature in their boats, in order to terrify and prevent their too near approach.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote54"><hi rend="italic">Uno Von Troil’s Letters on Banks’s and</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote54"><hi rend="italic">Uno Von Troil’s Letters on Banks’s and Solander’s Voyage to Iceland in 1772</hi>: Melville’s slightly modified extract is from Letter 12 of in the 1780 <hi rend="italic">Letters on Iceland</hi> by Swedish naturalist Uno von Troil (1746-1803), who later became archbishop of Uppsala. Swedish botanist Daniel Solander (1733-1782), friend and assistant of renowned naturalist and explorer Sir Joseph Banks (1743-1820), sailed with von Troil around the world (1768-1771) on the bark Endeavour under Captain James Cook (see above). Soon after their return, the three naturalists made their 1772 collecting trip to Iceland and the Outer Hebrides, as recorded in von Troil’s <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>. The first sentence of Melville’s extract rewrites the von Troil original—“The Icelanders, however, seldom venture to attack the larger ones, as their boats are small, and they unprovided with instruments proper for that purpose”—and converts “ones” to “whales.” Melville also substitutes “lime-stone” for von Troil’s “brimstone” (see Revision Narrative above).</note>
</l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote54"><hi rend="italic">Solander’s Voyage to Iceland in 1772</hi></ref>.</l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The <hi rend="bold">Spermacetti Whale</hi> found by the Nantuckois, is an active, fierce animal, and requires vast address and boldness in the fishermen.”</p>
<p><l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote55"><hi rend="italic">Thomas Jefferson’s Whale Memorial to the</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote55"><hi rend="italic">Thomas Jefferson’s Whale Memorial to the French minister in 1778</hi>: Melville’s extract conflates two consecutive sentences (minus 51 words after “Nantuckois”) from Jefferson’s November 19, 1788 letter to John Hay in <hi rend="italic">Memoir, Correspondence, and Miscellanies from the Papers of Thomas Jefferson</hi>, ed. by his grandson Thomas Jefferson Randolph (1829), Vol. 2, Letter 170,  p. 398. Jefferson was minister to France from 1785 to 1789, and the quoted passage appears in his lengthy “observations,” intended for the French minister and “annexed” to the Hay letter; they argue for opening markets in France to the American whaling industry. Melville may be having fun with Jefferson. He capitalizes and adds a “t” to Jefferson’s properly spelled “spermaceti whale” and alludes to the ponderous annex as a “Whale Memorial.” The misdating of Jefferson’s ministerial position to “1778” might be Melville's error or part of the teasing. See also Melville’s perhaps intentional misdating of Linnaeus’s work as “1776” in “Cetology” (Ch. 32) and Stubb's tricking of the inexperienced French whalemen in “The Pequod meets the Rose-Bud” (Ch. 91). Assuming the Jefferson misdating to be an error, NN corrects the date to “1788.” Recognizing the date may be intended, MEL makes no change but instead records the discrepancy here.</note>
</l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote55"><hi rend="italic">French minister in <hi rend="bold">1778</hi></hi></ref>.</l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“And pray, sir, what in the world is equal to it?”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote56"><hi rend="italic">Edmund Burke’s reference in Parliament</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote56"><hi rend="italic">Edmund Burke’s reference in Parliament to the Nantucket Whale-Fishery</hi>: Anglo-Irish member of Parliament known as the founder of modern conservative political thought, Edmund Burke (1729-1797) made the extracted remark in his March 22, 1775 speech before Parliament in support of <hi rend="italic">Conciliation with the Colonies</hi>. According to the NN editors (822), the lower-case “sir” suggests that  Melville found the passage quoted this way in one or the other of his often-consulted authorities, Thomas Beale and J. Ross Browne (who excerpted Beale).</note></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote56"><hi rend="italic">to the Nantucket Whale-Fishery</hi></ref>.</l>
</p>
<lb/>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212727586-3uz4m9d8esq-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0030.jpg"/>

<p>“Spain—a great whale stranded on the shores of Europe.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote57"><hi rend="italic">Edmund Burke. (somewhere.)</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote57"><hi rend="italic">Edmund Burke. (somewhere.)</hi>: The amusingly vague attribution suggests that Melville is quoting from memory. According to the NN edition (823), a possible source, close in wording, is James Prior’s 1824 <hi rend="italic">Memoir of the Life and Character of the Right Hon. Edmund Burke</hi> (see above). Melville’s choice of this brief passage with its metaphorical comparison of country and whale prefigures Ishmael’s metaphors in “Fast Fish and Loose Fish” (Ch. 89).</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“A tenth branch of the king’s ordinary revenue, said to be grounded on the consideration of his guarding and protecting the seas from pirates and robbers, is the right to royal fish, which are whale and sturgeon. And these, when either thrown ashore or caught near the <hi rend="bold">coast</hi>, are the property of the king.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote58"><hi rend="italic">Blackstone</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote58"><hi rend="italic">Blackstone</hi>: The 1765-1769 <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Laws of England</hi> by Sir William Blackstone (1723-1780) was the best-known exposition of English law in Melville’s day. This extract, from Book 1, p. 280, which establishes that whales caught offshore are "the property of the king," is revisited in “Heads or Tails” (Ch. 90). Its wording matches Blackstone's text except that both American and British versions print "coast" rather than the original “coasts.” NN emends to the plural; MEL retains "coast."</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Soon to the sport of death the crews repair:</l>
<l rend="4em">Rodmond unerring o’er his head suspends</l>
<l rend="4em">The barbed steel, and every turn attends.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote59"><hi rend="italic">Falconer’s Shipwreck</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote59"><hi rend="italic">Falconer’s Shipwreck</hi>: Melville cites Canto 2, lines 71 and 75-76 of <hi rend="italic">The Shipwreck</hi> (1762) by Scottish sailor William Falconer (1732-1769); however, he took the lines as quoted in Joseph C. Hart’s romance <hi rend="italic">Miriam Coffin, or The Whale-Fishermen</hi> (1834). Curiously, the passage has nothing to do with whaling. Falconer had survived the shipwreck of the merchant ship Britannia, and his popular, book-length poem about the event was highly regarded for its nautical realism. The extracted passage is part of an episode relating the first mate Rodmond’s killing of a dolphin. James Hart modified the Falconer passage as an epigraph for his chapter on the pursuit and killing of a whale (see vol. 2, ch. 6); Hart probably omitted lines 72-74 because they relate Rodmond’s use of a three-pronged spear (and not a harpoon).  Melville’s additional extract from <hi rend="italic">Miriam Coffin</hi> (below) and his reference to its “Author” in “Cetology” (Ch. 32) confirm his familiarity with Hart’s romance. For evidence that Melville read Falconer’s <hi rend="italic">Shipwreck</hi> directly, see “water-spout” in Ch. 40 and “Arion and the dolphin” (Ch. 83).</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Bright shone the roofs, the domes, the spires,</l>
<l rend="6em">And rockets <hi rend="bold">blew</hi> self driven,</l>
<l rend="4em">To hang their momentary <hi rend="bold">fires</hi></l>
<l rend="6em"><hi rend="bold">Around</hi> the vault of heaven.</l>
<lb/>
<l rend="4em">“So fire with water to compare,</l>
<l rend="6em">The ocean serves on high,</l>
<l rend="4em">Up-spouted by a whale in air,</l>
<l rend="6em">To express unwieldy joy.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote60"><hi rend="italic">Cowper, on the Queen’s Visit to London</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote60"><hi rend="italic">Cowper, on the Queen’s Visit to London</hi>: William Cowper (1731-1800), pronounced “Cooper,” was during his lifetime one of the most widely-read English poets of the 18th century. However, “On the Queen’s Visit to London, the Night of the 17th March, 1789” was published in William Hayley’s 3-volume <hi rend="italic">The Life, and Posthumous Writings, of William Cowper</hi> (1803). The American and British editions of <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> differ from Cowper’s original in the same three places: “blew” for “flew,” “fire” for “fires,” and “Around” for “Amid.” Only the second variant (“fire”) is clearly an error of transcription because it breaks the rhyme with “spires,” and MEL emends it to “fires.” The NN editors emended all three variants to Cowper’s originals, but since “blew” and “around” are arguably Melville’s revisions, MEL retains them.  Cowper appears again in a list of authors in “The Try-Works” (Ch. 96).</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Ten or fifteen gallons of blood are thrown out of the heart at a stroke, with immense velocity.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote61"><hi rend="italic">John Hunter’s account of the dissection</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote61"><hi rend="italic">John Hunter’s account of the dissection of a whale. (A small sized one.)</hi>: This observation by Scottish surgeon and anatomist John Hunter (1728-1793) first appeared in his “Observations on the Structure and Oeconomy of Whales,” published in the Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society, Vol. 77 (1787), pp. 371-450. However, Melville’s source is from Rev. William Paley’s fuller, though slightly modified quotation of Hunter, in his <hi rend="italic">Natural Theology; or Evidences of the Existence and Attributes of the Deity</hi> (1802), Ch. 10, p. 166.  Paley (1743-1805) quotes Hunter’s concluding line on the subject—“the whole idea fills the mind with wonder”—but Melville chooses not to include this expression of their wonderment, adding only the ”an” after “with” in his extract. The fact that the following extract uses Paley’s words that directly precede his Hunter quotation confirms that Melville’s source for Hunter is certainly Paley.  Hunter is mentioned in “Cetology” (Ch. 32). See also note on “the great Hunter” in “Of the Monstrous Pictures of Whales” (Ch. 55). For Ishmael’s description of a whale spouting blood, see “Stubb Kills a Whale” (Ch. 61).</note></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote61"><hi rend="italic">of a whale. (A small sized one.)</hi></ref></l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The aorta of a whale is larger in the bore than the main pipe of the water-works at London Bridge, and the water roaring in its passage through that pipe is inferior in impetus and velocity to the blood gushing from the whale’s heart.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote62"><hi rend="italic">Paley’s Theology</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote62"><hi rend="italic">Paley’s Theology</hi>: The passage is quoted verbatim from <hi rend="italic">Natural Theology; or Evidences of the Existence and Attributes of the Deity</hi> (1802), Ch. 10, by Rev. William Paley (1743-1805). See also the note for the previous extract.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The whale is a mammiferous animal without hind feet.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote63"><hi rend="italic">Baron Cuvier</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote63"><hi rend="italic">Baron Cuvier</hi>: Melville’s definition slightly modifies the one given by Baron Georges Cuvier (1769-1832) in "The Class Mammalia," vol. 4 of <hi rend="italic">The Animal Kingdom</hi> (1827), which reads “The Cetacea are mammiferous animals without hind feet.” Or perhaps it rephrases Cuvier’s sentence as quoted in Melville’s frequent source, the article on “Whales” in <hi rend="italic">The Penny Cyclopaedia</hi> (1843): “Cuvier defines the Cetaceans to be mammiferous animals without posterior feet” (Vol. 27, p. 273). In either case, Melville removed the Latin and changed the sentence to the singular. Baron Cuvier is mentioned in “Cetology” (Ch. 32) and “The Fossil Whale” (Ch. 104) and should not be confused with his brother, the naturalist Frédéric Cuvier, as Melville does in “Moby Dick” (Ch. 41). See also “Frederick Cuvier” in Ch. 55. Melville’s only copy of the Baron’s <hi rend="italic">Animal Kingdom</hi> was Vol. 10, on “The Class Pisces,” given to him, perhaps as a joke, by his younger brother Allan, on 1 January 1851, while Herman was writing his <hi rend="italic">Whale</hi> (Sealts 171).</note>.</p>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212915636-05l2jmnwou7f-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0031.jpg"/>

<p>“In 40 degrees south, we saw Spermacetti Whales, but did not take any till the first of May, the sea being then covered with them.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote64"><hi rend="italic">Colnett’s Voyage for the Purpose of</hi></ref></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote64"><hi rend="italic">Extending the Spermacetti Whale Fishery</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote64"><hi rend="italic">Colnett’s Voyage for the Purpose of Extending the Spermacetti Whale Fishery</hi>: Melville’s source—British naval officer, explorer, and trader James Colnett (1753-1806)—is quoted verbatim except for the deleted clause “when we made the Isle” following the word “May.” The passage is from the entry for 1 May 1793 in <hi rend="italic">A Voyage to the South Atlantic . . . for the Purpose of Extending the Spermaceti Whale Fisheries</hi> (1798). Colnett is also mentioned in “Monstrous Pictures of Whales” (Ch. 55) and “Less Erroneous Pictures of Whales” (Ch. 56).</note>.</l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“In the free element beneath me swam,</l>
<l rend="4em">Floundered and dived, in play, in chace, in battle,</l>
<l rend="4em">Fishes of every color, form, and kind;</l>
<l rend="4em">Which language cannot paint, and mariner</l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="bold">Had</hi> never seen; from dread Leviathan</l>
<l rend="4em">To insect millions peopling every wave:</l>
<l rend="4em"><hi rend="bold">Gather’d</hi> in shoals immense, like floating islands,</l>
<l rend="4em">Led by mysterious <hi rend="bold">instincts</hi> through that waste</l>
<l rend="4em">And trackless region, though on every side</l>
<l rend="4em">Assaulted by voracious enemies,</l>
<l rend="4em">Whales, sharks, and monsters, arm’d in front or jaw,</l>
<l rend="4em">With swords, saws, spiral horns, or hooked fangs.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#ref_19462"><hi rend="italic">Montgomery’s World before the Flood</hi></ref><note xml:id="ref_19462"><hi rend="italic">Montgomery’s World before the Flood</hi>: James Montgomery (1771-1854), Scottish-born poet, published his long poem <hi rend="italic">The World Before the Flood</hi> in 1812. But the extract is actually from Canto 2 of “The Pelican Island” from Montgomery’s <hi rend="italic">The Pelican Island and Other Poems</hi> (1812). However, Melville’s source for the text is Henry T. Cheever’s <hi rend="italic">The Whale and His Captors</hi> (1849), where the same lines are used as an epigraph for Chapter 8, “Atlantic Ocean Mammoths and Monsters.” Cheever’s version removes eight lines from Montgomery’s original and makes two minor changes: “Had” for Montgomery’s “Hath” and “Gather’d” for “Others.” Cheever also mistakenly attributed the lines to <hi rend="italic">The World Before the Flood</hi>. Melville adopted Cheever’s changes and misattribution, and made a change of his own: “instincts” for “instinct.”  Although the NN edition (824) takes the plural to be an error in transcription and restores ”instinct,” MEL retains “instincts” as possibly Melville’s intended revision and notes the difference here. Montgomery’s “Which language cannot paint,” in line 4, is echoed in “Of Monstrous Pictures of Whales” (Ch. 55) where Ishmael observes that Leviathan “must remain unpainted to the last.” Melville’s chapter title also echoes Cheever’s “Mammoths and Monsters” in his Chapter 8.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="6em">“Io! Pæan! Io! sing,</l>
<l rend="6em">To the finny people’s king.</l>
<l rend="6em">Not a mightier whale than this</l>
<l rend="6em">In the vast Atlantic is;</l>
<l rend="6em">Not a fatter fish than he,</l>
<l rend="6em">Flounders round the Polar Sea."</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote65"><hi rend="italic">Charles Lamb’s Triumph of the Whale</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote65"><hi rend="italic">Charles Lamb’s Triumph of the Whale</hi>: These lines open “The Triumph of the Whale” — a sly jab at the Prince of Wales, later King George IV — by English poet and essayist Charles Lamb (1775-1834). The poem was first published in the <hi rend="italic">Examiner</hi>, March 15, 1812. According to his 1 May 1850 letter to Richard Henry Dana, Jr., Melville’s first exposure to Lamb was in the ship’s library as he crossed the Atlantic in October 1849. In his London travel journal, Melville lists having acquired “Charles Lamb’s Works (octavo)” directly from publisher Edward Moxon, and Sealts identifies <hi rend="italic">The Works of Charles Lamb, A New Edition</hi>(1848) as the likely item Melville listed.  (See NN <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi> 144 and Sealts 315, 316.) A four-volume set, it is also Melville’s likely source for his extract.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“In the year <hi rend="bold">1690</hi> some persons were on a high <hi rend="bold">hill</hi> observing the whales spouting and sporting with each other, when one observed; there—pointing to the sea—is a green pasture where our children’s grand-children will go for bread.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote66"><hi rend="italic">Obed Macy’s History of Nantucket</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote66"><hi rend="italic">Obed Macy’s History of Nantucket</hi>: Not counting minor omissions, after “1690” and “hill,” for the sake of brevity, this extract reproduces verbatim the wording found on p. 33 of <hi rend="italic">The History of Nantucket</hi> (1835) by Obed Macy (1762-1844). Macy’s original wording is also quoted in J. Ross Browne’s 1846 <hi rend="italic">Etchings of a Whaling Cruise</hi> (p. 518). Melville owned both books (Sealts 88, 345), and the omissions are his. In “The Mast-Head” (Ch. 35), Melville paraphrases another of Macy’s anecdotes concerning the sighting of whales from land, which appears two paragraphs earlier on p. 31 in Macy’s book. (See Revision Narrative “Obed Macy” in Ch. 35.) Browne, Melville’s more likely source, reproduces both of Macy’s anecdotes without alteration in an extensive block quotation In his book’s “Appendix” (pp. 517-518). Browne, who is the source of an extract below, is also mentioned in “Cetology” (Ch. 32) and “Less Erroneous Pictures of Whales” (Ch. 56).</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“I built a cottage for Susan and myself and made a gateway in the form of a Gothic Arch, by setting up a whale’s jaw bones.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote67"><hi rend="italic">Hawthorne’s Twice Told Tales</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote67"><hi rend="italic">Hawthorne’s Twice Told Tales</hi>: This and the following extract are from Vol. 2 of <hi rend="italic">Twice-Told Tales</hi> by Melville’s admired friend Nathaniel Hawthorne (1804-1864), to whom <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> is dedicated. Melville had borrowed a copy of Hawthorne’s 1837 collection of stories and sketches from Evert Duyckinck in July 1849 (Sealts 258). On January 22, 1851, Hawthorne gave Melville the entire collection in two unmatched volumes, both of which are marked with marginal checks and/or vertical lines in Melville’s hand. Both extracts appear in the second, 1842 volume (Sealts 260; see also Jonathan A. Cook’s “Introduction” in MMO), and both are check marked by Melville. This extract appears verbatim and is part of an aged fisherman’s Thanksgiving recollection of his wife from “The Village Uncle.”</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“<hi rend="bold">She</hi> came to bespeak a monument for her first love, who had been killed by a whale in the Pacific ocean, no less than forty years <hi rend="bold">ago</hi>.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote68"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote68"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>: Melville’s second extract from Hawthorne’s <hi rend="italic">Twice-Told Tales</hi> (see note above) is from “Chippings with a Chisel.” The sketch depicts the customers of a Martha’s Vineyard gravestone sculptor. Here, an elderly woman orders a memorial for her “ocean-buried” first love, similar to the plaques commemorating lost whalemen in “The Chapel” (Ch. 7). Ishmael’s up-beat conclusion that “we have hugely mistaken this matter of Life and Death” echoes Hawthorne’s similar sentiment: “Every gravestone … is the visible symbol of a mistaken system,” a line also marked in Melville’s copy. Melville adapted the passage, revising Hawthorne’s “An elderly lady” to “She” and his “before” to “ago.”</note>.</p>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431212982802-zl18jabz7op-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0032.jpg"/>

<p>“No, Sir, ’tis a Right Whale,” answered Tom; “I saw his spout; he threw up a pair of as pretty rainbows as a Christian would wish to look at. He’s a raal oil-butt, that fellow!”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote69"><hi rend="italic">Cooper’s Pilot</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote69"><hi rend="italic">Cooper’s Pilot</hi>: Except for minor changes in capitalization, Melville transcribed his extract verbatim from Ch. 17 of <hi rend="italic">The Pilot; A Tale of the Sea</hi> (1823) by <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:294" type="person">James Fenimore Cooper</name> (1789-1851). Although best known for <hi rend="italic">The Last of the Mohicans</hi> and the other novels in his Leatherstocking series, Cooper wrote more nautical fictions than land-based ones. A distinguishing feature of the right whale, also noted in “The Right Whale’s Head” (Ch. 75), is its two spiracles and double spout, which Tom in the extract identifies as “a pair of as pretty rainbows as a Christian would wish to look at.” In his discussion of the sperm whale’s single, bushy spout in “The Fountain” (Ch. 85), Ishmael mentions the phenomenon of the rainbow radiating from the spout’s mist and gives the image a metaphysical if not Christian application. The “thick mists of the dim doubt of my mind” suffused with the “heavenly ray” of “divine intuition” challenge us to regard the whale’s rainbow-emitting spout with an “equal eye” that can comprehend both doubt and belief. </note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The <hi rend="bold">papers</hi> were brought in, and we saw in the Berlin Gazette that <hi rend="bold">whales</hi> had been introduced on the stage there.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote70"><hi rend="italic">Eckermann’s Conversations with Goethe</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote70"><hi rend="italic">Eckermann’s Conversations with Goethe</hi>: Melville’s extract follows Margaret Fuller’s translation of Johann Peter Eckermann’s <hi rend="italic">Conversations with Goethe in the last Years of his Life</hi> (1839) verbatim, except for two differences: “papers” for “newspapers” and “whales” for “whales and sea-monsters.” Although Melville elsewhere interchanges “monster” for “whale,” his deletion of “sea-monsters” here lessens the sensationalism of the Berlin staging. Melville also cites Eckermann’s description of Goethe’s “massive chest” as an example of strength and beauty in “The Tail” (Ch. 86). In several other works and in an 1851 letter to Hawthorne, Melville alludes to  Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749-1832), the renowned German playwright, novelist, critic, and scientist. Goethe’s characters Faust and Mephistopheles (<hi rend="italic">Faust</hi> Part 1, 1808, Part 2, 1832) suggest aspects of Ahab and Fedallah.</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“My God! Mr. <ref target="#MDextractsNote8"><hi rend="bold">Chace</hi></ref>, what is the matter?” I answered, “we have been stove by a whale.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote71"><l rend="10em">"<hi rend="italic">Narrative of the <hi rend="bold">Shipwreck</hi> of the Whale Ship</hi></l></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote71"><hi rend="italic">Narrative of the <hi rend="bold">Shipwreck</hi> of the Whale Ship Essex</hi>: “Stove” meaning smashed is past tense for “stave”; see Glossary. Owen Chase’s 1821 <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi> relates the sinking of the whaleship Essex by repeated attacks of a whale. In April 1851, Melville’s father-in-law Lemuel Shaw gave Melville a copy of the book (Sealts 134), and using it to lend credence to the fact that a whale can sink a ship, Melville added verbatim passages from the <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi> in “The Affidavit” (Ch. 45; see note on “the ship Essex).</note>
<l rend="12em">	<hi rend="italic">Essex of Nantucket, which was attacked and</hi></l>
<l rend="12em">	<hi rend="italic">finally destroyed by a large <hi rend="bold">Sperm Whale</hi></hi></l>
<l rend="12em">	<hi rend="italic">in the Pacific Ocean.” By Owen Chace of</hi></l>
<l rend="12em">	<hi rend="italic">Nantucket, first mate of said vessel. New</hi></l>
<l rend="12em">	<hi rend="italic">York. 1821.</hi></l>
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote8">REVISION NARRATIVE // Mr. <hi rend="bold">Chace</hi>: The editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> alter Melville's spelling of “Chace” (as it appears in both American and British versions) to “Chase” (as the name appears in Chase’s book). MEL retains "Chace" since it is a variant of the name and one Melville used in annotating his copy of Chase’s book. In the title cited for this extract, Melville has dropped “Most Extraordinary and Distressing” as adjectives for “Shipwreck” and reduced the original “Spermaceti-Whale” to “Sperm Whale.” As does the NN edition, Longman and MEL supply an end-quote mark dropped after "Ocean" in the American edition.</note>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="2em">“A mariner sat in the shrouds one night,</l>
<l rend="4em">The wind was piping free;</l>
<l rend="2em">Now bright, now dimmed, was the moonlight pale,</l>
<l rend="2em">And the phospher gleamed in the wake of the whale,</l>
<l rend="4em">As it floundered in the sea.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote9"><hi rend="italic">Elizabeth Oakes Smith</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote9">Elizabeth Oakes Smith: Melville’s quotation is from Smith's poem “The Drowned Mariner,” and it varies from the original in two places: He has “in the shrouds” rather than “on the shrouds” and “it floundered” rather than “he floundered.” The NN edition emends “in” to “on.” MEL retains both of Melville’s alterations, in particular the nautically correct usage, “in the shrouds.”</note>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The quantity of line withdrawn from the different boats engaged in the capture of this one whale, amounted altogether to 10,440 yards or nearly six English miles.”  *  *  *</p>
<p>“Sometimes the whale shakes its tremendous tail in the air, which, cracking like a whip, resounds to the distance of three or four miles.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:303" type="person"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:966" type="artwork"><hi rend="italic">Scoresby</hi></name></name>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Mad with the <hi rend="bold">agonies</hi> he endures from these fresh attacks, the infuriated <hi rend="bold">Sperm Whale</hi> rolls over and over; he rears his enormous head, and with wide expanded <hi rend="bold">jaws</hi> snaps at everything <hi rend="bold">around him</hi>. He rushes at the boats with his head; they are propelled before him with vast swiftness, and sometimes utterly destroyed.</p>
<p>&#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; * &#xA0;&#xA0; It is a matter of great astonishment that the consideration of the habits of so interesting, and, in a commercial
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213000609-gyi6njhico5-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0033.jpg"/> point of view, of so important an animal <hi rend="bold">(as the Sperm Whale)</hi> should have been so entirely neglected, or should have excited so little curiosity among the numerous, and many of them competent observers, that of late years must have possessed the most abundant and the most convenient opportunities of witnessing their habitudes.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote10"><hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:955" type="artwork"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:304" type="person">Thomas Beale</name></name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:176" type="text">History of the Sperm Whale</name>, 1839.</hi></ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote10">Thomas Beale: Melville made minor adaptations to his extract from Beale. He pluralized “agony,” revised “sea beast” to “Sperm Whale,” altered “jaw” to “jaws,” added “him” to give “around him,” and inserted the parenthetical phrase “(as the Sperm Whale).” The NN edition alters “jaws” back to “jaw”; MEL retains “jaws” and all other variants.</note></p>
<lb/>

<p>“The Cachalot” (Sperm Whale) “is not only better armed than the True Whale” (Greenland or Right Whale) “in possessing a formidable weapon at either extremity of its body, but also more frequently displays a disposition to employ these weapons offensively, and in a manner at once so artful, bold, and mischievous, as to lead to its being regarded as the most dangerous to attack of all the known species of the whale tribe.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:184" type="text">Frederick Debell Bennett’s Whaling </name></hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Voyage Round the Globe. 1840.</hi></l>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l>October 13. “There she blows,” was sung out from the mast-head.</l>
<l>“Where away?” demanded the captain.</l>
<l>“Three points off the lee bow, sir.”</l>
<l>“Raise up your wheel. Steady!”</l>
<l>“Steady, sir.”</l>
<l>“Mast-head ahoy! Do you see that whale now?”</l>
<l>“Ay ay, sir! A shoal of Sperm Whales! There she blows! There she breaches!”</l>
<l>“Sing out! sing out every time!”</l>
<l>“Ay ay, sir! There she blows! there—there—thar she blows—bowes—bo-o-o-s!”</l>
<l>“How far off?”</l>
<l>“Two miles and a half.”</l>
<l>“Thunder and lightning! so near! Call all hands!”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p>
<lg>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:239" type="person"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/artwork:958" type="artwork">J. Ross Browne</name></name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:115" type="text">Etchings</name></hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">of a Whaling Cruize. 1846.</hi></l>
</lg>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The Whale-ship Globe, on board of which vessel occurred the horrid transactions we are about to relate, belonged to the island of Nantucket.”</p>
<p>
<lg>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">“Narrative of the Globe Mutiny,” by</hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Lay and Hussey survivors. A. D. 1828.</hi></l>
</lg>
</p>
<lb/>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213023618-35d415uv3xt-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0034.jpg"/>

<p>“Being once pursued by a whale which he had wounded, he parried the assault for some time with a lance; but the furious monster at length rushed on the boat; himself and comrades only being preserved by leaping into the water when they saw the onset was inevitable.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Missionary Journal of Tyerman and Bennet</hi>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Nantucket itself,” said Mr. Webster, “is a very striking and peculiar portion of the National interest. There is a population of eight or nine thousand persons, living here in the sea, adding largely every year to the National wealth by the boldest and most persevering industry.”</p>
<p>
<lg>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Report of Daniel Webster’s Speech in the</hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">U. S. Senate, on the application for the </hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Erection of a Breakwater at Nantucket.</hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
 <hi rend="italic">1828.</hi></l>
</lg>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The whale fell directly over him, and probably killed him in a moment.”</p>
<p>
<lg>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">“The Whale and his Captors, or The Whaleman’s</hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Adventures and the Whale’s Biography, gathered</hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">on the Homeward Cruise of the Commodore</hi></l>
<l rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Preble.” By Rev. Henry T. Cheever.</hi></l>
</lg>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“If you make the least damn bit of noise,” replied Samuel, “I will send you to hell.”</p>
<p>
<lg>
<l rend="2em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Life of Samuel Comstock (the mutineer), by his</hi></l>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">brother, William Comstock. Another Ver-</hi></l>
<l rend="4em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">sion of the whale-ship Globe narrative.</hi></l>
</lg>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The voyages of the Dutch and English to the Northern Ocean, in order, if possible, to discover a passage through it to India, though they failed of their main object, laid open the haunts of the whale.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">McCulloch’s Commercial Dictionary.</hi>
</p>
<lb/>

<p>“These things are reciprocal; the ball rebounds, only to bound forward again; for now in laying open the haunts of the whale, the whalemen seem to have indirectly hit upon new clews to that same mystic North-West Passage.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote11"><hi rend="italic">From “Something” unpublished</hi></ref>.</p><note xml:id="MDextractsNote11"><hi rend="italic">From “Something” unpublished</hi>: Probably a bit of writing cut from <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>. The extract echoes wording (here in bold) in "Moby Dick" (Ch. 41), in which Ishmael discusses how the "secluded White Whale had <hi rend="bold">haunted</hi> those uncivilized seas mostly frequented by the Sperm Whale fishermen" and how Moby Dick's ubiquity is explained by the legend that the sperm whale had long ago discovered a <hi rend="bold">Nor' West Passage</hi> between the Atlantic and Pacific.</note>

<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213068273-2fja0fancys-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0035.jpg"/>

<p>“It is impossible to meet a whale-ship on the ocean without being struck by her mere appearance. The vessel under short sail, with look-outs at the mast-heads, eagerly scanning the wide expanse around them, has a totally different air from those engaged in a regular voyage.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Currents and Whaling. <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:190" type="text">U. S. Ex. Ex</name>.</hi></p>
<lb/>

<p>“Pedestrians in the vicinity of London and elsewhere may recollect having seen large curved bones set upright in the earth, either to form arches over gateways, or entrances to alcoves, and they may perhaps have been told that these were the ribs of whales.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:191" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Tales of a Whale Voyager to the Arctic Ocean</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“It was not till the boats returned from the pursuit of these whales, that the whites saw their ship in bloody possession of the savages enrolled among the crew.”</p>
<p>
<l rend="1em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote12"><hi rend="italic">Newspaper Account</hi></ref> <hi rend="italic">of the Taking and</hi></l>
<l rend="1em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic">Retaking of the Whale-ship</hi> <ref target="#MDextractsNote36"><hi rend="italic">Hobomack</hi></ref></l>
</p>
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote12"><hi rend="italic">Newspaper Account</hi>: According to Wilson Heflin, this extract is certainly an “invention” (<hi rend="italic">Herman Melville’s Whaling Years</hi>, 98). Nor would it be the only time Melville concocted “accounts” from newspapers for fictional or rhetorical ends (see <hi rend="italic">Typee</hi>, Ch. 4 and <hi rend="italic">Billy Budd</hi>, Ch. 29). In Typee, for instance, he had referred to a Fiji “massacre” of the crew of the “Hobomak,” and though that whale ship existed, under the spelling “Hobomok,” it was never the scene of any  “bloody possession.” However, the captain of the Hobomok, Silas Jones, had written an account of his experience of the 1835 islander attack aboard the Awashonks, on which he had served as third mate. The story is a “classic in the annals of whaling” (Wilson 91). Melville might have heard the account from Jones or his Hobomok crew when they gammed with Melville’s ship Acushnet in the Galápagos in 1842. That said, the Awashonks attack did not involve “savages enrolled among the crew.” This extract detail comports more closely with events on board the Fairhaven whale ship Sharon, in 1842, while Melville was at sea. In this case, the Sharon’s abusive captain Norris had beaten to death Black sailor John Babcock. Subsequent desertions reduced Norris’s crew to seventeen. "Enrolled" among them were three islanders, who seized the ship and murdered Norris (Wilson 95-98). Melville’s conflation of the Awashonks and Sharon incidents with the ship’s name Hobomok in his “newspaper account” might be a lapse of memory; however, Melville’s consistently misspelled “Hobomak” and “Hobomack,” in <hi rend="italic">Typee</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>, respectively, suggest an intentional variance. See “Hobomack,” below.</note>
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote36"><hi rend="italic">Hobomack</hi>: In using the word “Hobomack” (with an “a”) to identify the whaler Hobomok (with an “o”) as the scene of maritime violence, Melville perpetuates a variant he initiated in his first book, <hi rend="italic">Typee</hi>, where he refers to the “Hobomak” (with an “a”). In fact, no mutiny or massacre occurred on the Hobomok (see “<hi rend="italic">Newspaper Account</hi>,” above). The name—with various versions of each spelling (see NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> 829)—refers to the Wampanoag spirit of death, later associated with the Christian devil. It is also the name of a warrior and intermediary much admired by the Plymouth settlers and the namesake hero in Lydia Maria Child’s 1824 interracial novel <hi rend="italic">Hobomok</hi> (Penguin <hi rend="italic">Typee</hi> 316n). Since Melville’s reference is to the whale ship (spelled with an “o”) and assuming Melville’s spelling (with an “a”) is an error, the editors of the NN <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> emended Melville’s “Hobomack” to “Hobomock.” MEL, however, argues that Melville’s spelling may be intentional, especially in light of the fictive nature of the extract, and, therefore, retains “Hobomack.”</note>
<lb/>

<p>“It is generally well known that out of the crews of Whaling vessels (American) few ever return in the ships on board of which they departed.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:192" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Cruise in a Whale Boat</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“Suddenly a mighty mass emerged from the water, and shot up perpendicularly into the air. It was the whale.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:177" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Miriam Coffin or the Whale Fisherman</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“The Whale is harpooned to be sure; but bethink you, how you would manage a powerful unbroken colt, with the mere appliance of a rope tied to the root of his tail.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:181" type="text"><hi rend="italic">A Chapter on Whaling in Ribs and Trucks</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>“On one occasion I saw two of these monsters (whales) probably male and female, slowly swimming, one after the other, within less than a stone’s throw of the shore” (<ref target="#MDextractsNote13">Tierra</ref><note xml:id="MDextractsNote13">Tierra: In the American and British editions, Melville’s parenthetical insertion of “(Terra Del Fuego)” gives the Portuguese “Terra” instead of the proper Spanish, “Tierra.” Since Melville’s 1846 edition of Darwin’s classic voyage of the Beagle spells the word properly, the word “Terra” is probably a typo, and MEL corrects to “Tierra.”</note> Del Fuego), “over which the beech tree extended its branches.”</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<hi rend="italic"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/person:305" type="person">Darwin</name>’s <name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:193" type="text">Voyage of a Naturalist</name>.</hi></p>
<lb/>

<p>“‘Stern all!’ exclaimed the mate, as upon turning his head, he saw the distended jaws of a large Sperm Whale close to the
<pb facs="https://dave-uploads-juxtaeditions.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads%2F1431213089747-6b70fik7kle-f4677a0452eaecc0b72412ff0846d2ad%2F000005737_0036.jpg"/> head of the boat, threatening it with instant destruction;—‘Stern all, for your lives!”’</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:194" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Wharton the Whale Killer</hi></name>.</p>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“So be cheery, my lads, let your hearts never fail,</l>
<l rend="4em">While the bold harpooneer is striking the whale!”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p>
<l rend="10em">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<ref target="#MDextractsNote14"><name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:195" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Nantucket Song</hi></name></ref>.</l>
</p>
<note xml:id="MDextractsNote14"><hi rend="italic">Nantucket Song</hi>: These lines seem to be a conflation of two renderings of a song quoted twice in different versions in Browne’s <hi rend="italic">Etchings</hi>. (See Stuart Frank, “Two Songs,” MSEx 63: 4-7.)</note>
<lb/>

<p>
<lg>
<l rend="4em">“Oh, the rare old Whale, mid storm and gale</l>
<l rend="6em">In his ocean home will be</l>
<l rend="4em">A giant in might, where might is right,</l>
<l rend="6em">And King of the boundless sea.”</l>
</lg>
</p>
<p rend="center">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;
<name ref="https://mel-catalog.herokuapp.com/api/entries/text:196" type="text"><hi rend="italic">Whale Song</hi></name>.</p>

</body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
