<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Glossary</title>



            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>

                <publisher/>
                <pubPlace/>
                <date/>
                <authority/>
                <availability><p/></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="main" rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Glossary of Nautical and Whaling Terms</hi></head>

<p><hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> is rich in nautical language, and at times Melville provides his own definitions and descriptions. Since in most cases, today’s readers are not likely to know these words, or remember them while reading, the Glossary is a ready guide. Many terms have more than one meaning; this list focuses on Melville’s usage in context.</p>
<p>Nautical and whaling terms also defined elsewhere in the Glossary appear in <hi rend="bold">bold</hi>. Synonyms and related terms are <hi rend="italic">italicized</hi>. The sources for this Glossary are standard dictionaries as well as nautical word lists by such sailor-authors as Dana, Falconer, Russell, Smyth, Lever, and Bradford (see Further Reading).</p>

<p><ref target="54-the-town-hos-story#abaft" type="reference" xml:id="abaft"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">abaft</hi></hi></ref> Behind; toward the stern.</p>
<p><ref target="71-the-pequod-meets-the-jeroboam-her-story#abeam" type="reference" xml:id="abeam"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">abeam</hi></hi></ref> At 90 degrees to a vessel’s midsection.</p>
<p><ref target="28-ahab#above_hatches" type="reference" xml:id="above_hatches"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">above hatches</hi></hi></ref> On deck.</p>
<p><ref target="29-enter-ahab-to-him-stubb#afoul" type="reference" xml:id="afoul"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">afoul</hi></hi></ref> Tangled up or dangerously in contact with; see also <hi rend="bold">foul</hi> and <hi rend="bold">coming afoul of</hi>.</p>
<p><ref target="22-merry-christmas#aft" type="reference" xml:id="aft"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">aft</hi></hi></ref> Toward, to, or at the rear.</p>
<p><ref target="53-the-gam#after-oar" type="reference" xml:id="after-oar"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">after-oar</hi></hi></ref> The oar in the whaleboat closest to the <hi rend="bold">stern</hi>.</p>
<p><ref target="99-the-doubloon#alow" type="reference" xml:id="alow"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">alow</hi></hi></ref> Below.</p>
<p><ref target="66-the-shark-massacre#anchor-watch" type="reference" xml:id="anchor-watch"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">anchor-watch</hi></hi></ref> The short night watch, kept by fewer men than usual, when a whaling vessel is tethered to a whale carcass; it is named by analogy to the practice on non-whaling vessels, which keep a reduced watch while at anchor.</p>
<p><ref target="133-the-chase-first-day#apeak" type="reference" xml:id="apeak"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">apeak</hi></hi></ref> Pointing upward. The oars’ handles are placed in notches in the flooring on the opposite side of the boat, leaving the oars pointing up into a V shape; also <hi rend="italic">peaked</hi>.</p>
<p><ref target="64-stubbs-supper#argosy" type="reference" xml:id="argosy"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">argosy</hi></hi></ref> Large merchant vessel.</p>
<p><ref target="16-the-ship#articles" type="reference" xml:id="articles"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">articles</hi></hi></ref> Seaman’s contract with the owners.</p>
<p><ref target="107-the-carpenter#athwartships" type="reference" xml:id="athwartships"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">athwartships</hi></hi></ref> Across, crosswise; also <hi rend="italic">athwart</hi>.</p>
<p><ref target="3-the-spouter-inn#avast" type="reference" xml:id="avast"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">avast</hi></hi></ref> “Stop,” or “stop that!”</p>
<p><ref target="47-the-mat-maker#away_from_the_wind" type="reference" xml:id="away_from_the_wind"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">away from the wind</hi></hi></ref> With the wind directly behind.</p>
<p><ref target="22-merry-christmas#back" type="reference" xml:id="back"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">back</hi></hi></ref> Turn the <hi rend="bold">spar</hi> holding a sail so the wind strikes the front of the sail (and slows the vessel), as in “back the <hi rend="bold">main-yard</hi>”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">backstays</hi></hi> Strong ropes supporting a mast, leading from it, rearward, to the sides of the ship.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">baleen</hi></hi> Long, fringed plates in the mouth, with which certain whales strain their food from seawater. Also called <hi rend="bold">whalebone</hi>; they are not bone but are made of keratin, the main component of teeth and hair.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">ballast</hi></hi> Heavy materials such as iron or stones placed in the hold of a vessel to keep it from capsizing.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bands</hi></hi> 1) Ties fastening whaleboats to their ship. 2) Iron collars near the ends of the <hi rend="bold">yardarms</hi>, to which the supporting <hi rend="bold">lifts</hi> are shackled. Also meaning strips of canvas sewn across the top of a sail to strengthen it. <hi rend="italic">Reef bands</hi> are narrow strips of strengthening canvas sewn across a sail to hold a line of <hi rend="italic">reef-points</hi>, the short ropes with which a sail is partly tied up to reduce its area.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bank</hi></hi> Large elevated area of the sea floor, usually rich in fish and other marine life.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">barrel</hi></hi> An inexact measure; in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> there are ten barrels to the ton of sperm oil (Ch. 68), and six barrels to an oil <hi rend="bold">cask</hi> (Ch. 98).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">batten</hi></hi> Also <hi rend="italic">batten down</hi>. Seal tightly with canvas and <hi rend="italic">battens</hi>, pieces of wood, as in “batten the hatches.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">belay</hi></hi> Secure a rope to a <hi rend="bold">belaying pin</hi>. Also “stop that,” <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">avast</hi></hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">belaying-pins</hi></hi> Often shortened to <hi rend="italic">pins</hi>. Tapered bars of wood or iron (but of whale ivory on the <hi rend="italic">Pequod</hi>) in various places on deck, to which ropes of the <hi rend="bold">running rigging</hi> are secured.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bells</hi></hi> To mark time, a bell is struck every half-hour with one added strike for each successive half hour, over a four-hour period, after which the sequence is repeated. Thus, 12:30 a.m. is one bell; one o’clock, two bells, and so on to four a.m., or eight bells. Eight a.m., noon, four p.m., eight p.m., and midnight are also eight bells. “Eight bells there below! Tumble up!” (Ch. 40).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bible leaves</hi></hi> Thin slices (like pages in a Bible) into which <hi rend="bold">horse-pieces</hi> of blubber are cut with <hi rend="bold">mincing knives</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">binnacle</hi></hi> Box at the <hi rend="bold">helm</hi> for the two compasses. A <hi rend="italic">binnacle lamp</hi> shines on the compass <hi rend="bold">cards</hi>; a <hi rend="italic">binnacle watch</hi> is a timepiece placed there.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">blocks…sheaves</hi></hi> A block houses a <hi rend="bold">sheave</hi>, a roller or wheel; together they make a pulley.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bluff bows</hi></hi> Rounded, full front, as in the architecture of a whaleship.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">boarding-sword</hi></hi> Long, two-handed, double-edged knife used in the work of peeling blubber from the whale and bringing it <hi rend="italic">on board</hi>; thus the name. Also <hi rend="italic">boarding knife</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">boat hook</hi></hi> Pole with an iron hook at the end, used for pushing off from or holding on to objects when in a boat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">boat-knife</hi></hi> Knife kept at the bow of a whaleboat, used for cutting the whale line in an emergency. Also <hi rend="bold">line-knife</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">boat-header</hi></hi> Commander of a whaleboat, usually a mate, who kills the harpooned whale.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">boat-spade</hi></hi> Short-handled tool usually used to cut a hole in the dead whale through which to pass a towing line.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">boatswain</hi></hi> Pronounced “bos’n.” A subordinate ship’s officer in charge of rigging, cables, anchors, and supplies.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bone in her mouth</hi></hi> A fast-moving vessel creating a white bow wave is said to have a bone in her mouth.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">boom</hi></hi> 1) The heavy pole extending from the mast along the foot of a <hi rend="bold">fore-and-aft sail</hi>. 2) A small spar rigged to extend the length of a <hi rend="bold">yard</hi> to permit adding a small <hi rend="bold">stunsail</hi> beside the <hi rend="bold">square sail</hi>, thereby extending the total sail area. 3) Other booms, also attached to the masts, are used in moving cargo or bringing aboard parts of the butchered whale.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bow</hi></hi> The front of a vessel. <hi rend="italic">The bows</hi> signifies the entire rounded front part.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bowline</hi></hi> Pronounced “bohlin.” A fixed loop made in a line as part of a knot of that name. Also a “rope leading forward from the [vertical edge] of a square sail to keep [it extended]” (Dana).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bowsman</hi></hi> The man who pulls the second oar, after the harpooneer, and is later directly behind the mate who has come to the bow to lance the whale.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bowsprit</hi></hi> The pole projecting from the bow of a vessel.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">box-line</hi></hi> A section of harpoon line coiled in the bow of the whaleboat. Defined in Ch. 60.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">brace up</hi></hi> Using the <hi rend="bold">braces</hi>, sailors pull the <hi rend="bold">yards</hi> as far as possible toward the fore-and-aft position, thereby pointing the ship as closely into the wind as it can sail. Also <hi rend="italic">brace sharp up</hi>, <hi rend="italic">brace hard up</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">braces</hi></hi> Long ropes attached to the ends of the <hi rend="bold">yardarms</hi> and leading to the deck. Pulling on them, sailors change the angle of the sails to the wind.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">break out</hi></hi> Remove objects from the <hi rend="bold">hold</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">breaker</hi></hi> Small barrel for liquids.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">brig</hi></hi> Two-masted, <hi rend="bold">square-rigged</hi> vessel.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bright waist</hi></hi> A broad band of white paint encircling the hull. On it black squares were sometimes painted to deceive pirates, who, from a distance, might mistake them for gun-ports and believe that the vessel was armed with cannon.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bring by the lee</hi></hi> Unintentionally turn the vessel so the wind hits the <hi rend="bold">lee</hi> side of its sails and may possibly cause it to capsize.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">brit</hi></hi> Tiny marine organisms, including crustaceans, the food of <hi rend="bold">baleen</hi> whales; defined in Ch. 58.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bulkhead</hi></hi> A partition wall below deck.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bull’s eye</hi></hi> Thick, rounded piece of glass set in the deck to let light below; also a small block of strong wood with a hole through which a rope may pass.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">bulwarks</hi></hi> Pronounced “bularks.” The part of a ship’s side above the deck.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Burtons</hi></hi> Hoisting <hi rend="bold">tackles</hi> for moving items into or out of the hold.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">by the board</hi></hi> Over the side, overboard.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Cape-Horner</hi></hi> Large, square-rigged ship built to withstand the rigors of a Cape Horn passage.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">capstan</hi></hi> Large, upright cylindrical device, turned by men pushing on long, spoke-like bars, and used for heavy tasks, such as raising the anchor. See <hi rend="bold">windlass</hi>, which serves the same functions, and appears twice as often in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">capstan-head</hi></hi> The rounded top of the capstan.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">card</hi></hi> Short for <hi rend="bold">compass card</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">carlines</hi></hi> Carlings; fore-and-aft timbers between the deck beams, which in the cabin are ceiling beams.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cask</hi></hi> Containers varying greatly in size used for different purposes. An oil cask contains six barrels (Ch. 98), though the term <hi rend="bold">barrel</hi> is also inexact.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">chains</hi></hi> Combination of rigid links of chain and narrow wooden platforms called <hi rend="italic">channels</hi>, fastened to the sides of a ship to take the strain of the rigging supporting the masts.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">chock a’ block</hi></hi> 1) The situation when the two blocks of a <hi rend="bold">tackle</hi> come together, at the limit of its use. 2) Full to the brim, said of the hold or a container.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">chocks</hi></hi> Lead-lined grooves in the <hi rend="bold">prow</hi> of a whaleboat through which the harpoon line travels.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">chronometer</hi></hi> Exceptionally precise timepiece set to Greenwich Mean Time, and used in finding a ship’s longitude.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">close-reef</hi></hi> Partially tie up a sail so that its minimum area is exposed to the wind.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">clumsy cleat</hi></hi> Brace in the <hi rend="bold">bow</hi> of a whaleboat, in which the harpooner or the lance-throwing mate places his knee for stability.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">coasting smack</hi></hi> Fishing boat that stays close to shore.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cockpits</hi></hi> Properly <hi rend="italic">cockpit</hi>. Low-ceilinged space below the waterline in a man-of-war, used for treating the wounded.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">coffer-dam</hi></hi> A watertight structure within which repairs can be made below water level.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">coming afoul of</hi></hi> Coming dangerously in contact or getting tangled with.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">companion-way</hi></hi> Protected staircase between the deck and the level below.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">compass-card</hi></hi> Pivoted horizontal disk marked with the points and degrees of the compass. Also simply <hi rend="bold">card</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cooper’s club hammer</hi></hi> Axe-like hammer used by the cooper (barrel-maker).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">copper</hi></hi> Sheathing on a wooden hull to protect it from boring worms.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">copper-pump</hi></hi> Device used to pump whale oil from one barrel to another.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cranes</hi></hi> Hinged, triangular wooden supports that swing out to support the whaleboats when they are hanging from the ship’s side.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cross-trees</hi></hi> Light, horizontal timbers attached high up on a mast. In Ch. 35 Ishmael stands on the <hi rend="bold">t’gallant</hi> cross-trees, on the lookout for whales.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">crotch</hi></hi> A support in the <hi rend="bold">bow</hi> of the whaleboat for the wooden ends of the harpoons; defined in Ch. 63.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">crowd sail.</hi></hi> Raise as many sails as possible.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">crown</hi></hi> The place where the arms of an anchor join its shank.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cruising ground</hi></hi> An area of the sea where, expecting to find whales, a whaler will slowly sail back and forth.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cutting stage</hi></hi> Narrow platform hung over a ship’s side for men to stand on while removing (<hi rend="bold">cutting in</hi>) the whale’s blubber.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cutting tackles</hi></hi> Heavy, multiple block-and-tackle arrangement with a large hook, used in the process of stripping off the whale’s blubber. See Ch. 67.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">cutting-in</hi></hi> Removing the whale’s blubber.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Davy Jones</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">Davy Jones’s Locker</hi> at the bottom of the sea, the destination of the dead in sailor folklore.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">dead reckoning</hi></hi> “Dead” is a corruption of the abbreviation “ded.,” meaning “deduced”; <hi rend="italic">dead reckoning</hi> deduces a ship’s approximate position relative to its previous one by multiplying speed by time elapsed to give distance covered, by observing the compass courses steered, and by estimating the effects of <hi rend="italic">drift</hi> caused by winds and currents. It is much less precise than celestial navigation.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">dog-vane</hi></hi> Small flag or streamer indicating wind direction.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">double-banked</hi></hi> Two men to an oar.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">douse sail</hi></hi> Lower sails in a hurry.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">down helm</hi></hi> Push the tiller away from the wind, thereby turning the ship itself toward the wind. A wheel is turned toward the wind to achieve the same effect.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">draw</hi></hi> Require a certain depth of water in order to float; said of a vessel.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">eye-splice</hi></hi> Loop made by weaving the strands of the end of a rope back into its body.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">fathom</hi></hi> Six feet in length or depth.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">fiddle-headed beak</hi></hi> Decorative block of wood carved like the head of a violin; an economical alternative to a figurehead.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">fore</hi></hi> 1) Forward part of a vessel and the opposite of <hi rend="bold">aft</hi>. 2) Short for foremast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">fore-and-aft sails</hi></hi> Sails (mostly triangular) set from masts or <hi rend="bold">stays</hi> rather than from <hi rend="bold">yards</hi>. “All sails which are not set to yards” (Smyth).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">fore hatchway</hi></hi> Opening in the deck above the forward hold.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">forecastle</hi></hi> Pronounced “fohcs’l.” 1) The sailors’ living/sleeping quarters, below decks in the <hi rend="bold">bow</hi> of the ship. 2) Short for the <hi rend="italic">forecastle deck</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">forecastle deck</hi></hi> That part of the deck above the sailors’ quarters, forward of the foremast; sometimes also called, confusingly, the <hi rend="italic">forecastle</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">forecastle scuttle</hi></hi> Stairway from the deck to the <hi rend="bold">forecastle</hi> below.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">foremast</hi></hi> The first mast, closest to the <hi rend="bold">bow</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">foul</hi></hi> 1) Entangled or dangerously touching, as in “got foul of,” or “a foul line.” 2) Unfavorable or contrary, as “foul weather” or “a foul breeze.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">founder</hi></hi> Sink.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">from stem to stern</hi></hi> From front to back, end to end.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">furl</hi></hi> Roll up and secure a sail on its <hi rend="bold">yard</hi> or <hi rend="bold">boom</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">gaff</hi></hi> Hooked tool used for moving pieces of blubber.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">galliot</hi></hi> Dutch or Flemish cargo vessel with rounded sides and flattened bottom.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">gam</hi></hi> “A social meeting of two (or more) Whale-ships” at sea. (Melville’s definition, Ch. 53.)</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">gangway</hi></hi> On the <hi rend="italic">Pequod</hi>, the passageway between the deck and the stern cabin below.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">give way</hi></hi> Command to begin rowing or to row harder.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">glass</hi></hi> Telescope.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">grapnel</hi></hi> Small, anchor-like device with several arms, used for dragging the sea floor and for holding on to objects.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">green-hand</hi></hi> Inexperienced crewman.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">ground-swell</hi></hi> Long, rolling waves.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">ground-tier butts</hi></hi> Bottom layer of large oil casks in the hold.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">gunwale</hi></hi> Pronounced “gun’l”; strip of wood along the top of a vessel’s side.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">halyards</hi></hi> Ropes for raising and lowering sails.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hamper</hi></hi> 1) Spars and rigging aloft; also <hi rend="italic">top-hamper</hi>. 2) Tangled ropes and other gear.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">handspike</hi></hi> Lever used for turning a <hi rend="bold">windlass</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hard down</hi></hi> Command to a helmsman to steer into the wind, bringing the vessel more or less to a stop.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">harpoon</hi></hi> Barbed spear used to fasten the whaleboat to a whale; the fishhook of whaling.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hatch</hi></hi> Covering for a <hi rend="bold">hatchway</hi> (also called a <hi rend="italic">hatch</hi>), an opening in the deck of a ship.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hatchway</hi></hi> Square or rectangular opening in the deck, giving access to the deck below or to a <hi rend="bold">hold</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hawser</hi></hi> Thick rope used for towing and other heavy work.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">head sea</hi></hi> Waves running directly against the course of a vessel.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">headsails</hi></hi> triangular <hi rend="bold">fore-and-aft</hi> sails at a vessel’s bow.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">head-wind</hi></hi> Wind blowing from the direction of a vessel’s intended course.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">headway</hi></hi> Forward progress through the water.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">heave-to</hi></hi> Make a pause on the sea by adjusting sails to counteract one another and so keep the vessel relatively still; past tense <hi rend="bold">hove to</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">heave down</hi></hi> Tip a vessel over on one side for repairs, careen. Also <hi rend="italic">heave out</hi>. (Past tense, <hi rend="italic">hove down</hi>.)</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">helm</hi></hi> 1) Steering position. 2) The steering gear (wheel, tiller, rudder).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">helmsman</hi></hi> Sailor at the helm, steering the ship.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hogshead</hi></hi> Large barrel holding at least 63 gallons.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hold</hi></hi> Large storage compartment; a whaleship might have three.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hornpipe</hi></hi> Lively sailor’s dance.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">horns</hi></hi> Ends of the <hi rend="bold">cross-trees</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">horse-pieces</hi></hi> Blocks of blubber about 10 inches wide and 2 feet long (Browne), so called because they were placed on a wooden bench called a “horse” to be sliced.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hove out</hi></hi> Tipped up on one side.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hove over</hi></hi> Leaning.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">hove-to</hi></hi> Stopped.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Indiaman</hi></hi> Large cargo vessel trading with the East Indies (which includes Indonesia, the Philippines, Southeast Asia, and India).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">jib</hi></hi> Triangular sail rigged to the <hi rend="bold">jib-boom</hi> and <hi rend="bold">jib-stay</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">jib-boom</hi></hi> “A Spar supported by the <hi rend="bold">bowsprit</hi>, and extending beyond it” (Russell).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">jib-stay</hi></hi> The support line leading from the <hi rend="bold">foremast</hi> to the <hi rend="bold">jib-boom</hi>, on which the triangular <hi rend="bold">jib</hi> sail is strung.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">jolly-boat</hi></hi> A small work boat, usually carried at the stern of a vessel and sometimes called a <hi rend="italic">yawl</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">jury-mast</hi></hi> Temporary replacement for a lost or badly damaged mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">keel</hi></hi> The lowest timber of a vessel, and its backbone.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">keel up</hi></hi> Capsize.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">kelson</hi></hi> Long, strong timber bolted to the ship’s keel for reinforcement.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">kentledge</hi></hi> Pig iron <hi rend="bold">ballast</hi>, laid along the <hi rend="bold">kelson</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">keelson.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">King-Post</hi></hi> “Short, square timber known by that name in Arctic whalers [serving]…to brace the ship against the icy concussions of those battering seas” (Melville’s definition, Ch 27).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">knight-heads</hi></hi> Strong timbers coming up vertically through the deck in the bow of a vessel; they support the <hi rend="bold">bowsprit</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lance</hi></hi> Spear used to kill the whale by striking a vital organ.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">larboard</hi></hi> Left, or the left side when facing forward on a ship. The now-common term <hi rend="italic">port</hi> is not used in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lash the helm a’lee</hi></hi> Fasten the steering mechanism so the ship remains pointed into the wind, stopping its forward motion. Also <hi rend="italic">a-lee the helm</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lashing</hi></hi> Rope fastening one thing to another.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lead</hi></hi> Lead weight attached to a marked line, used for measuring water depth beneath a vessel; also short for <hi rend="italic">lead line</hi>, the line and weight together.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">league</hi></hi> Three nautical miles, each of which is 6,080 feet. One degree of latitude equals 60 nautical miles or 20 leagues.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lee</hi></hi> 1) The side protected from the wind. 2) The direction opposite to that from which the wind is blowing; also <hi rend="bold">leeward</hi>. See also <hi rend="bold">bring by the lee</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lee coast</hi></hi> A shore on a ship’s <hi rend="bold">lee</hi> side (to <hi rend="bold">leeward</hi>) close enough to be a danger because the wind may blow the vessel ashore.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lee-beam</hi></hi> At a right angle to the middle of the ship, on the <hi rend="bold">lee</hi> side.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lee-way</hi></hi> The distance a ship is pushed to <hi rend="bold">leeward</hi> of its course by the wind.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">leeward</hi></hi> Pronounced “looard.” Downwind.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lifts</hi></hi> Ropes leading from each <hi rend="bold">mast-head</hi> to its <hi rend="bold">yardarm</hi> ends, supporting the weight of the <hi rend="bold">yards</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">line-knife</hi></hi> See <hi rend="bold">boat-knife</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">line-of-battle ship</hi></hi> The largest warship of the time, carrying seventy-four or more guns.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">locker</hi></hi> Storage chest or closet.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">log</hi></hi> Log book, a daily record of all navigational details and other observations.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">log-line</hi></hi> A thin line marked with attached knots and wound on a reel. At the line’s end is a <hi rend="italic">chip</hi> or <hi rend="italic">log</hi> of wood that is thrown overboard. The line unreels for a set period of time, and the length of line that has run out by then indicates the ship’s speed.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">loggerhead</hi></hi> “[A] stout sort of post rooted in the keel [of a whaleboat], and rising some two feet above the level of the stern platform” (Melville’s definition, Ch. 48).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lubber</hi></hi> Nautically ignorant, awkward person.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">lubber’s-hole</hi></hi> An opening in the platform called the <hi rend="bold">top</hi>; the scorned access to the topmast, easier than climbing the supporting ropes (<hi rend="bold">shrouds)</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">luff</hi></hi> Or <hi rend="italic">luff up</hi>; bring the bow closer to the wind.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">main brace</hi></hi> Rope attached to an end of the <hi rend="bold">main-yard</hi>, used to control the angle of the <hi rend="italic">mainsail</hi> to the wind.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">main-mast</hi></hi> Of a whaleship’s three masts, the center and tallest one.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">main-top</hi></hi> The platform at the top of the lower <hi rend="bold">main-mast</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">main-truck</hi></hi> The round cap on the <hi rend="bold">main-mast</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">main-yard</hi></hi> The lowest <hi rend="bold">yard</hi> on the <hi rend="bold">main-mast</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">make</hi></hi> 1) To see. 2) To arrive at. 3) <hi rend="italic">Make sail</hi> is to set sail. 4) <hi rend="italic">Make fast</hi> is to secure.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">man-rope</hi></hi> Safety line.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">marline</hi></hi> Pronounced “marlin.” Narrow, two-stranded, tarred rope.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">marling-spike</hi></hi> Pointed metal tool used in splicing rope; also <hi rend="italic">marlinespike</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">mast-head</hi></hi> The top of a mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">men before the mast</hi></hi> Those who live in the <hi rend="bold">forecastle</hi>, forward of the foremast; non-officers.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">mess</hi></hi> Group of shipmates who eat their meals together.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">middle-watch</hi></hi> Midnight to 4 a.m.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">midships</hi></hi> “The middle part of the vessel, either with regard to her length or breadth” (Smyth); also <hi rend="italic">amidships</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">mincing knives</hi></hi> Cutting implements over 2 feet long, with a handle at each end; used to slice blubber for the <hi rend="bold">try-pots</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">mizen shrouds</hi></hi> The fixed rigging supporting the rearmost mast, the <hi rend="bold">mizen-mast</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">mizen-mast</hi></hi> The third and rearmost mast; commonly spelled <hi rend="italic">mizzenmast</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">mizentop</hi></hi> Small platform at the top of the lower <hi rend="bold">mizen-mast</hi>, the ship’s third mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">oakum</hi></hi> Fibers from unraveled old ropes, impregnated with tar and used to caulk seams in wooden ships.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">offing</hi></hi> 1) That distant part of the sea visible from shore. 2) A good distance out to sea at the start of a voyage.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">on the quarter</hi></hi> From the rear, at about a 45-degree angle to the ship’s side.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">open</hi></hi> 1) To sight. 2) Unobscured.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">orlop-deck</hi></hi> The lowest deck; also <hi rend="italic">orlop</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">packet</hi></hi> Vessel making regular, scheduled trips between the same ports.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">pike</hi></hi> Single-pronged pole used for moving chunks of blubber.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">piled-up</hi></hi> With all sails set.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">pin</hi></hi> Short for <hi rend="bold">belaying pin</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">plug-hole</hi></hi> Drain hole in the bottom of a boat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">pod</hi></hi> A school of whales; a group that travels together.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">point</hi></hi> 1/32 of a compass circle, or 11.25 degrees.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">poop</hi></hi> Raised section of the deck at the stern.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Post Captain</hi></hi> Commanding officer of a ship who also has the naval rank of Captain.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">preventer tackles</hi></hi> Additional ropes as backup to the rudder tackles.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">proa</hi></hi> Large Malay war-vessel, propelled by oars and sails.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">prow</hi></hi> The <hi rend="bold">bow</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">quarter</hi></hi> The side of a vessel, from the <hi rend="bold">stern</hi> forward to the rigging supporting the <hi rend="bold">main-mast</hi> (Lever, Dana). See <hi rend="bold">on the quarter</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">quarter-boat</hi></hi> One of the whaleboats hanging from the ship’s <hi rend="bold">quarter</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">quarter-deck</hi></hi> The part of the deck to the rear of the <hi rend="bold">main-mast</hi>, and special domain of the captain.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">raise</hi></hi> See and shout out for.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">range</hi></hi> Come abreast of another vessel or a whale.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">razee</hi></hi> Cut down, reduce. (Normally in reference to a ship’s hull.)</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">reef</hi></hi> Reduce sail area by tying up part of the sail.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">reeve</hi></hi> Pass a rope through a hole or over the wheel of a pulley.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">riggers</hi></hi> Workers hired to prepare the ship’s ropes and <hi rend="bold">tackle</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">rigging</hi></hi> A vessel’s visible ropes. A sailing vessel has <hi rend="italic">standing rigging</hi>, fixed ropes supporting the masts, and <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">running rigging</hi></hi>, pulled on to control yards and sails.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">ring-bolt</hi></hi> Large iron ring bolted through the deck.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">rope walk</hi></hi> A building in which rope was manufactured; it could be 1,000 feet long or more.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">round-house</hi></hi> Normally a cabin in the stern large enough to walk around in (thus its name), but in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> also the French captain’s privy (Ch. 99).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">rowlocks</hi></hi> Pronounced “rolicks”; spaces cut in a boat’s <hi rend="bold">gunwale</hi> for the oars to rest in while rowing.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">royal mast</hi></hi> The highest section of any mast; also, confusingly, the name given to the top portion of the top-gallant mast; also called in the text <hi rend="bold">t’ gallant mast</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">royal mast-head</hi></hi> The top of the <hi rend="bold">royal mast</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">royal yard</hi></hi> The fourth <hi rend="bold">yard</hi> from the deck, on any mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">run</hi></hi> A separate area below decks where a ship begins to narrow and curve upward toward the stern.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">running rigging</hi></hi> Ropes that are pulled on or otherwise adjusted while sailing.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sail</hi></hi> Figure of speech for a sailing ship or ships.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">schooner</hi></hi> Common type of sailing vessel with two or more masts, <hi rend="bold">fore-and-aft</hi> rigged.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">scud</hi></hi> Blowing mist or low, broken clouds.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">scupper-holes</hi></hi> Drainholes in the deck’s gutters. Also <hi rend="italic">scuppers</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">scuttle</hi></hi> 1) An opening in the deck which, in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>, is always the entrance to a stairway leading below. 2) Verb meaning to sink a vessel by making or opening holes in its hull.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">scuttle-butt</hi></hi> Fresh-water cask on deck. From sailors’ conversations there comes the meaning “gossip.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">seas</hi></hi> Waves, as in “sledge-hammering seas” (Ch. 135); also singular, as in “a combing sea dashed me off” (Ch. 100).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Season-on-the-Line</hi></hi> One of the best places and times to hunt sperm whales in the Pacific was within a few degrees of the equator (<hi rend="italic">the Line</hi>) from near the Galapagos Islands off South America to the Kingsmills Islands 90 degrees longitude to the west, and from November or December to April.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">seizings</hi></hi> Bindings of cord or rope.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">seventy-four</hi></hi> Large, 74-gun warship.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">shallop</hi></hi> Small boat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">shears</hi></hi> Beams above the quarter-deck on some whaleships, bearing spare or disabled boats; defined in Ch. 131.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sheave</hi></hi> See <hi rend="bold">blocks . . . sheaves</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sheet home</hi></hi> Spread the sail horizontally as far as possible by pulling on the <hi rend="bold">sheets</hi>, the ropes attached to one or both lower corners of a sail.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sheets</hi></hi> 1) Ropes controlling the lower corners or <hi rend="italic">clews</hi> of <hi rend="bold">square sails</hi> and the rear lower corners of <hi rend="bold">fore-and-aft sails</hi> (also called <hi rend="italic">clews</hi>). 2) The sheets of a <hi rend="bold">boom</hi> hold it against the force of the wind in its sail.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">ship biscuit</hi></hi> Unsalted flour-and-water biscuit baked hard for preservation; <hi rend="italic">hardtack</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">ship keepers</hi></hi> Crew members who work only aboard ship (not in the whaleboats).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">shoal</hi></hi> 1) Large group (usually of sea-creatures). 2) Particularly shallow place in the water.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">shorten</hi></hi> Reduce sail area by <hi rend="bold">furling</hi> and/or <hi rend="bold">reefing</hi> the sails set.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">shrouds</hi></hi> The fixed (<hi rend="italic">standing</hi>) <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">rigging</hi></hi> supporting the masts.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">skiff</hi></hi> Small rowboat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">skrimshander</hi></hi> Now called “scrimshaw”: incised sperm whale teeth or items carved from whale bone (Melville’s definition, Ch. 57).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sky-sail</hi></hi> A small, light <hi rend="bold">square sail</hi> above the r<hi rend="bold">oyal</hi>, used in fair weather.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">skylarking</hi></hi> Fooling; playing tricks.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">skysail-poles</hi></hi> Detachable upper extremities of masts, rising above the <hi rend="bold">royal masts</hi> to support the highest yards and sails, <hi rend="bold">sky-sails</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">slip the cable</hi></hi> Let go of the anchor cable rather than raise the anchor.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sloop</hi></hi> Sailing vessel with one mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sogger</hi></hi> Meaning “soldier”; in sailor-usage, someone whose supposed hard work is only pretense.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sou’-wester</hi></hi> Waterproof sailor’s hat with an extra-wide brim at the back.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">soundings</hi></hi> Material from the sea bottom brought up by a deep-sea measuring line and lead (as used in Ch. 106); to be <hi rend="italic">on soundings</hi> is to be in water shallow enough for the line to reach the sea floor; <hi rend="italic">off soundings</hi> means being in water too deep to be measured by the line.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">spar</hi></hi> Wooden, sail-supporting part of a vessel. “The general term for any <hi rend="bold">mast</hi>, <hi rend="bold">yard</hi>, <hi rend="bold">boom</hi>, <hi rend="bold">gaff</hi>, &amp;c.” (Smyth).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">speak:</hi></hi> Communicate with a ship at sea.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">splice</hi></hi> 1) Make two ropes into one by weaving their strands together. 2) A joining made by weaving together. See <hi rend="bold">eye-splice</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sprung</hi></hi> Strained enough to injure the wood fibers.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">square in</hi></hi> Turn the <hi rend="bold">yards</hi> so that they (and their <hi rend="bold">square sails</hi>) are at right angles to the hull of the vessel. Also <hi rend="italic">square the yards</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">square-rigged</hi></hi> Referring to a vessel with masts crossed by horizontal <hi rend="bold">yards</hi> from which rectangular <hi rend="bold">square sails</hi> hang.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">square sail</hi></hi> Four-cornered sail hung from a <hi rend="bold">yard</hi> which is suspended at the middle from a mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stand away</hi></hi> Steer a course, as in “stood away for the nearest harbor” (Ch. 54).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Star—bo-l-e-e-n-s</hi></hi> The men in the starboard watch; from <hi rend="bold">starboard</hi> and <hi rend="bold">bowline</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">starboard</hi></hi> Right, or the right side when facing forward on a ship.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stave</hi></hi> Smash in or puncture, past tense <hi rend="bold">stove</hi>; as in “come a stove boat and stove body when they will, for stave my soul, Jove himself cannot” (Ch. 7).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stay</hi></hi> Rope supporting a mast segment (as <hi rend="italic">main-topmast stay</hi>, <hi rend="italic">fore-t’gallant stay</hi>, etc.). A <hi rend="italic">forestay</hi> leads straight forward; a <hi rend="italic">backstay</hi> leads to the ship’s side, to the rear.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stem</hi></hi> The foremost timber in the hull of a vessel.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stern</hi></hi> The rear of a vessel; and as a verb, to row backwards. Used in various expressions, such as <hi rend="italic">by the stern</hi>, meaning stern-first, “[the <hi rend="italic">Pequod</hi>] profoundly settled by the stern” (Ch. 124); <hi rend="italic">under the stern</hi>, meaning close to the stern, “[a boat] pulled round under the stern” (Ch. 48), and also from behind, “a ship . . . bearing down under the stern” (Ch. 100).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stern sheets</hi></hi> The space to the rear of the <hi rend="bold">thwarts</hi> (rowing seats) in a small boat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">storm-trysail</hi></hi> Strong triangular sail used in bad weather.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stove</hi></hi> Also <hi rend="italic">staved,</hi> <hi rend="italic">staven</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">stoven,</hi> the past tense and participle of <hi rend="bold">stave</hi>; describing anything smashed in or punctured.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">strike</hi></hi> To lower. <hi rend="italic">Strike down</hi> is to lower something into the hold.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">stunsail</hi></hi> Pronounced “stuns’l.” Studding sail, a light sail rigged from a portable extension to a <hi rend="bold">yardarm</hi> called a stunsail <hi rend="bold">boom</hi>, and set in fair weather to increase speed.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sway up</hi></hi> Lift by means of <hi rend="bold">tackles</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">sword-mat</hi></hi> A yarn mat, named for the sword-shaped wooden slat used in weaving it.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">t’ gallant-mast</hi></hi> Topgallant mast, the third section of a mast from the deck up, pronounced as Melville spelled it. The <hi rend="bold">royal-mast</hi> is actually the top portion of this mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">tack</hi></hi> Change from one course to another by turning the vessel’s <hi rend="bold">bow</hi> through the wind.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">tackles</hi></hi> Pronounced “taykls.” Lifting devices made of ropes and pulleys (see <hi rend="bold">blocks . . . sheaves</hi>).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">taffrail</hi></hi> Curved deck railing at the ship’s stern.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">tarpaulins</hi></hi> Waterproof hats.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">thole-pins</hi></hi> Upright pins in the <hi rend="bold">gunwale</hi> of a boat that keep the oars in place while rowing.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">thwart</hi></hi> Rowing seat of a whaleboat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">tiller</hi></hi> Steering lever attached to the rudder.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">timber head</hi></hi> The part of a ship’s rib above the deck, to which large ropes may be tied.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">top</hi></hi> Platform at the top of a lower mast.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">top-block</hi></hi> Large single-pulley block used to raise or lower the topmasts.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">top-gallant sails</hi></hi> Pronounced “t’gallant” and sometimes spelled that way in <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi>. The third level of sails above the deck.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">top-maul</hi></hi> Heavy hammer.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">topsails</hi></hi> Second layer of sails above the deck.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">train oil</hi></hi> Oil from right whales, large baleen whales; defined in Ch. 32.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">transom</hi></hi> A crossbeam in the stern, used as a seat.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">tree-nails</hi></hi> Pronounced “trunnels.” Long hardwood pins joining together the planks and timbers as nails would do.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">trick</hi></hi> Two-hour turn at the helm (Russell).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">trim dish</hi></hi> Adjust a vessel’s posture, its <hi rend="italic">trim</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">truck</hi></hi> Small circle of wood topping a mast; metaphorically, the finishing piece.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">try-pots</hi></hi> Huge iron pots mounted in the brick <hi rend="bold">try-works</hi> on a whaleship’s deck, in which blubber is fried to extract the oil. See Ch. 96.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">try-works</hi></hi> The brick structure on deck holding the <hi rend="bold">try-pots</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">tub</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">Line tub</hi> placed in the bottom of a whaleboat, in which the harpoon line is coiled.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Turk’s-head</hi></hi> Complex, turban-shaped decorative knot.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">turn to!</hi></hi> “Get to work!”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">turning flukes</hi></hi> Said of a whale in the act of diving, and thereby showing its tail flukes.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">under weigh</hi></hi> A ship is under weigh when the anchor has been raised (<hi rend="italic">weighed</hi>). It is <hi rend="italic">under way</hi> when it is moving through the water.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">up helm</hi></hi> Command to move the tiller toward the windward side of the vessel, which would turn it so the wind blows from astern.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">waif pole</hi></hi> “[A] pennoned pole…which, when additional game is at hand, [is] inserted upright into the floating body of a dead whale, both to mark its place on the sea, and also as token of prior possession…” (Ch. 87).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">waist</hi></hi> The midsection of the deck, between the <hi rend="bold">forecastle</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">quarterdeck</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">watch</hi></hi> A period of time on duty (usually four hours), and the men in that duty group. The on-duty watch is <hi rend="italic">on deck</hi>, while those off duty are referred to as <hi rend="italic">below</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">weather side</hi></hi> Windward side; the side struck by the wind, opposite the <hi rend="bold">lee</hi> side.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">weather-sheet</hi></hi> Rope on the windward side of a vessel controlling a <hi rend="bold">boom</hi> or the lower corner of a sail.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">whale-pike</hi></hi> Single-pronged pole used for moving pieces of blubber.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">whalebone</hi></hi> See <hi rend="bold">baleen</hi>. Also <hi rend="italic">whale-bone</hi> but not <hi rend="italic">whale bone</hi>, which is actual bone.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">whip</hi></hi> Light <hi rend="bold">tackle</hi> made of a single rope and single <hi rend="bold">block</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">white-bone</hi></hi> The white water at the bow of a moving vessel or the head of a swimming whale. See also <hi rend="bold">bone in her mouth</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">windlass</hi></hi> Horizontal cylindrical machine near the bow, turned with handles or with levers called <hi rend="bold">handspikes</hi>, and used, as is a <hi rend="bold">capstan</hi>, in raising the anchor and other heavy tasks.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">windlass-bitts</hi></hi> Two strong timbers protruding from the deck and supporting the ends of the <hi rend="bold">windlass</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">working</hi></hi> Coming loose.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">yard</hi></hi> Long, heavy pole, attached at its center to a mast, from which a <hi rend="bold">square sail</hi> is suspended. A yard is a type of <hi rend="bold">spar</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">yard-arm</hi></hi> One of a <hi rend="bold">yard</hi>’s two arms, from the mast to its end.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">yaw</hi></hi> Swing from one side to the other of an intended course.</p>
        </body></text></TEI>
