<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transcription"><body><div type="section-1"><pb facs="#f000"/>
				<head>HAWTHORNE AND HIS MOSSES.</head>
				<head><hi rend="small-caps">by a virginian spending july in vermont</hi>.</head>
				<p><hi rend="small-caps">A papered</hi> chamber in a fine old farm-house,<lb/> a mile from any other dwelling, and dipped to <lb/> the eaves in foliage--surrounded by moun-<lb/>tains, old woods, and Indian ponds,--this, surely, is the place to write of Hawthorne.<lb/> Some charm is in this northern air, for love<lb/> and duty seem both impelling to the task. A<lb/> man of a deep and noble nature has seized me<lb/> in this seclusion. His wild, witch-voice rings <lb/> through me; or, in softer cadences, I seem to hear it in the songs of the hill-side birds <lb/> that sing in the larch trees at my window.</p>
				<p>Would that all excellent books were found-<lb/>lings, without father or mother, that so it<lb/> might be we could glorify them, without in-<lb/>cluding their ostensible authors!<note>HM had used a full-stop in the MS.</note> Nor would<lb/> any true man take exception to this; least of<lb/> all, he who writes, "When the Artist rises high<lb/> enough to achieve the Beautiful, the symbol by<lb/> which he makes it perceptible to mortal senses<lb/> becomes of little value in his eyes, while his<lb/> spirit possesses itself in the enjoyment of the reality."</p>
				<p>But more than this. I know not
                what would be <lb/> the right name to put on the title-page of<lb/> an excellent
                    book; but this I feel, that the <lb/>names of all fine authors are fictitious
                    ones,<lb/> far more so than that of Junius; simply stand-<lb/>ing, as they do,
                    for the mystical, ever-eluding<lb/> spirit of all beauty, which ubiquitously
                    pos-<lb/>sesses men of genius. Purely imaginative as<lb/> this fancy may appear,
                    it nevertheless seems to<lb/> receive some warranty from the fact, that on<lb/>
                    a personal interview no great author has ever<lb/> come up to the idea of his
                    reader. But that<lb/> dust of which our bodies are composed, how <lb/> can it
                    fitly express the nobler intelligences<lb/> among us? With reverence be it
                    spoken, that<lb/> not even in the case of one deemed more than<lb/> man, not
                    even in our Saviour, did his visible<lb/> frame betoken anything of the
                    augustness of <lb/>the nature within. Else, how could those<lb/> Jewish
                    eyewitnesses fail to see heaven in his glance!</p>
                <p> It is curious, how a man may travel along a<lb/> country road, and yet miss the
                    grandest, or<lb/> sweetest of prospects by reason of an inter-<lb/>vening hedge,
                    so like all other hedges, as in<lb/> no way to hint of the wide landscape
                    beyond.<lb/> So has it been with me concerning the en-<lb/>chanting landscape in
                    the soul of this Haw-<lb/>thorne, this most excellent Man of Mosses.<cb/> His
                    "Old Manse" has been written now four<lb/> years, but I never read it till a day
                    or two<lb/> since. I had seen it in the book-stores--heard<lb/> of it
                    often--even had it recommended to me<lb/> by a tasteful friend, as a rare, quiet
                    book, per-<lb/>haps too deserving of popularity to be popu-<lb/>lar. But there
                    are so many books called "ex-<lb/>cellent," and so much</p>
            
               
                <p>unpopular merit, that <lb/>amid the thick stir of other things, the hint of<lb/> my tasteful
                    friend was disregarded; and for<lb/> four years the Mosses on the Old Manse
                    never<lb/> refreshed me with their perennial green. It<lb/> may be, however,
                    that all this while the book,<lb/> likewise, was only improving in flavor
                    and<lb/> body. At any rate, it so chanced that this<lb/> long procrastination
                    eventuated in a happy re-<lb/>sult. At breakfast the other day, a mountain<lb/>
                    girl, a cousin of mine, who for the last two<lb/> weeks has every morning helped
                    me to straw-<lb/>berries and raspberries, which, like the roses<lb/> and pearls
                    in the fairy tale, seemed to fall into<lb/> the saucer from those
                    strawberry-beds, her<lb/> cheeks--this delightful creature, this charming<lb/>
                    Cherry says to me-- "I see you spend your<lb/> mornings in the haymow; and
                    yesterday I<lb/> found there 'Dwight's Travels in New En-<lb/>gland.' Now I have
                    something far better than<lb/> that, something more congenial to our summer<lb/>
                    on these hills. Take these raspberries, and<lb/> then I will give you some
                    moss." "Moss!"<lb/> said I. "Yes, and you must take it to the<lb/> barn with you, and good-by to 'Dwight' ".</p>
                <p>With that she left me, and soon returned<lb/> with a volume, verdantly bound, and
                    garnished<lb/> with a curious frontispiece in green; nothing<lb/> less than a
                    fragment of real moss cunningly pressed to a fly-leaf. "Why this," said I<lb/>
                    spilling my raspberries, "this is the 'Mosses<lb/> from an Old Manse.'" "Yes"
                    said cousin<lb/> Cherry, "yes, it is that flowery Hawthorne."<lb/> "Hawthorne
                    and Mosses," said I ,"no more:<lb/> it is morning: it is July in the country: and I</p>
            
       
            
                <p>am off for the barn."</p>
                <p>Stretched on that new mown clover, the<lb/> hill-side breeze blowing over me
                    through the<lb/> wide barn door, and soothed by the hum of the<lb/> bees in the
                    meadows around, how magically<lb/> stole over me this Mossy Man! And how<lb/>
                    amply, how bountifully, did he redeem that<lb/> delicious promise to his guests
                    in the Old<lb/> Manse, of whom it is written--"Others could<lb/> give them
                    pleasure, or amusement, or instruc-<lb/>tion--these could be picked up
                    anywhere--but<lb/> it was for me to give them rest.<lb/> Rest, in a life of
                    trouble! What better could be done<lb/> for weary and world-worn spirits?
                    What<lb/> better could be done for anybody, who came<lb/> within our magic
                    circle, than to throw the spell<lb/> of a magic spirit over him?" So all that
                    day,<lb/> half-buried in the new clover, I watched this<lb/> Hawthorne's
                    "Assyrian dawn, and Paphian<lb/> sunset and moonrise, from the summit of our
                    Eastern Hill."</p>
                <p>The soft ravishments of the man spun me<lb/> round about in a web of dreams, and
                    when<lb/> the book was closed, when the spell was over,<lb/> this wizard
                    "dismissed me with but misty re-<lb/>miniscences, as if I had been dreaming of
                    him."</p>
                <p>What a wild moonlight of contemplative<lb/> humor bathes that Old Manse!--the
                    rich and<lb/> rare distilment of a spicy and slowly-oozing<lb/> heart. No
                    rollicking rudeness, no gross fun<cb/> fed on fat dinners, and bred in the
                    lees<lb/> of wine,--but a humor so spiritually gentle, so<lb/> high, so deep,
                    and yet</p>
            
       
            
                <p>so richly relishable, that<lb/> it were hardly inappropriate in an angel. It<lb/>
                    is the very religion of mirth; for nothing so<lb/> human but it may be advanced
                    to that. The<lb/> orchard of the Old Manse seems the visible<lb/> type of the
                    fine mind that has described it.--<lb/> those twisted and contorted old trees,
                    "that<lb/> stretch out their crooked branches, and take such hold of the
                    imagination, that we remem-<lb/>ber them as humorists and odd-fellows."<lb/> And
                    then, as surrounded by these grotesque<lb/> forms, and hushed in the noon-day
                    repose of<lb/> this Hawthorne's spell, how aptly might the<lb/> still fall of
                    his ruddy thoughts into your soul<lb/> be symbolized by "the thump of a
                    great<lb/> apple, in the stillest afternoon, falling without<lb/> a breath of
                    wind, from the mere necessity of<lb/> perfect ripeness!" For no less ripe
                    than<lb/> ruddy are the apples of the thoughts and fancies<lb/> in this sweet
                    Man of Mosses.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="align(center)"> "Buds and Bird-voices"--</hi><lb/> What a
                    delicious thing is that! "Will the<lb/> world ever be so decayed, that Spring
                    may not<lb/> renew its greenness?" And the "Fire-<lb/>Worship." Was ever the
                    hearth so glorified<lb/> into an altar before? The mere title of that<lb/> piece
                    is better than any common work in fifty<lb/> folio volumes. How exquisite is
                    this:-- "Nor<lb/> did it lessen the charm of his soft, familiar<lb/> courtesy
                    and helpfulness, that the mighty<lb/> spirit, were opportunity offered him,
                    would<lb/> run riot through the peaceful house, wrap its<lb/> inmates in his
                    terrible embrace, and leave<lb/> nothing of them save their whitened</p>
            

                <p>bones.<lb/> This possibility of mad destruction only made<lb/> his domestic
                    kindness the more beautiful and<lb/> touching. It was so sweet of him, being
                    en-<lb/>dowed with such power, to dwell, day after<lb/> day, and one long,
                    lonesome night after an-<lb/>other, on the dusky hearth, only now and then<lb/>
                    betraying his wild nature, by thrusting his red<lb/> tongue out of the
                    chimney-top! True, he had<lb/> done much mischief in the world, and was<lb/>
                    pretty certain to do more, but his warm heart<lb/> atoned for all. He was kindly
                    to the race of<lb/> man."</p>
                <p>But he has still other apples, not quite so<lb/> ruddy, though full as ripe;--
                    apples, that have<lb/> been left to wither on the tree, after the plea-<lb/>sant
                    autumn gathering is past. The sketch of<lb/> "The Old Apple Dealer" is conceived
                    in the<lb/> subtlest spirit of sadness; he whose "sub-<lb/>dued and nerveless
                    boyhood prefigured his<lb/> abortive prime, which, likewise, contained<lb/>
                    within itself the prophecy and image of his<lb/> lean and torpid age." Such
                    touches as are in<lb/> this piece can not proceed from any common<lb/> heart.
                    They argue such a depth of tender-<lb/>ness, such a boundless sympathy with
                    all<lb/> forms of being, such an omnipresent love, that<lb/> we must needs say
                    that this Hawthorne is<lb/> here almost alone in his generation, --at
                    least,<lb/> in the artistic manifestation of these things.<lb/> Still more. Such
                    touches as these, -- and<lb/> many, very many similar ones, all through his<lb/>
                    chapters--furnish clues, whereby we enter a<lb/></p>
            
       

       
                <p>little way into the intricate, profound heart<lb/> where they originated. And we
                    see, that<lb/> suffering, some time or other and in some shape<lb/> or other,--
                    this only can enable any man to<lb/> depict it in others. All over him,
                    Hawthorne's </p></div></body></text>