<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transcription"><body><div type="section-1"><p><pb facs="#f001"/> melancholy rests like an Indian Summer,<lb/> which, though
                    bathing a whole country in one<lb/> softness, still reveals the distinctive hue
                    of<lb/> every towering hill, and each far-winding vale.</p>
                <p>But it is the least part of genius that attracts<lb/> admiration. Where Hawthorne
                    is known, he<lb/> seems to be deemed a pleasant writer, with a<lb/> pleasant
                    style, --a sequestered, harmless man,<lb/> from whom any deep and weighty thing
                    would<lb/> hardly be anticipated--a man who means no<lb/> meanings. But there is
                    no man, in whom<lb/> humor and love, like mountain peaks, soar to<lb/> such a
                    rapt height, as to receive the irradiations<lb/> of the upper skies; --there is
                    no man in<lb/> whom humor and love are developed in that<lb/> high form called
                    genius; no such man can<lb/> exist without also possessing, as the
                    indis-<lb/>pensable complement of these, a great, deep<lb/> intellect, which
                    drops down into the universe<lb/> like a plummet. Or, love and humor are
                    only<lb/> the eyes, through which such an intellect<lb/> views this world. The
                    great beauty in such a<lb/> mind is but the product of its strength.<lb/> What,
                    to all readers, can be more charming<lb/> than the piece entitled "Monsieur du
                    Miroir;"<lb/> and to a reader at all capable of fully fathom-<lb/>ing it, what,
                    at the same time, can possess<lb/> more mystical depth of meaning?--yes,
                    there<lb/> he sits, and looks at me,--this "shape of mys-<lb/>tery," this
                    "identical Monsieur du Miroir."<lb/></p>
            
       
   
                <p>"Methinks I should tremble now, were his<lb/> wizard power of gliding through all
                    impedi-<lb/>ments in search of me, to place him suddenly<lb/> before my eyes".</p>
                <p> How profound, nay appalling, is the moral<lb/> evolved by the Earth's Holocaust;
                    where--<lb/>beginning with the hollow follies and affect-<lb/>ations of the world,--all
                    vanities and empty<lb/> theories and forms are, one after another, and<lb/> by an
                    admirably graduated, growing compre-<lb/>hensiveness, thrown into the allegorical
                    fire,<lb/> till, at length, nothing is left but the all-<lb/>engendering heart of man;
                    which remaining<lb/> still unconsumed, the great conflagration is<lb/> nought.</p>
                <p> Of a piece with this, is the "Intelligence<lb/> Office," a wondrous symbolizing of
                    the secret<lb/> workings in men's souls. There are other<lb/> sketches, still more charged
                    with ponderous<lb/> import.</p>
                <p>"The Christmas Banquet," and "The<lb/> Bosom Serpent" would be fine subjects for a<lb/>
                    curious and elaborate analysis, touching the<lb/> conjectural parts of the mind that
                    produced<lb/> them. For spite of all the Indian-summer<lb/> sunlight on the hither side of
                    Hawthorne's<lb/> soul, the other side--like the dark half of the<lb/> physical sphere--is
                    shrouded in a blackness,<lb/> ten times black. But this darkness but gives<lb/> more
                    effect to the ever-moving dawn, that<lb/> forever advances through it, and
                    circumnavi-<lb/>gates his world. Whether Hawthorne has<lb/> simply availed himself of this
                    mystical<lb/> blackness as a means to the wondrous effects he<lb/> makes it to produce in
                    his lights and shades;<lb/> or whether there really lurks in him, perhaps<lb/> unknown to
                    himself, a touch of Puritanic<lb/> gloom,--this, I cannot</p>
            
       
    
  
                <p>altogether tell. Cer-<lb/>tain it is, however, that this great power of<lb/>
                    blackness in him derives its force from its ap-<lb/>peals to that Calvinistic
                    sense of Innate De-<lb/>pravity and Original Sin, from whose visita-<lb/>tions,
                    in some shape or other, no deeply think-<lb/>ing mind is always and wholly free.
                    For, in<lb/> certain moods, no man can weigh this world<lb/> without throwing in
                    something, somehow like<lb/> Original Sin, to strike the uneven balance.<lb/> At
                    all events, perhaps no writer has ever<lb/> wielded this terrific thought with
                    greater terror<lb/> than this same harmless Hawthorne. Still<lb/> more: this
                    black conceit pervades him through<cb/> and through. You may be witched by his
                    sun-<lb/>light,-- transported by the bright gildings in<lb/> the skies he builds
                    over you; but there is the<lb/> blackness of darkness beyond; and even his<lb/>
                    bright gildings but fringe and play upon the<lb/> edges of thunder-clouds. In
                    one word, the<lb/> world is mistaken in this Nathaniel Haw-<lb/>thorne. He
                    himself must often have smiled<lb/> at its absurd misconception of him. He
                    is<lb/> immeasurably deeper than the plummet of the<lb/> mere critic. For it is
                    not the brain that can<lb/> test such a man; it is only the heart. You<lb/>
                    cannot come to know greatness by inspecting<lb/> it; there is no glimpse to be
                    caught of it,<lb/> except by intuition; you need not ring it, you<lb/> but touch
                    it, and you find it is gold</p>
                <p> Now it is that blackness in Hawthorne, of<lb/> which I have spoken, that so
                    fixes and fasci-<lb/>nates me. It may be, nevertheless, that it is<lb/> too </p>
            
       
                <p>largely developed in him. Perhaps he<lb/> does not give us a ray of his light for
                    every<lb/> shade of his dark. But however this may be,<lb/> this blackness it is
                    that furnishes the infinite<lb/> obscure of his background,--that
                    back-<lb/>ground, against which Shakspeare plays his<lb/> grandest conceits,
                    the things that have made for<lb/> Shakspeare his loftiest, but most
                    circumscribed<lb/> renown, as the profoundest of thinkers. For<lb/> by
                    philosophers Shakspeare is not adored as the<lb/> great man of tragedy and
                    comedy.-- "Off with<lb/> his head! so much for Buckingham!" This<lb/> sort of
                    rant, interlined by another hand, brings<lb/> down the house,--those mistaken
                    souls, who<lb/> dream of Shakspeare as a mere man of<lb/> Richard-the-Third
                    humps, and Macbeth dag-<lb/>gers. But it is those deep far-away things in<lb/>
                    him; those occasional flashings-forth of the<lb/>intuitive Truth in him; those
                    short, quick probings at the very axis of reality;--these<lb/> are the things
                    that make Shakspeare, Shak-<lb/>speare. Through the mouths of the dark<lb/>
                    characters of Hamlet, Timon, Lear, and Iago,<lb/> he craftily says, or sometimes
                    insinuates the<lb/> things, which we feel to be so terrifically true,<lb/> that
                    it were all but madness for any good man,<lb/> in his own proper character, to
                    utter, or even<lb/> hint of them. Tormented into desperation,<lb/> Lear the
                    frantic King tears off the mask, and<lb/> speaks the same madness of vital
                    truth. But,<lb/> as I before said, it is the least part of genius<lb/> that
                    attracts admiration. And so, </p>
            
       
    

                <p> much of the<lb/> blind, unbridled admiration that has been heap-<lb/>ed upon
                    Shakspeare, has been lavished upon<lb/> the least part of him. And few of his
                    endless<lb/> commentators and critics seem to have re-<lb/>membered, or even
                    perceived, that the immedi-<lb/>ate products of a great mind are not so
                    great,<lb/> as that undeveloped, and sometimes undeve-<lb/>lopable yet
                    dimly-discernable greatness, to<lb/> which these immediate products are but the
                    in-<lb/>fallible indices. In Shakspeare's tomb lies in-<lb/>finitely more than
                    Shakspeare ever wrote.<lb/> And if I magnify Shakspeare, it is not so<lb/>
                    much for what he did do, as for what he did<lb/> not do, or refrained from
                    doing. For in this<lb/> world of lies, Truth is forced to fly like a<lb/> scared
                    white doe in the woodlands; and only<lb/> by cunning glimpses will she reveal
                    herself, as<lb/> in Shakspeare and other masters of the great<lb/> Art of
                    Telling the Truth,--even though it be<lb/> covertly, and by snatches.</p>
                <p>But if this view of the all-popular Shak-<lb/>speare be seldom taken by his
                    readers, and if<lb/> very few who extol him have ever read him<lb/> deeply, or,
                    perhaps, only have seen him on the<lb/> tricky stage, (which alone made, and is
                    still<lb/> making him his mere mob renown)--if few<lb/> men have time, or
                    patience, or palate, for the<lb/> spiritual truth as it is in that great
                    genius;--<lb/>it is, then, no matter of surprise that in a con-<lb/>temporaneous
                    age, Nathaniel Hawthorne is a<cb/> man as yet almost utterly mistaken among<lb/>
                    men. Here and there, in some quiet arm-<lb/> chair in the noisy town, or some
                    deep nook<lb/> among the noiseless mountains, he may be ap-<lb/>preciated for
                    something of what he is.</p>
            
      

                <p>But <lb/>unlike Shakspeare, who was forced to the <lb/>contrary course by
                    circumstances, Hawthorne<lb/> (either from simple disinclination, or else
                    <lb/>from inaptitude) refrains from all the popular-<lb/>izing noise and show of
                    broad farce and <lb/>blood-besmeared tragedy; content with the<lb/> still, rich
                    utterances of a great intellect in re-<lb/>pose, and which sends few thoughts
                    into circu-<lb/>lation, except they be arterialized at his large<lb/> warm
                    lungs, and expanded in his honest heart.</p>
                <p>Nor need you fix upon that blackness in <lb/>him, if it suit you not. Nor,
                    indeed, will all<lb/> readers discern it; for it is, mostly, insinuated<lb/> to
                    those who may best understand it, and ac-<lb/>count for it; it is not obtruded
                    upon every one<lb/> alike.</p>
                <p> Some may start to read of Shakspeare and <lb/>Hawthorne on the same page. They
                    may say, <lb/>that if an illustration were needed, a lesser <lb/>light might
                    have sufficed to elucidate this Haw-<lb/>thorne, this small man of yesterday.
                    But I <lb/>am not willingly one of those who, as touching <lb/>Shakespeare at
                    least, exemplify the maxim of <lb/>Rochefoucault, that "we exalt the reputation
                    <lb/>of some, in order to depress that of others";-<lb/>who, to teach all
                    noble-souled aspirants that <lb/>there is no hope for them, pronounce
                    Shak-<lb/>speare absolutely unapproachable. But Shak-<lb/>speare has been
                    approached. There are minds <lb/>that have gone as far as Shakspeare into the
                    <lb/>universe. And hardly a mortal man, who, at <lb/>some time or other, has not
                    felt as great <lb/>thoughts in him as any you will find in Ham-<lb/>let. We must
                    not inferentially malign man-<lb/>kind</p>
            
       
  
                <p>for the sake of any one man, whoever he <lb/>may be. This is too cheap a purchase
                    of con-<lb/>tentment for conscious mediocrity to make. <lb/>Besides, this
                    absolute and unconditional adora-<lb/>tion of Shakspeare has grown to be a
                    <lb/>part of our Anglo Saxon superstitions. <lb/>The Thirty-Nine articles are
                    now Forty. <lb/>Intolerance has come to exist in this matter. <lb/>You must
                    believe in Shakspeare's unapproach-<lb/>ability, or quit the country. But what
                    sort of <lb/>a belief is this for an American, a man who is <lb/>bound to carry
                    republican progressiveness into <lb/>Literature as well as into Life? Believe
                    me, <lb/>my friends, that men, not very much inferior <lb/>to Shakspeare, are
                    this day being born on the <lb/>banks of the Ohio. And the day will come<lb/>
                    when you shall say, Who reads a book by an <lb/>Englishman that is a modern? The
                    great<lb/> mistake seems to be, that even with those <lb/>Americans who look
                    forward to the coming of <lb/>a great literary genius among us, they
                    some-<lb/>how fancy he will come in the costume of <lb/>Queen Elizabeth's day,
                    be a writer of dramas <lb/>founded upon old English history or the tales <lb/>of
                    Boccaccio. Whereas, great geniuses are <lb/>parts of the times, they themselves
                    are the <lb/>times, and possess a correspondent coloring. <lb/>It is of a piece
                    with the Jews, who, while their <lb/>Shiloh was meekly walking in their
                    streets,<lb/> were still praying for his magnificent coming; <lb/>looking for
                    him in a chariot, who was already <lb/>among them on an ass. Nor must we
                    forget<lb/> that, in his own life-time, Shakspeare was</p>
            
       
   
                <p>not <lb/>Shakspeare, but only Master William Shak-<lb/>speare of the shrewd, thriving,
                    business firm <lb/>of Condell, Shakspeare &amp; Co., proprietors of the <lb/>Globe Theatre in
                    London; and by a courtly <lb/>author, of the name of Chettle, was looked at<lb/>
                    as an "upstart crow," beautified "with other <lb/>birds' feathers." For, mark it well,
                    imitation <lb/>is often the first charge brought against real <lb/>originality. Why this
                    is so, there is not space </p></div></body></text>