<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="transcription"><body><div type="section-2"><p><pb facs="#f005"/>
                    <lb/>man. "Who in the name of thunder" (as the <lb/>country- people say in this
                    neighborhood),<lb/> "who in the name of thunder, would antici-<lb/>pate any
                    marvel in a piece entitled 'Young<lb/> Goodman Brown?'" You would of course
                    <lb/>suppose that it was a simple little tale, intend-<lb/>ed as a supplement to
                    "Goody Two Shoes." <lb/>Whereas, it is deep as Dante; nor can you <lb/>finish
                    it, without addressing the author in his <lb/>own words--"It is yours to
                    penetrate, in every <lb/>bosom, the deep mystery of sin". And with<lb/></p>
            
                <p>Young Goodman, too, in allegorical pursuit of <lb/>his Puritan wife, you cry out
                    in your anguish:</p>
                <p>"'Faith !' shouted Goodman Brown, in a voice <lb/>of agony and desperation; and
                    the echoes of the <lb/>forest mocked him, crying-- 'Faith! Faith!' as if
                    <lb/>bewildered wretches were seeking her all through <lb/>the wilderness."</p>
                <p>Now this same piece, entitled "Young Good-<lb/>man Brown," is one of the two that
                    I had not <lb/>all read yesterday; and I allude to it now, <lb/>because it is,
                    in itself, such a strong positive<lb/> illustration of that blackness in
                    Hawthorne, <lb/>which I had assumed from the mere occasional <lb/>shadows of it,
                    as revealed in several of the <lb/>other sketches. But had I previously perused
                    <lb/>"Young Goodman Brown," I should have been <lb/>at no pains to draw the
                    conclusion, which I <lb/>came to, at a time when I was ignorant that the
                    <lb/>book contained one such direct and unqualified <lb/>manifestation of
                    it.</p>
                <p>The other piece of the two referred to, is <lb/>entitled "A Select Party," which,
                    in my first <lb/>simplicity upon originally taking hold of the <lb/>book, I
                    fancied must treat of some pumpkin-<lb/>pie party in old Salem, or some
                    chowder-<lb/>party on Cape Cod. Whereas, by all the gods <lb/>of Peedee! it is
                    the sweetest and sublimest <lb/>thing that has been written since Spencer
                    <lb/>wrote. Nay, there is nothing in Spencer that <lb/>surpasses it, perhaps
                    nothing that equals it. <lb/>And the test is this: read any canto in "The
                    <lb/>Faery Queen," and then read "A Select <lb/>Party," and decide which pleases
                    you the most,--<lb/>that is, if you are qualified to judge. Do not <lb/>be
                    frightened at this; for when Spencer was <lb/>alive, he was thought of very much
                    as Haw-<lb/>thorne is now,--was generally accounted just <lb/>such a "gentle"
                    harmless man. It may be, <lb/>that to common eyes, the sublimity of
                    Haw-<lb/>thorne seems lost in his sweetness,--as per-<lb/>haps in this same
                    "Select Party" of his; for <lb/>whom he has builded so august a dome of
                    sun-<lb/>set clouds, and served them on richer plate<lb/> than</p>
            
       
       
                <p>Belshazzar when he banquetted his lords <lb/>in Babylon.</p>
                <p>But my chief business now, is to point out <lb/>a particular page in this piece,
                    having reference <lb/>to an honored guest, who under the name of <lb/>"The
                    Master Genius" but in the guise "of a <lb/>young man of poor attire, with no
                    insignia of <lb/>rank or acknowledged eminence," is intro-<lb/>duced to the ,an
                    of Fancy, who is the giver <lb/>of the feast. Now the page having reference
                    <lb/>to this "Master Genius," so happily expresses <lb/>much of what I yesterday
                    wrote, touching the <lb/>coming of the literary Shiloh of America, <lb/>that I
                    cannot but be charmed by the coincidence; <lb/>especially, when it shows such a
                    parity of ideas, <lb/>at least in this one point, between a man like
                    <lb/>Hawthorne and a man like me.</p>
                <p>And here, let me throw out another conceit <lb/>of mine touching this American
                    Shiloh, or <lb/>"Master Genius," as Hawthorne calls him. <lb/>May it not be,
                    that this commanding mind has <lb/>not been, is not, and never will be,
                    individually <lb/>developed in any one man? And would it, <lb/>indeed, appear so
                    unreasonable to suppose, <lb/>that this great fulness and overflowing may
                    <lb/>be, or may be destined to be, shared by a plu-<lb/>rality of men of genius?
                    Surely, to take the <cb/>very greatest example on record, Shakspeare <lb/>cannot
                    be regarded as in himself the concretion <lb/>of all the genius of his time; nor
                    as so im-<lb/>measurably beyond Marlow, Webster, Ford, <lb/>Beaumont, Jonson,
                    that those great men can <lb/>be said to share none of his power? For <lb/>one,
                    I conceive that there were dramatists in <lb/>Elizabeth's day, between whom and
                    Shak-<lb/>speare the distance was by no means great. <lb/>Let anyone, hitherto
                    little acquainted with <lb/>those neglected old authors, for the first time
                    <lb/>read them thoroughly, or even read Charles Lamb's <lb/>Specimens of them,
                    and he will</p>
            
       

                <p>be <lb/>amazed at the wondrous ability of those Anaks <lb/>of men, and shocked at
                    this renewed example <lb/>of the fact, that Fortune has more to do with
                    <lb/>fame than merit,-- though, without merit, last-<lb/>ing fame there can be
                    none.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, it would argue too ill of my <lb/>country were this maxim to hold
                    good con-<lb/>cerning Nathaniel Hawthorne, a man, who <lb/>already, in some few
                    minds, has shed "such a <lb/>light, as never illuminates the earth save when
                    <lb/>a great heart burns as the household fire of a <lb/>grand intellect."</p>
                <p>The words are his,--in the "Select Party;"<lb/> and they are a magnificent
                    setting to a coinci-<lb/>dent sentiment of my own, but ramblingly
                    ex-<lb/>pressed yesterday, in reference to himself. <lb/>Gainsay it who will, as
                    I now write, I am <lb/>Posterity speaking by proxy--and after times <lb/>will
                    make it more than good, when I declare, <lb/>that the American, who up to the
                    present day, <lb/>has evinced, in literature, the largest brain <lb/>with the
                    largest heart, that man is Nathaniel <lb/>Hawthorne. Moreover, that whatever
                    Na-<lb/>thaniel Hawthorne may hereafter write, "The <lb/>Mosses from an Old
                    Manse" will be ulti-<lb/>mately accounted his master-piece. For there <lb/>is a
                    sure, though a secret sign in some works <lb/>which prove the culmination of the
                    powers <lb/>(only the developable ones, however) that <lb/>produced them. But I
                    am by no means de-<lb/>sirous of the glory of a prophet. I pray <lb/>Heaven that
                    Hawthorne may <hi rend="italics">yet</hi> prove me an <lb/>impostor in this
                    prediction. Especially, as I <lb/>somehow cling to the strange fancy, that, in
                    all <lb/>men, hiddenly reside certain wondrous, occult <lb/>properties--as in
                    some plants and minerals--<lb/>which by some happy but very rare accident
                    <lb/>(as bronze was discovered by the melting of <lb/>the iron and brass in the
                    burning of Corinth) <lb/>may chance to be called forth here on earth; <lb/>not
                    entirely waiting for their better discovery <lb/>in the more congenial, blessed
                    atmosphere of <lb/>heaven.</p>
                <p>Once more--for it is hard to be finite upon <lb/>an infinite subject, and all subjects
                    are infinite.</p>
            
                      
                <p>By some people, this entire scrawl of mine may <lb/>be esteemed altogether
                    unnecessary, inasmuch, <lb/>"as years ago" (they may say) "we found out <lb/>the
                    rich and rare stuff in this Hawthorne, <lb/>whom you now parade forth, as if
                    only <hi rend="italics">your-<lb/>self</hi> were the discoverer of this
                    Portuguese dia-<lb/>mond in our literature." But even granting <lb/>all this--
                    and adding to it, the assumption that <lb/>the books of Hawthorne have sold by
                    the five <lb/>thousand,--what does that signify? They <lb/>should be sold by the
                    hundred thousand; and <lb/>read by the million; and admired by every one
                    <lb/>who is capable of admiration.</p></div>
        </body>
    </text>