<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="base"><body><div type="leaf" n="6"><pb facs="#f005"/>
                <p>bones. This possibility of mad destruction only <lb/> made his domestic kindness
                    the more beautiful <lb/> and touching. It was so sweet of him, being <lb/>
                    endowed with such power, to dwell, day after <lb/> day, and one long, lonesome
                    night after <lb/> another, on the dusky hearth, only now &amp; then <lb/>
                    betraying his wild nature, by thrusting his <note>This revision was missed in
                    the NN edition.</note>
               <lb/> red tongue out of the chimney-top! True, he had <lb/>
                    done much mischief in the world, and was <lb/> pretty certain to do more, but
                    his warm heart <lb/> atoned for all<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">;</hi> He was kindly to the race of man."</p>
                <p>But he has still other apples, not <lb/> quite so ruddy, though full as
                    ripe;--apples, that <lb/> have been left to wither on the tree, after the <lb/>
                    pleasant autumn gathering is past. The <lb/> sketch of "<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">The</hi> Old Apple
                    Dealer is conceived in <lb/> the subtlest spirit of sadness; he whose "subdued <lb/>
                    and nerveless boyhood prefigured his abortive <lb/> prime, which, likewise,
                    contained within itself <lb/> the prophecy and image of <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">his</hi> lean and torpid <lb/>
                    age" Such <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">touches</hi>
                    as are <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">in</hi> this
                    piece can not <lb/> proceed from any common heart. They argue <lb/> such a
                    depth of tenderness, such a boundless sym<lb/>-pathy with <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">all</hi> forms of being,
                    such an omni-<lb/>present love, that we must needs say, that this <lb/>
                    Hawthorne is here almost alone in <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">his</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">
                    generation,</hi>
               <lb/> -- at least, in the artistic manifestation of these <lb/>
                    things<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">.</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">Still</hi> more. Such <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">touches</hi> as these, <lb/>
                    -- and many, very many <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">similar
                    ones,</hi>, all through his <lb/> chapters<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">--</hi>furnish clews,
                    whereby we enter a</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="7">
                </div></body></text>