<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="base"><body><div type="leaf" n="12"><pb facs="#f011"/>

                <p>But unlike Shakespeare, who was forced <lb/>to <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">the contrary course</hi>
                    by circumstances, Hawthorne <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">(</hi>either from <lb/>simple disinclination, or else from
                    inaptitude) <lb/>refrains from all the <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">popularizing noise</hi>
                    and show of <lb/>broad farce, <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">&amp;</hi> blood-besmeared tragedy; <lb/>content with the
                    still, rich utterance<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">s</hi>
                    of a <lb/>great intellect in repose, and which sends <lb/>few thoughts into
                    circulation, except they be <lb/>arterialized <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">at</hi> his large warm
                    lungs, and <lb/>expanded in his honest heart.</p>
                <p>Nor need you <lb/>fix upon that blackness in him, if it suit <lb/>you not. Nor,
                    indeed, will all readers discern <lb/>it, for it is, <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">mostly,</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">insinuated</hi> to those
                    who may <lb/>best undersand it, and account for it; it is <lb/>not obtruded
                    upon every one alike.</p>
                <p> Some may start to read of Shakespeare and <lb/>Hawthorne on the same page. They
                    may say, that if <lb/>an illustration were needed, a lesser light might have <lb/>sufficed
                    to elucidate this Hawthorne, this <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">small</hi> man of <lb/>yesterday. But I am not, willingly, one
                    of those, who, <lb/>as touching Shakespeare at least, exemplify the <lb/>maxim
                    of Rochefoucault, that "we exalt the reputation <lb/>of some, in order to
                    depress that of others"<hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">
                    ;--</hi> who, to <lb/>teach all <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold"> noble-souled aspirants</hi> that there is no hope for them, <lb/>pronounce
                    Shakespeare absolutely unapproachable. <lb/>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">But</hi>
               <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">Shakespeare</hi> has
                    been approached. There are minds <lb/>that have gone as <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">far</hi> as Shakespeare
                    into <lb/>the universe. And hardly a mortal man, <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">who,</hi>
               <lb/>at some
                    time or other, has not felt <lb/>as great thoughts in him as any you will find <lb/>in
                    Hamlet. We must not <hi xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="bold">
                    inferentially</hi> malign mankind</p>
            </div>

            <div type="leaf" n="13">
                </div></body></text>