<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>(Billy in the Darbies)</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div  id="billy-in-the-darbies">
<head><ref target="#BBdarbiesNote1">(Billy in the Darbies)</ref>
<note xml:id="BBdarbiesNote1">(Billy in the Darbies): The "ballad," as it is called in Chapter 30, is a dramatic monologue, fair copied in ink in HM's hand, with revisions in pencil. If the date—"April 19th 1891"—added after the words "End of Book" inscribed also in pencil at the bottom of the poem's final leaf is any indication, these pencil changes represent part of HM's last revision acts for his novella. The title, tucked in the upper right hand corner of the poem's first leaf, and surrounded by parentheses, is also a late revision, likely triggered by revisions to the third to last line of the poem, in which HM revises "this iron" to "this shackles" to "this darbies." Chances are this incomplete revision inspired HM's title; see "these darbies," below. His displaying the title parenthetically also corresponds to the final subtitle for the entire book, "(An inside narrative.)". See note on "Billy Budd Sailor" in Chapter 1.</note>
</head> <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0789.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/17619"/>
				<lg type="ballad">
	<l>Good of the Chaplain to enter Lone Bay</l>
<l>And down on his marrow-bones here and pray</l>
<l>For the likes just o' me, Billy Budd.—But, look:</l>
<l>Through the port comes the moon-shine astray!</l>
<l>It tips the guard's <choice ><orig>cutlas</orig><reg>cutlass</reg></choice> and silvers this nook;</l>
<l>But 'twill die in the dawning of Billy's last day. </l>
<l>A jewel-block they'll make of me tomorrow,</l>
<l>Pendant pearl from the yard-arm-end</l>
<l>Like the ear-drop I gave to Bristol Molly— <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0791.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/17622"/></l>
<l>O, 'tis me, not the sentence they'll suspend. </l>
<l>Ay, Ay, all is up; and I must up too</l>
<l>Early in the morning, aloft from alow.</l>
<l>On an empty stomach now never it would do.  </l>
<l>They'll give me a nibble—bit o' <choice ><orig>buiscit</orig><reg>biscuit</reg></choice> ere I go.</l>
<l>Sure, a messmate will reach me the last parting cup;</l>
<l>But, turning heads away from the hoist and the belay,</l>
<l>Heaven knows who will have the running of me up!</l>
<l>No pipe to those halyards.—But aren't it all sham?</l>
<l>A blur's in my eyes; it is dreaming that I am. </l>
<l>A hatchet to my <choice ><orig>hauzer</orig><reg>hawser</reg></choice>? all adrift to go? <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0793.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/17621"/></l>
<l>The drum roll to grog, and Billy never know?</l>
<l>But Donald he has promised to stand by the plank;</l>
<l>So I'll shake a friendly hand ere I sink.</l>
<l>But—no! It is dead then I'll be, come to think.—</l>
<l>I remember Taff the Welshman when he sank.</l>
<l>And his cheek it was like the budding pink</l>
<l>But me they'll lash me in hammock, drop me deep. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0795.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/17620"/></l>
<l>Fathoms down, fathoms down, how I'll dream fast asleep. </l>
<l>I feel it stealing now. Sentry, are you there? </l>
<l>Just ease <choice ><orig>this</orig><reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_30172">these darbies</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ref_30172">these darbies: HM's last minute revisions to this phrase also triggered the title of poem, displayed in parentheses at the top of the poem's first leaf: "(Billy in the Darbies)"; see note above. Initially, HM had in his fair copy of the poem settled on the line "Just ease this iron at the wrist,". However, he revised "iron" to "shackles" and then again to "darbies" (slang for handcuffs), but he neglected to modify "this" to the plural "these". MEL emends to "these darbies."</note></reg></choice> at the wrist,</l>
<l>and roll me over fair,</l>
<l>I am sleepy, and the oozy weeds about me twist.</l></lg></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
