<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>Chapter 23</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="chapter-23">
				<pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0673.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/16824"/> <lb/>
			<head>Chapter 23</head><lb/>
				<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Of a series of incidents within a brief term rapidly following each other, the adequate   <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0671.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18548"/> narration may take up a term less brief, especially if explanation or comment here and there seem requisite to the better understanding   <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0673.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18559"/> of such incidents. Between the entrance into the cabin of him who never left it alive, and him who when he did leave it left it as one condemned to die; between <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0675.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/16826"/> this and the closeted interview just given less than an hour and a half  had elapsed. It was an interval long enough however to awaken speculations among no few of the ship's company as to what it was that could be detaining in the cabin the Master-at-arms and the sailor; for a rumor that both of them had been seen to enter it and neither of them had been seen to emerge, this rumor had got abroad upon the gun-decks and in the tops; the people of a great war ship being in one respect like villagers, taking microscopic note of every outward movement or non-movement going on. When therefore in weather <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0677.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/16497"/> not at all tempestuous all hands were called in the second dog-watch, a summons under such circumstances not usual in those hours, the crew were not wholly unprepared for some announcement extraordinary, one having connection too with the continued absence of the two men from their wonted haunts.</p>

<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">There was a moderate sea at the time; and the moon, newly risen and near to being at its full, silvered the white spar-deck wherever not blotted by the clear-cut shadows horizontally thrown of fixtures and moving men. On either side the quarter-deck the marine <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0679.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/16830"/> guard under arms was drawn up; and Captain Vere standing in his place surrounded by all the ward-room officers, addressed his men. In so doing his manner showed neither more nor less than that properly pertaining to his supreme position aboard <ref target="#ref_29618">his own ship.</ref><note xml:id="ref_29618">his own ship.] Originally, Melville wrote "aboard the 'Indomitable.'" Later, in pencil, he deleted "Indomitable" and inserted "his own ship," neglecting to delete "the." MEL deletes the remnant "the."</note> In clear terms and concise he told them what had taken place in the cabin; that the master-at-arms was dead; that he who had killed him had been already tried by a summary court and condemned to death; and that the execution would take place in the early morning watch. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0681.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/16499"/> The word <hi rend="italic">mutiny</hi> was not named in what he said. He refrained too from making the occasion an opportunity for any preachment as to the maintenance of discipline, thinking perhaps that under existing circumstances in the navy the consequence of violating discipline should be made to speak, for itself.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Their captain's announcement was listened to by the throng of standing sailors in a dumbness like that of a seated congregation of believers in hell listening to the clergyman's announcement of his Calvinistic text. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0683.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18552"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">At the close, however, a confused murmer went up. It began to wax. All but instantly, then, at a sign, it was pierced and suppressed by shrill whistles of the Boatswain and his Mates <ref target="#ref_29619">piping down one watch</ref><note xml:id="ref_29619">piping down one watch] Down the left margin of his manuscript leaf, and in pencil, Melville wrote a note to himself: "Another order to be given here in place of this one." In the top margin, also in pencil, and preceded with a finger pointing device he wrote: "The word was given to about ship." As the document shows, Melville did not then finalize these instructions by deleting and inserting text at the revision site, and his remote, marginal instructions to revise are a kind of uncompleted revision. HS and NN emend by following the instructions: they remove "piping down one watch," ending the sentence with "mates." And they insert a new final sentence: "The word was given to about ship."  But given his exploratory revision practices, Melville may well have revised beyond the instructions given here once he started "finalizing" his revision.  To underscore this fluid condition of revision, MEL alerts readers to the uncompleted nature of the revision but does not emend.</note>.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">To be prepared for burial Claggart's body was delivered to certain petty-officers of his mess. And here, not to clog the sequel with lateral matters, it may be added that at a suitable hour, the Master-at-Arms was committed to the sea with every funeral honor properly belonging to his naval grade. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0685.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18608"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In this proceeding as in every public one growing out of the tragedy strict adherence to usage was observed. Nor in any point could it have been at all deviated from, either with respect to Claggart or Billy Budd without begetting undesirable speculations in the ship's company, sailors, and more particularly men-of-war's men, being of all men the greatest sticklers for usage. For similar cause, all communication  between Captain Vere and the condemned one <ref target="#ref_29620"><choice ><orig>closed / ended</orig><reg>ended</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29620">ended] Originally, Melville wrote "closed with the closeted interview." Later, in pencil, he inscribed "ended" over "closed," probably to reduce the sound of redundancy in "closeted." But Melville did not delete "closed." MEL emends this oscillating revision to "ended."</note> with the closeted interview already given, the latter being now surrendered to the <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0687.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18610"/> ordinary routine preliminary to the end. His transfer under guard from the Captain's quarters was effected without unusual precautions—at least no visible <choice ><orig>ones.—</orig><reg>ones.</reg></choice> If possible not to let the men so much as surmise that their officers anticipate aught amiss from them is the tacit rule in a military ship. And the more that some sort of trouble should really be apprehended the more do the officers keep that apprehension to themselves; <choice ><orig>tho&#x27;</orig><reg>though</reg></choice> not the less unostentatious vigilance may be augmented.  <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0689.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18612"/> In the present instance the sentry placed over the prisoner had strict orders to let no one have communication with him but the Chaplain. And certain unobtrusive measures were taken absolutely to insure this point.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
