<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>Chapter 12</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="chapter-12">
				<pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0328.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15835"/> <lb/>
			<head>Chapter 12</head><lb/>
				<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<hi rend="italic">Pale ire, envy and despair</hi></p>

<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">That Claggart's figure was not amiss, and his face, save the chin, well moulded, has already been said. Of these favorable points he seemed not insensible, for he was not only neat but careful in his dress. But the form of Billy Budd was heroic; and if his face was without the intellectual look of the pallid Claggart's, not the less was it <ref target="#ref_29844">lit</ref><note xml:id="ref_29844">lit] Click on the associated MS leaf thumbnail, and then click on the Revision Narratives explaining Melville's revisions at this site.</note>, like his, from within, though from a different source. The bonfire in his heart made luminous the <ref target="#ref_29843">rose-tan</ref><note xml:id="ref_29843">rose-tan] Melville wrote "ruddiness" first, then crossed it out and wrote "rose-tan" above the line.</note> in his cheek. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0330.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15846"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In view of the marked contrast between the persons of the twain, it is more than probable that when the Master-at-arms in the scene last given applied to the sailor the proverb <hi rend="italic">Handsome is as handsome does</hi>; he there let escape an ironic inkling not caught by the young sailors who heard it, as to what it was that had first moved him against Billy, namely, his significant personal beauty.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Now envy and <choice ><orig>antipathy (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>antipathy,</reg></choice> passions irreconcilable in reason, <choice ><orig>neverthless</orig><reg>nevertheless</reg></choice> in fact may spring conjoined like Chang and Eng in one birth. Is Envy then such a monster? Well, though many an <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0332.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15848"/> arraigned mortal has in hopes of mitigated penalty pleaded guilty to horrible actions, did ever anybody seriously confess to envy? Something there is in it universally felt to be more shameful than even felonious crime. And not only does everybody disown it <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0334.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15838"/> but the better sort are inclined to incredulity when it is in earnest imputed to an intelligent man. But since its lodgement is in the heart not the brain, no degree of intellect supplies a guarantee against it. But Claggart's was no vulgar form of the passion. Nor, as directed toward Billy Budd <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0340.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15839"/> did it partake of that streak of apprehensive jealousy that marred Saul's visage <choice ><orig>perturbidly</orig><reg>perturbedly</reg></choice> brooding on the comely young David. Claggart's envy struck <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0338.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15850"/> deeper. If askance he eyed the good looks, cheery health and frank enjoyment of young life in Billy Budd, it was because these went along with a nature that as Claggart magnetically felt, had in its simplicity never willed malice or experienced the reactionary bite of that serpent. To him, the spirit lodged within Billy, and looking out from his <ref target="#ref_29849">welkin</ref><note xml:id="ref_29849">welkin] Melville wrote and deleted "blue" in the line, then "azure" above the line before writing "welkin" in pencil below the line.</note> eyes as from windows, that ineffability it was which <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0342.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15841"/> made the dimple in his <ref target="#ref_29852">dyed</ref><note xml:id="ref_29852">dyed] Melville replaced "rich."</note> cheek, suppled his joints, and dancing in his yellow curls made him preeminently the Handsome Sailor. One person <choice ><orig>excepted (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>excepted,</reg></choice> the master-at-arms was perhaps the only man in the ship <choice ><orig>intellectualy</orig><reg>intellectually</reg></choice> capable of adequately appreciating the moral phenomenon presented in Billy Budd. And the insight but intensified his passion, which assuming various secret forms within him, at times assumed that of cynic disdain—disdain of innocence—<ref target="#ref_29981">To be nothing more than innocent!</ref><note xml:id="ref_29981">To be nothing more than innocent!] Originally, HM set this phrase off as a sentence by itself, and without quotation marks, as the narrator's performance of words that the disdainful Claggart might think. In revising the preceding sentence, he added a dash linking sentence to phrase, without de-capitalizing "To." HS and NN put "to" in the lower case, which confuses the grammatical structure. MEL retains the upper case to indicate the uncompleted condition of the site.</note> Yet in an aesthetic way he saw the charm of it, the courageous free-and-easy temper of it, and fain would have shared it, but he despaired of it. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0344.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15842"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">With no power to annul the elemental evil in him, <choice ><orig>tho</orig><reg>though</reg></choice> readily enough he could hide it; apprehending the good, but powerless to be it; a nature like <choice ><orig>Claggart&#x27;s (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>Claggart's,</reg></choice> surcharged with energy as such natures almost invariably are, what recourse is left to it but to recoil upon itself and like the scorpion for which the Creator alone is responsible, act out to the end the part <choice ><orig>alloted</orig><reg>allotted</reg></choice> it.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
