<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>Chapter 10</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher />
			<pubPlace />
			<date />
		<authority />
		<availability><p /></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p /></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="chapter-10"><p>
				<pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/a75lbisofmkur07pjnm3shi3plun;1" corresp="img_281" /> <lb />
			<head type="main">CHAPTER 10</head>
		</p><p>The next day an incident served to confirm Billy Budd in his incredulity as to the Dansker's strange summing up of the case submitted. <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/pxzxy7fzuzkop5wphaf8khwx5ht1;1" corresp="img_283" /> The ship at noon going large before the wind was rolling on her course, and he below at dinner and engaged in some sportful talk with the members of his mess, chanced in a sudden lurch to spill the entire contents of his soup-pan upon the new scrubbed deck. Claggart, <choice><orig>The</orig><reg>the</reg></choice> Master-at-arms, official rattan in hand, happened to be passing along the battery in a bay of which the mess was lodged, and the greasy liquid streamed just across his path. Stepping over it, he was proceeding <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/5gd9o0td9o07x8abm6w8c58j1upn;1" corresp="img_285" /> on his way without comment, since the matter was nothing to take notice of under the circumstances, when he happened to observe who it was that had done the spilling. His countenance changed. <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/w63ia1ndhk5kuv7i5uhprvrwgxvp;1" corresp="img_287" /> Pausing, he was about to ejaculate something hasty at the sailor, but checked himself, and pointing down to the streaming soup, playfully tapped him from behind with his rattan, saying in a low musical voice peculiar to him at times "Handsomely done, my lad! And handsome is as handsome did it too!" And with that passed on. Not noted by Billy as not coming within his view was the involuntary smile, or rather grimace, that accompanied Claggart's equivocal words. Aridly it drew down the thin corners of his shapely mouth. But everybody taking his remark as <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/ogehhc9ug3v0g0f6y6lj50h8fpva;1" corresp="img_289" /> meant for humorous, and at which therefore as coming from a superior they were bound to laugh, "with <choice><orig>counterfieted</orig><reg>counterfeited</reg></choice> glee" acted accordingly; and Billy tickled, it may be, by the allusion to his being the handsome sailor, merrily joined in; then addressing his messmates <choice><orig>exclaimed (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>exclaimed,</reg></choice> "There now, who says that Jimmy Legs is down on me!"</p>

<p>"And who said he was, Beauty?" demanded one Donald with some surprise. Whereat the foretopman looked a little foolish recalling that it was only one person, Board-her-in-the-smoke who had suggested what to him was the smoky idea that this <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/196pqpczroto06q8qy5q3fforl3m;1" corresp="img_291" /> Master-at-arms was in any peculiar way hostile to him. Meantime that functionary resuming his path must have momentarily worn some expression less guarded than that of the bitter smile, and usurping the face from the heart, some distorting expression perhaps, for a drummer-boy heedlessly frolicking along from the opposite direction and chancing to come into light collision with his person was strangely disconcerted by his aspect. Nor was the impression lessened when the official <ref target="#ref_29778">impulsively</ref><note xml:id="ref_29778">impulsively: Melville used pencil to insert "impulsively" before and above "giving him". HS and NN read this word as "impetuously." (Click on thumbnail to inspect HM's inscription.)</note> giving him a sharp cut with the rattan, vehemently <choice><orig>exclaimed (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>exclaimed,</reg></choice> "Look where you go!" </p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
