<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 25</title>



			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

				<publisher />
				<pubPlace />
				<date />
				<authority />
				<availability>
					<p />
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p />
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="chapter-25"><p>
				<pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/k65eqqqom7max8p7b8xuiblaqbxb;1" corresp="img_719" /> <lb />
				<head type="main">CHAPTER 25</head>
			</p><p>The night so luminous on the spar-deck but
					otherwise on the cavernous ones below, levels so like the tiered galleries in a
					coal-mine—the luminous night passed away. But, like the prophet in the chariot
					disappearing in heaven and dropping his mantle to Elisha, the withdrawing night
					transferred its pale robe to the breaking day. A meek shy light appeared in the
					East where stretched a diaphonous fleece of white furrowed vapor. <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/zqiwrdrqs6ojokhcy5wguo6jucsn;1" corresp="img_721" /> That light slowly
					waxed. Suddenly <hi rend="italic">eight bells</hi> were struck aft, responded to
					by one louder metallic stroke from forward. It was four o'clock in the morning.
					Instantly the silver whistles were heard summoning all hands to witness
					punishment. Up through the great hatchways rimmed with racks of heavy shot, the
					watch below came <choice>
						<orig>pouring (no comma in MS)</orig>
						<reg><ref target="#ref_30457">pouring,</ref><note xml:id="ref_30457">pouring,] MEL adds the comma to clarify reading
								by indicating that the following word "overspreading" recapitulates
								but extends the word "pouring."</note></reg>
					</choice> overspreading with the watch already on deck the space between the
					mainmast and foremast including that occupied by the capacious launch and the
					black booms tiered on either side of it, boat and booms making a summit of
					observation for the powder-boys and younger tars. <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/o12ess2yyftl5n8cbv9zq8gbfqc2;1" corresp="img_723" /> A different group
					comprising one watch of topmen leaned over the rail of that sea-balcony, no
					small one in a seventy-four, looking down on the crowd below. Man or boy none
					spake but in whisper, and few spake at all. Captain Vere—as before, the central
					figure among the assembled commissioned officers—stood nigh the break of the
					poop-deck facing forward. Just <choice>
						<orig>Below</orig>
						<reg><ref target="#ref_29817">below</ref><note xml:id="ref_29817">HM added "Just" in the margin next to "Below"
								without lowercasing it.</note></reg>
					</choice> him on the quarter-deck the marines in full equipment were drawn up
					much as at the scene of the promulgated sentence. <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/d3wgn7zuboxrkl643fzges6uoamu;1" corresp="img_725" /></p>

				<p>At sea in the old time, the execution by
					halter of a military sailor was generally from the fore-yard. In the present
					instance, for <ref target="#ref_29839">special reasons</ref><note xml:id="ref_29839">special reasons] For this inserted phrase, HM originally
						wrote "for strategic reasons."</note> the main-yard was assigned. Under an
					arm of <ref target="#ref_29838">that yard</ref><note xml:id="ref_29838">that
						yard] A yard is the spar from which a sail hangs, and the main-yard crosses
						the main or central mast. The arm or yard-arm is the end of the spar.
						Depending upon the direction of the wind, a yard-arm can be designated as a
						weather yard (i.e. fronting the wind) or lee yard (away from the wind). In a
						deleted sentence preceding this one, HM had specified that Billy is brought
						under the "lee-yard," placing him out of the wind. But this specification is
						lost along with the deletion of the sentence. Billy now appears under "an
						arm of that yard," meaning one or the other of the two main-yard-arms. In
						pencil, and above "an arm," HM wrote "weather or lee," as a note to himself
						to choose one side of the ship over the other. Visually, the choice is not
						inconsequential. Later in the chapter, HM indicates that the weather itself
						is moderate but strong enough for the ship to roll away from the wind and
						into the lee, so that if Billy were hanged from the lee-yard-arm, his body
						would sway over the sea. In ch. 21, Vere makes a point of placing the three
						jurors on the lee-side of the cabin and himself on the weather-side,
						effectively placing himself as witness higher in the tilting ship than the
						jury. Another important choice in the present chapter is the hanging of
						Billy from the main-yard, closer to the officers' area, and not, as was
						customary, from the fore-yard, where the seamen assemble. In short, HM
						places Billy's execution at the "waist" of the ship, between officers and
						crew. Vere's decision to part from convention in this placement is based on
						"special reasons"—originally "strategic reasons"—which are not divulged and
						remain open to interpretation.</note> the prisoner was presently brought up,
					the Chaplain attending him. It was noted at the time and remarked upon
					afterwards, that in this final scene the good man evinced little or nothing of
					the perfunctory. Brief speech indeed he had with the condemned one, <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/d9j9cow9gzgbdvi0mfc5ybvavhew;1" corresp="img_727" /> but the genuine
					Gospel was less on his tongue than in his aspect and manner towards him. The
					final <choice>
						<orig>preperations</orig>
						<reg>preparations</reg>
					</choice> personal to the latter being speedily brought to an end by two
					boatswain's-mates, the consummation impended. Billy stood facing aft. At the
					penultimate moment, his words, his only ones, words wholly unobstructed in the
					utterance were these–"God bless Captain Vere!" Syllables <choice>
						<orig>So</orig>
						<reg>so</reg>
					</choice> unanticipated coming from one with the ignominious hemp about his
						neck—<ref target="#ref_29822"><choice>
							<orig>a a conventional</orig>
							<reg>a conventional</reg>
						</choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29822">Initially HM added "felon's" before
						"benediction," but he then erased "felon's" and penciled in "a conventional
						felon's" without deleting the redundant "a."</note> felon's benediction
					directed aft towards the quarters of honor; syllables too delivered in the clear
					melody of a singing-bird <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/gb8vomyuoyddn9c4ps4tklibfycv;1" corresp="img_729" /> on the point of
					launching from the twig, had a phenomenal effect, not unenhanced by the rare
					personal beauty of the young sailor spiritualized now <choice>
						<orig>thro'</orig>
						<reg>through</reg>
					</choice> late experiences so poignantly profound. </p>
				<p>Without volition as it were, as if indeed the
					ship's populace were but the vehicles of some vocal current electric, with one
					voice from alow and aloft came a resonant sympathetic echo–"God bless Captain
					Vere!" And yet at that instant Billy alone must have been in their hearts, <ref target="#ref_30458">even as he was in their eyes</ref><note xml:id="ref_30458">even as he in their eyes] Originally, HM wrote "even as
						he was in their eyes" in ink. He revised, also in ink, by adding "alone"
						first after "was" to give "he was alone" then immediately transposed "alone"
						to before "was" to give "he alone was." Later, in pencil, HM deleted both
						"alone" and "was." Deleting "alone" eliminated the awkward repetition of
						that word in the previous clause, but deleting "was" creates confusion. NN
						emends this uncompleted revision by further deleting "he" to give "even as
						in their eyes." MEL emends by restoring "was" to give "even as he was in
						their eyes." </note>. </p>
				<p>At the pronounced words and the spontaneous
					echo that voluminously rebounded them, <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/fhyzp32g2lfrqxpl44z7kt7gw3ja;1" corresp="img_731" /> Captain Vere, either <choice>
						<orig>thro</orig>
						<reg>through</reg>
					</choice> stoic self-control or a sort of momentary paralysis induced by
					emotional shock, stood erectly rigid as a musket in the ship-armorer's rack. </p>
				<p>The hull <choice>
						<orig>deliberatly</orig>
						<reg>deliberately</reg>
					</choice> recovering from the periodic roll to leeward was just regaining an
					even keel, when <ref target="#ref_29860">the last fatal <choice><orig>death-signal (no comma in MS)</orig>
						<reg>death-signal,</reg>
						</choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29860">the last fatal death-signal] Originally in ink, HM
						inscribed "when the preconcerted fatal sign was given." In pencil he then
						revised by deleting "fatal sign" and adding "signal." Deleting "signal" he
						then inserted "death-signal a" earlier in the sentence, intending to place
						it after "when the" and before "preconcerted" (inadvertently placing his
						insertion caret between "when" and "the"). He then deleted "death-" and
						added "fatal" but quickly deleted "fatal," adding "last" to give "when the
						last signal a preconcerted." However, HM underlined the deleted phrase indicating his intention to restore "fatal
						death-" so that MEL's final reading is "the last fatal death-signal". HS and
						NN do not acknowledge the restoration and print "the last signal" only. All three supply a comma
						after "signal".</note>
						 a preconcerted dumb <choice>
						<orig>one (no comma in MS)</orig>
						<reg>one,</reg>
					</choice> was given. At the same moment it chanced that the vapory fleece
					hanging low in the <ref target="#ref_29853"><choice>
							<orig>East, (comma in MS)</orig>
							<reg>East</reg>
						</choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29853">East] MEL removes the comma after
						"East," a remnant of a two-line deletion.</note> was shot <choice>
						<orig>thro</orig>
						<reg>through</reg>
					</choice> with a soft glory as of the fleece of the Lamb of God seen in mystical
					vision <pb facs="https://iiif.archivengine.com/iiif/3/uw9b6730ygjmcglkzmkflf2tdqsg;1" corresp="img_733" /> and <choice>
						<orig>Simultaniously</orig>
						<reg>simultaneously</reg>
					</choice> therewith, watched by the wedged mass of upturned faces, Billy
					ascended; and, ascending, took the full rose of the dawn. </p>
				<p>In the pinioned figure, arrived at the
					yard-end, to the wonder of <choice>
						<orig>all [no comma]</orig>
						<reg>all,</reg>
					</choice> no motion was <choice>
						<orig>apparent [no comma]</orig>
						<reg>apparent,</reg>
					</choice> none–save that created by the <ref target="#ref_30459">ship's <choice>
							<orig>motion.</orig>
							<reg>motion,</reg>
						</choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_30459">ship's motion,] The pencil addition
						of "ship's motion"—replacing "slow roll of the hull,"—is followed by a
						period. HM also placed pencil brackets around his "in moderate weather ...
						ponderously-cannoned" phrase, as if to reposition it; however, he changed
						his mind. (See following note on "in moderate weather.") MEL changes the period after "ship's motion"
						to a comma and retains the bracketed phrase following it.</note>
					<ref target="#ref_29828">in moderate weather so majestic in a great ship
						ponderously-cannoned.</ref><note xml:id="ref_29828">in moderate ...
						ponderously-cannoned] See the MS thumbnail for more details of the various
						(and uncompleted) revisions to this phrase and its leaf. HM bracketed this
						phrase and wrote a note to move it to the previous page. He then erased the
						note but did not delete the brackets. Presumably HM meant to restore the
						phrase in its original position. MEL retains the phrase, with the exception
						of the brackets.</note></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>