<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 6</title>



			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

				<publisher/>
				<pubPlace/>
				<date/>
				<authority/>
				<availability>
					<p/>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p/>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="chapter-6"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0173.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15592"/> <lb/>
				<head type="main">CHAPTER 6</head>

			</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But on board the seventy-four in which Billy now swung
				his hammock, very little in the manner of the men and nothing obvious in the
				demeanor of the officers would have suggested to an ordinary observer that the Great
				Mutiny was a recent event. In their general bearing and conduct the commissioned
				officers of a war-ship naturally take their tone from the commander, that is if he
				have that <ref target="#ed-note1">ascendency</ref><note xml:id="ed-note1">Hayford and Sealts emended to "ascendancy," but MEL and NN retain Melville's original spelling in the MS because "ascendency" was an accepted spelling in the eighteenth and nineteenth century, as the <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</hi> shows (see "ascendancy | ascendency, n.". <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. June 2021. Oxford University Press).</note> of character that ought to be his.
				<pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0175.tif"
					tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15602"/></p>

				<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Captain the Honorable Edward Fairfax Vere, to
					give his full title,
				was a bachelor of forty or thereabouts, a sailor of distinction even
					in a time prolific of renowned seamen. Though allied to the higher nobility his
					advancement had not been altogether <choice>
						<orig>oweing</orig>
						<reg>owing</reg>
					</choice> to influences connected with that circumstance. He had seen much
					service, been in many various engagements, always acquitting himself as an
					officer mindful of the wellfare of his men, but never tolerating an infraction
					of <ref target="#ref_30365">discipline,</ref><note xml:id="ref_30365"
						>discipline,] In revising this passage in ink, HM used an insertion bubble
						to add "of discipline." He later added a semi-colon outside of the bubble,
						but seems to have altered the semi-colon to a comma. NN prints the
						semi-colon here; MEL, the comma.</note> thoroughly versed in the science of
					his profession, and intrepid to the verge of temerity <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0177.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15608"/> though never
					injudiciously so. For his gallantry in the West Indian waters as flag-lieutenant
					under Rodney in that Admiral's crowning victory over De Grasse, he was made a
					post-captain. </p>

					<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Ashore in the garb of a <ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_30366"
								>civilian</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
								xml:id="ref_30366">civilian,] MEL adds the comma after "civilian" to
								clarify the ending of the (misplaced) introductory prepositional
								phrase.</note>, scarce anyone would have taken him for a sailor, more especially that
					he never garnished unprofessional talk with nautical terms, and grave in his
					bearing, evinced little appreciation of mere humor. It was not out of keeping
					with these traits that <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0179.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15610"/><choice>
						<orig>On (capitalized in MS)</orig>
						<reg>on</reg>
					</choice> a passage when nothing demanded his paramount action, he was the most
					undemonstrative of men. Any landsman observing this gentleman not conspicuous by
					his stature and wearing no pronounced insignia, emerging from his <choice>
						<orig>retreat / cabin </orig>
						<reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_29663"
								>cabin</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
								xml:id="ref_29663">cabin] Originally, Melville inscribed "retreat"
								in ink but later wrote "cabin," in pencil above. Because he did not
								delete "retreat," the site is an uncompleted and oscillating
								revision. MEL emends to "cabin."</note></reg>
					</choice> to the open deck, and noting the silent deference of the officers
					retiring to leeward, might have taken him for the King's <pb
						facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0181.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15596"/> guest, a civilian
					aboard the King's-ship some highly honorable discreet envoy on his way to an
					important post. But in fact this <choice>
						<orig>unobtrusivness</orig>
						<reg>unobtrusiveness</reg>
					</choice> of demeanor may have proceeded from a certain unaffected modesty of
					manhood sometimes accompanying a resolute nature, a modesty evinced at all times
					not calling for pronounced action, and which shown in any rank of life suggests
					a virtue aristocratic in kind. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0183.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15614"/> As with some others
					engaged in various departments of the world's more heroic activities, Captain
					Vere though practical enough upon occasion would at times betray a certain
					dreaminess of mood. Standing alone on the weather-side of the quarter deck, one
					hand holding by the <choice>
						<orig>rigging (no comma in MS)</orig>
						<reg>rigging,</reg>
					</choice> he would absently gaze off at the blank sea. At the presentation to
					him <pb
						facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0189.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15598"/> then of some minor
					matter interrupting the current of his thoughts he would show more or less
					irascibility; but instantly he would control it. </p>

					<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In the navy he was popularly known by the
					<ref target="#BB6Note1">appellation</ref><note xml:id="BB6Note1">appellation: MEL emends Melville's MS misspelling "appelation" to "appellation."</note>—Starry Vere. How such a designation happened <ref target="#ref_29667"><choice>
							<orig>to fall to upon (doubled prepositions in MS)</orig>
							<reg>to fall</reg>
						</choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29667">to fall] Originally, HM wrote "to
						fall to him." To expand at this site, he deleted "him" (but not the second
						"to") and attached a clip with new text, in pencil, beginning with "upon one
						who...." To repair the doubled prepositions in "to fall to upon one who,"
						MEL emends to "to fall upon one who."</note>
					<pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0187.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15599"/> upon one who
					whatever his sterling qualities was without any brilliant ones <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0189.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18651"/> was in this wise: A
					favorite kinsman, Lord Denton, a free-hearted fellow, had been the first to meet
					and congratulate him upon his return to England from his West Indian cruise; and
					but the day previous turning over a copy of Andrew Marvell's poems had lighted,
					not for the first time however, upon the lines entitled <hi rend="italic"
						>Appleton House</hi>, the name of one of the seats of their <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0191.tif"
						tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15600"/> common ancestor, a
					hero in the German wars of the seventeenth century, in which poem occur the
					lines, </p>

					<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<lg>
					<l><ref target="#ref_30367">This</ref> 'tis to have been from the first</l>
					<note xml:id="ref_30367">This] In manuscript, HM places
						quotation marks around the four quoted lines from Andrew Marvell's 1681 poem
						"Upon Appleton House." NN retains the quotation marks, which might suggest
						that a voice other than Marvell's is speaking. To avoid this suggestion and
						in keeping with modern conventions, MEL drops the quotation mark here and
						after "Vere" at the end of the fourth line.</note>
					<l>In a domestic heaven nursed,</l>
					<l>Under the discipline severe</l>
					<l>Of Fairfax and the starry <choice><orig>Vere" (no period in MS)</orig><reg>Vere.</reg></choice></l>
				</lg>
				</p>

				<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">And so, upon embracing his cousin fresh
					from Rodney's great victory wherein he had played so gallant a part, brimming
					over with just family pride in the sailor of their house, he exuberantly
					exclaimed, "Give ye joy, Ed; give ye joy, my starry Vere!" This got currency,
					and the novel prefix serving in familiar parlance readily to distinguish <hi
						rend="italic">The Indomitable</hi>'s captain from another Vere his senior, a
					distant <choice>
						<orig>relative (no comma in MS)</orig>
						<reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_29673"
								>relative</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
								xml:id="ref_29673">relative,] Inserting "a distant relative" as a
								second apposition, HM neglected to add a comma after "relative." MEL
								supplies the necessary comma.</note>,</reg>
					</choice> an officer of like rank in the navy, it remained permanently attached
					to the surname.</p></div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
