<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>Chapter 8</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="chapter-8"><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
				<pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0215.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15676"/> <lb/>
			<head type="main">CHAPTER 8</head>
		</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <choice ><orig>lieutenants, (comma in MS)</orig><reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_29697">lieutenants</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ref_29697">lieutenants] In revision, HM reduced a series of three kinds of officers to two, but neglected to delete a serial comma after "lieutenants." MEL removes the remnant comma, as do HS and NN.</note></reg></choice> and other commissioned gentlemen forming Captain Vere's staff it is not necessary here to particularize, nor needs it to make any mention of any of the warrant-officers. But among the petty-officers was one who having much to do with the story, may as well be forthwith introduced. His portrait I essay, but shall never hit it. This was John Claggart, the Master-at-arms. But that <choice ><orig>sea-tittle</orig><reg>sea-title</reg></choice> may to <choice ><orig>landsman</orig><reg>landsmen</reg></choice> seem somewhat equivocal. <ref target="#ref_30370">Originally,</ref><note xml:id="ref_30370">Originally,] In manuscript, HM initially supplied, in ink, what looks like an inverted, mirror-image comma. Later, he altered it by inscribing a proper comma in pencil. NN reads the alteration as a deletion of the inverted comma and does not print it.  MEL retains the comma, which also obviates the difficulty of reading "Originally doubtless, etc."</note> doubtless <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0217.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/18652"/><pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0219.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15674"/> that petty-officer's function was the instruction of the men in the use of <ref target="#ref_29701"><choice ><orig>arms. sword or cutlas</orig><reg>arms, sword or cutlass</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29701">arms, sword, or cutlass.] In ink, Melville originally inscribed "arms, sword or cutlas." In pencil, he deleted "sword or cutlas" and added a period after "arms." He then restored "sword or cutlas" without restoring the comma after "arms."  MEL emends by changing "cutlas" to "cutlass." </note>. But very long ago, <choice ><orig>oweing</orig><reg>owing</reg></choice> to the advance in gunnery making hand-to-hand encounters less frequent and giving to nitre and <ref target="#ref_30371"><choice ><orig>sulpher</orig><reg>sulpher</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_30371">sulphur] HM's manuscript spelling of "sulpher" is listed as a medieval variant in OED, suited to the era of armory "very long ago" that HM discusses.  MEL retains the non-standard spelling, as does NN.</note> the preeminence over steel, that function ceased; the master-at-arms of a great war-ship becoming a sort of Chief of Police charged among other matters with the duty of preserving order on the populous lower gun-decks.</p>

<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Claggart was a man about five and thirty, <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0221.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15678"/> somewhat spare and tall, yet of no ill figure upon the whole. His hand was too small and shapely to have been accustomed to hard toil. The face was a notable one; the features all except the chin cleanly cut as those on a Greek medallion; yet the chin, beardless as <ref target="#ref_30346">Tecumsah's</ref><note xml:id="ref_30346">Tecumsah's] MEL retain's HM's spelling of the name of Shawnee leader Tecumseh as a frequently found variant.</note>, had something of strange protuberant broadness in its make that recalled the prints of the <choice ><orig>Revd (no period in MS)</orig><reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_30372">Revd</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ref_30372">Revd] HM abbreviates "Reverend" in manuscript.  NN expands the abbreviation to "Reverend." MEL does not emend.</note></reg></choice> Dr. Titus Oates, the historic <choice ><orig>deponant</orig><reg>deponent</reg></choice> with the clerical drawl in the time of Charles II and the fraud of the alleged Popish Plot. It served Claggart in his office that his eye could cast a tutoring glance. His brow was of the sort phrenologically associated with more than average intellect; silken jet curls partly <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0223.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15680"/> clustering over it, making a foil to the pallor below, a pallor tinged with a faint shade of amber akin to the hue of time-tinted <choice ><orig>marbles. (remnant period in MS)</orig><reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_29707">marbles</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ref_29707">marbles of old.] HM deleted "of old," placing a period after "marbles." He then restored "of old" but neglected to delete the period. MEL removes the remnant period.</note></reg></choice> of old. This complexion, singularly contrasting with the red or deeply bronzed visages of the sailors, and in part the result of his official seclusion from the sunlight, <choice ><orig>tho</orig><reg>though</reg></choice> it was not exactly displeasing, nevertheless <choice ><orig>seemd</orig><reg>seemed</reg></choice> to hint of something defective or abnormal in the constitution and blood. But his general aspect and manner, were so suggestive of an education and career incongruous with his naval function that when <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0225.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15659"/> not actively engaged in it he looked like a man of high quality, social and moral, who for reasons of his own was keeping incog. Nothing was known of his former life. It might be that he was an Englishman; and yet there lurked a bit of accent in his speech suggesting that possibly he was not such by birth, but through naturalization in early childhood. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0227.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15660"/> Among certain grizzled sea-gossips of the gun-decks and forecastle went a rumor perdue that the master-at-arms was a <hi rend="italic">chevalier</hi> who had volunteered into the King's navy by way of compounding for some mysterious swindle whereof he had been arraigned at the King's Bench. The fact that <choice ><orig>nobody, (comma in MS)</orig><reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_29711">nobody</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ref_29711">nobody]  After "nobody" HM had originally inscribed "of course" with the requisite commas around it. In deleting "of course," he neglected to delete the comma after "nobody." MEL deletes the remnant comma.</note></reg></choice> could substantiate this  <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0233.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15661"/> <choice ><orig>report, (comma in MS)</orig><reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_30373">report,</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ref_30373">report,] HM's comma here is not necessary to the sentence structure but may indicate a rhetorical pause. MEL retains the comma, as does NN. </note></reg></choice> was, of course, nothing against its secret currency. Such a rumor once started on the gun-decks in reference to almost anyone below the rank of a commissioned officer would, during the period assigned to this narrative, have seemed not altogether wanting in credibility to the tarry old wiseacres of a man-of-war crew. And indeed a man of Claggart's accomplishments, without prior nautical experience entering the navy at mature life, as he did, and <choice ><orig>neccessarily</orig><reg>necessarily</reg></choice> <choice ><orig>alloted</orig><reg>allotted</reg></choice> at the start to the lowest grade in it; <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0231.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15686"/> a man too who never made allusion to his previous life ashore; these were circumstances which in the dearth of exact knowledge as to his true <choice ><orig>anticedents</orig><reg>antecedents</reg></choice> opened to the invidious a vague field for unfavorable surmise. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0235.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15690"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But the sailors' dog-watch gossip concerning him derived a vague <ref target="#BB8Note1">plausibility</ref>
<note xml:id="BB8Note1">plausibility: MEL emends Melville's MS misspelling "plausability" to "plausibility."</note> from the fact that now for some period the British Navy could so little afford to be squeamish in the matter of keeping up the muster-rolls, that not only were press-gangs notoriously abroad both afloat and ashore, but there was little or no secret about another matter, namely that the London police were at liberty to capture <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0237.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15692"/> any able-bodied suspect, any questionable fellow at large and summarily ship him to the dock-yard or fleet. Furthermore, even among voluntary enlistments there were instances where the motive thereto partook neither of patriotic impulse nor yet of a random desire to <choice ><orig>experice</orig><reg>experience</reg></choice> a bit of sea-life and martial adventure. Insolvent debtors of minor grade, together with the promiscuous lame ducks of <choice ><orig>morality (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>morality,</reg></choice> found in the Navy a convenient and secure refuge. Secure, because once enlisted aboard a King's-Ship, they were as much in <choice ><orig>sanctuary, </orig><reg><ref xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" target="#ref_29718">sanctuary</ref><note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ref_29718">sanctuary] Originally, HM had inscribed "as it were" after "sanctuary," surrounding the phrase with commas.  In deleting the phrase, he neglected to delete the comma after "sanctuary." MEL removes the remnant comma.</note></reg></choice> as the transgressor of the Middle Ages harboring himself under the shadow of the altar. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0241.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15696"/>  Such sanctioned irregularities which for obvious reasons the Government would hardly think to parade at the time and which consequently, and as affecting the least influential class of mankind, have all but dropped into oblivion, <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0239.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15694"/> <ref target="#ref_30348"><choice ><orig>lends</orig><reg>lend</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_30348">lend] HM originally wrote "lends." MEL emends to "lend" to resolve the subject-verb agreement problem. </note> color to something for the truth whereof I do not vouch, and hence have some scruple in <choice ><orig>stateing</orig><reg>stating</reg></choice>; something I remember having seen in print though the book I can not recall; but the same thing was personally communicated to me now more than forty years ago by an old pensioner in a cocked hat with whom I had a most interesting talk on the terrace at Greenwich, a Baltimore negro, a Trafalgar man. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0243.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15698"/> It was to this effect: In the case of a war-ship short of hands whose speedy sailing was imperative, the deficient quota in lack of any other way of making it good, would be eked out by draughts culled direct from the jails. For reasons previously suggested it would not perhaps be easy at the present day directly to prove or disprove the allegation. But allowed as a verity, how significant would it be of England's straits at the Time confronted by those wars which like a flight of harpies rose shrieking from the din and dust of the fallen <choice ><orig>Bastile</orig><reg>Bastille</reg></choice>. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0245.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15668"/> That <ref target="#ref_29724"><choice ><orig>era, (comma in MS)</orig><reg>era</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29724">era] Originally, HM wrote the qualifying phrase "nor long past" after "era," set it off with commas. In revision, he removed the phrase but left the comma after "era." MEL removes the remnant comma.</note> appears measurably clear to us who look back at it, and but read of it. But to the grandfathers of us graybeards, the more <choice ><orig>thoughful</orig><reg>thoughtful</reg></choice> of them, the genius of it presented an aspect like that of Camoen's Spirit of the Cape, an eclipsing menace mysterious and prodigious. Not America was exempt from apprehension. At the height of Napoleon's unexampled conquests, there were Americans who had fought at Bunker Hill who looked forward to the possibility that the Atlantic might prove no barrier against the ultimate schemes of this <choice ><orig>french</orig><reg>French</reg></choice> portentous upstart from the revolutionary chaos who seemed in act of fulfilling judgment prefigured in the Apocalypse. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0247.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15669"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">But the less credence was to be given to the gun-deck talk touching Claggart, seeing that no man holding his office in a man-of-war can ever hope to be popular with the crew. Besides, in derogatory comments upon anyone against whom they have a grudge, or for any reason or no reason mislike, sailors are much like landsmen, they are apt to exaggerate or romance it.

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">About as much was really known to the <hi rend="italic">Indomitable</hi>'s tars of the  master-at-arms' career before entering the service as an astronomer knows <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0249.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15700"/> about a comet's travels prior to its first observable appearance in the sky. The verdict of the sea quid-nuncs has been cited only by way of showing what sort of moral impression the man made upon rude uncultivated natures whose conceptions of human wickedness were necessarily of the narrowest, limited to ideas of vulgar rascality—a thief among the swinging hammocks during a night-watch, or the man-brokers and land-sharks of the sea-ports. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0251.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15704"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It was no gossip, however, but fact, that though, as before hinted, Claggart upon his entrance into the navy was, as a novice, assigned to the least honorable section of a man-of-war's crew, embracing the drudgery, he did not long remain there. The superior capacity he <choice ><orig>immediatly</orig><reg>immediately</reg></choice> evinced, his constitutional sobriety, ingratiating deference to superiors, together with a peculiar ferreting genius manifested on a singular occasion, all this capped by a certain austere patriotism abruptly advanced him to the position of master-at-arms. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0253.tif" tl_leaf="https://app.textlab.org/transcriptions/15706"/>

</p><p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Of this <choice ><orig>maratime</orig><reg>maritime</reg></choice> Chief of Police the ship's-corporals, so called, were the immediate subordinates, and compliant ones; and this, as is to be noted in some business departments ashore, almost to a degree inconsistent with entire moral volition. His place put various converging wires of underground influence under the Chief's control, capable when astutely worked <choice ><orig>thro&#x27;</orig><reg>through</reg></choice> his understrappers of operating to the mysterious discomfort if nothing worse, of any of the sea-commonalty.</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
