<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
		<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
			<title>Chapter 19</title>



		</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>

			<publisher/>
			<pubPlace/>
			<date/>
		<authority/>
		<availability><p/></availability>
	</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc><p/></sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<text>
			<body><div xml:id="chapter-19"><p>
				<pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0521.tif" corresp="img_521"/> <lb/>
			<head type="main">CHAPTER 19</head>
		</p><p>Now <ref target="#ref_29350"><choice><orig>When</orig><reg>when</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29350">when] Melville neglected to decapitalize "When" when he inserted "Now" at the head of his sentence.</note> the foretopman found himself in the cabin, closeted there, as it were, with the Captain and Claggart, he was <choice><orig>surprized</orig><reg>surprised</reg></choice> enough. But it <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0523.tif" corresp="img_523"/> was a <choice><orig>surprize</orig><reg>surprise</reg></choice> unaccompanied by apprehension or distrust. To an immature nature essentially honest and humane, forewarning intimations of subtler danger from one's kind come tardily if at all. The only thing that took shape in the young sailor's mind was this: Yes, the Captain, I have always thought, looks kindly upon me. Wonder if he's going to make me his coxswain. I should like that. And may be now he is going to ask the master-at-arms about me. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0525.tif" corresp="img_525"/></p>

<p>"Shut the door there, sentry," said the commander; "stand without, and let nobody come in.—Now, master-at-arms, tell this man to his face what you told of him to me"; and stood prepared to scrutinize the mutually confronting visages.  <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0529.tif" corresp="img_529"/> <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0527.tif" corresp="img_527"/> With the measured step and calm collected air of an asylum-physician approaching in the public hall some patient beginning to show indications of a coming paroxysm, Claggart <choice><orig>deliberatly</orig><reg>deliberately</reg></choice> advanced within short range of Billy, and <ref target="#BB19Note1">mesmerically looking him in the eye</ref><note xml:id="BB19Note1">REVISION NARRATIVE: mesmerically looking him in the eye // Having associated Claggart and mesmerism in his revisions to leaf 30 (see “mesmeristic glance” below), Melville turned to the present paragraph on the preceding leaf 29 with the idea of reinforcing the hypnotic association. In doing so, he also modified the paragraph’s rhythm and introduced his remarkable image of Claggart as an “asylum-physician.”
<lb/><lb/>
Originally, in ink on leaf 29 (image 529), Melville had rendered Claggart's movements in three short, almost cinematic sentences: "<hi rend="bold">Claggart <hi rend="italic">hesitated</hi> not an instant</hi>. Deliberately advancing ... <hi rend="bold">he spoke</hi>. <hi rend="bold">Without</hi> emphasis and in a tone more musical than ever, briefly <hi rend="bold">he delivered</hi> the accusation point-blank into his eyes." Tinkering in pencil, he then began combining these three sentences into one. He deleted "Without", substituting "minus" for it (which HS and NN do not record), and added "Without" to his first sentence, converting it to the introductory phrase "Without hesitation". He also deleted "he spoke", making "he delivered" his main subject and predicate. But before finalizing his new wording and punctuation, Melville crossed out the entire revised passage with orange crayon, and on separate paper no longer extant, he drafted a new image for Claggart. Abandoning Claggart's deliberate gait and "musical" voice, he transformed Claggart into a mesmerizing "asylum-physican." Melville then patched an inked fair copy of this new version (image 527) over the crossed-out original. For "asylum-physician," Melville could have drawn upon visits made decades earlier with friends confined to mental asylums. In his later years, Melville also frequented Staten Island's Snug Harbor — the asylum for retired sailors, governed by his brother Thomas — where in its "public halls" he might have witnessed physicans speaking in low tones to syphilitic or otherwise deranged inmates on the verge of panic.</note>, briefly recapitulated the accusation. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0533.tif" corresp="img_533"/>

</p><p>Not at first did Billy take it in. When he did, the rose-tan of his cheek looked struck as by white leprosy. He stood like one impaled and gagged. Meanwhile the <choice><orig>accuser' (no possessive s)</orig><reg>accuser's</reg></choice> eyes removing not as yet from the blue dilated ones, underwent a phenomenal change, their wonted rich violet color blurring into a muddy purple. Those lights of human intelligence losing human expression, gelidly protruding like the alien eyes of certain uncatalogued creatures of the deep.     <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0531.tif" corresp="img_531"/> <ref target="#BB19Note2">The first mesmeristic glance</ref><note xml:id="BB19Note2">REVISION NARRATIVE: The first mesmeristic glance // Melville’s introduction of mesmerism here on leaf 30 likely triggered similar revisions on the preceding leaf (see “mesmerically looking” above). In ink on leaf 30 (image 533), Melville had initially compared Claggart’s eyes — those “lights of <hi rend="bold">human</hi> intelligence” — to “uncatalogued creatures of <hi rend="bold">the deep</hi>.” Later, in pencil, he revised <hi rend="bold">“human</hi>” to “<hi rend="italic">Adam’s</hi>,” thereby adding post-Edenic implications. Then, in the leaf’s bottom margin, he squeezed several lines of experimental drafting also in pencil. Here, he altered his fair-copied “creatures of <hi rend="bold">the deep</hi>” to “creatures of <hi rend="italic"> tropic parts of that elemental host not only their first <hi rend="bold">mesmeric expression</hi> but also the last</hi>.” Beneath this inscription, he penciled further wording with what appears to be “judging the lesser? confreres? left unjudged.” (For "judging" and "lesser," HS and NN suggest "hungry" and "human", respectively.) Having second thoughts, Melville struck through “mesmeric expression,” and eventually, erased all of these penciled revisions, including his deletion of “the deep” and revision to “Adam’s,” thereby temporarily restoring his text to its fair-copy original.
<lb/><lb/>
Then, on separate paper no longer extant, Melville re-drafted a new version of his erased sentence, retaining its "first" / "last" sentence structure, the reference to mesmerism, and new hints of Eden. On a penciled fair copy of this lost drafting (image 531), he wrote “The first mesmeristic glance was one of serpent fascination; the last was as the paralyzing lurch of the torpedo-fish.” He also included the instruction “add p.30” on the patch and wrote the corresponding word “add” over the erasures on leaf 30. With the idea of Claggart’s “mesmeric” or “mesmeristic” gaze in mind, Melville returned to the preceding paragraph on leaf 29 (image 529) and made corresponding revisions there. (See “mesmerically looking” above.)</note> was one of serpent fascination; the last was as the paralyzing lurch of the torpedo-fish. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0535.tif" corresp="img_535"/>

</p><p>"Speak, man!" said Captain Vere to the transfixed one, struck by his aspect even more than by Claggart's, "Speak! defend yourself." Which appeal caused but <choice><orig>a a strange dumb</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_29358">a strange dumb</ref><note xml:id="ref_29358">a strange dumb]  Originally, in ink, Melville wrote "an ineffectual dumb gesturing" to indicate Billy's stutter. In pencil, he revised by striking out the "n" in "an" and all of "ineffectual," replacing them with "a strange," which resulted in the inadvertent doubling of "a." </note></reg></choice> gesturing and gurgling in Billy; amazement at such an accusation so suddenly sprung on inexperienced nonage; this, and, it may be, <choice><orig>horror ("at" not restored in MS)</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_29360">horror at</ref><note xml:id="ref_29360">horror at] In ink, Melville originally wrote "horror of the accuser," which places the perceived horror in Claggart himself. Later, Melville revised in pencil: he deleted "of" and added "at" and inserted "unearthly glance," which words he deleted separately, replacing them with "eyes" (neglecting to revise "accuser" to the possessive "accuser's"). The revision effectively places the horror not innately in Claggart but in Billy's perception.  However, Melville also deleted "at" without restoring "of" so that the revision is uncompleted.  HS emends by restoring "of"; NN restores "at" as does MEL.</note></reg></choice> the <choice><orig>accuser,</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_29362">accuser's</ref><note xml:id="ref_29362">accuser's] In revision, Melville neglected to add "'s" to create the possessive "accuser's."</note></reg></choice> eyes, serving to bring out his lurking defect and in this instance for the time intensifying it into a convulsed tongue-tie; while the intent head <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0537.tif" corresp="img_537"/> and entire form straining forward in an agony of ineffectual eagerness to obey the injunction to speak and defend himself, gave an expression to the face like that of a condemned Vestal priestess in the moment of being buried alive, and in the first struggle against suffocation.

</p><p>Though at the time Captain Vere was quite <choice><orig>ignonrant</orig><reg>ignorant</reg></choice> of Billy's liability to vocal impediment, he now <choice><orig>immediatly</orig><reg>immediately</reg></choice> divined it, since vividly Billy's aspect recalled to him that of a bright young schoolmate of his whom he had once seen struck by much the same <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0539.tif" corresp="img_539"/> startling impotence in the act of eagerly rising in the class to be foremost in <choice><orig>responce</orig><reg>response</reg></choice> to a testing question put to it by the master. Going close up to the young sailor, and laying a soothing hand on his shoulder, he <choice><orig>said (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>said,</reg></choice> "There is no hurry, my boy. Take your time, take your time." Contrary to the effect intended, these words so fatherly in tone, doubtless touching Billy's heart to the quick, prompted yet more violent efforts at utterance—efforts soon ending for the time in confirming the paralysis, and bringing to his face an expression which was as a crucifixion to behold. The next <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0541.tif" corresp="img_541"/> instant, quick as the flame from a discharged cannon at night, his right arm shot out, and Claggart dropped to the deck. Whether intentionally or but owing to the young athlete's superior height, the blow had taken effect full upon the <choice><orig>forhead</orig><reg>forehead</reg></choice>, so shapely and intellectual-looking a feature in the Master-at-arms; so that the body fell over lengthwise, like a heavy plank tilted from erectness. A gasp or two, and he lay motionless.

</p><p>"Fated boy," breathed Captain Vere in tone so low as to be almost a whisper, "what have you done! But here, help me." <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0543.tif" corresp="img_543"/>

</p><p>The twain raised the felled one from the loins up into a sitting position. The spare form flexibly <choice><orig>acquiesed</orig><reg>acquiesced</reg></choice>, but inertly. It was like handling a dead snake. They lowered it back. Regaining erectness Captain Vere with one hand covering his face stood to all appearance as impassive as the object at his feet. Was he absorbed in taking in all the bearings of the event and what was best not only now at once to be done, but also in the sequel? Slowly he uncovered his face; and the effect was as if the moon emerging from eclipse should reappear with quite another <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0545.tif" corresp="img_545"/> aspect than that which had gone into hiding. The father in him, manifested towards Billy thus far in the scene, was replaced by the military disciplinarian. In his official tone he bade the foretopman retire to a state-room aft, (pointing it <choice><orig>out,)</orig><reg>out),</reg></choice> and there remain till thence summoned. This order Billy in silence mechanically obeyed. Then going to the cabin-door where it opened on the quarter-deck, Captain Vere said to the sentry without, "Tell somebody to send Albert here." When the lad appeared his master so contrived it that he should not catch sight of the  prone one. "Albert," he said to him, <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0547.tif" corresp="img_547"/> "tell the Surgeon I wish to see him. You need not come back till called."

</p><p>When the Surgeon entered—a self-poised <choice><orig>man / character</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_29370">man</ref><note xml:id="ref_29370">man] Originally, Melville inscribed "a self-poised man," but later, in pencil, inserted "character" above "man." Melville did not delete one or the other, and the site remains an uncompleted or oscillating revision.  NN selects "character." MEL prints "man" at this site.</note></reg></choice> of that grave sense and experience that hardly anything could <ref target="#ref_29372"><choice><orig>surprise / take him aback</orig><reg>surprise</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29372">surprise] Originally, Melville inscribed "surprise," but at a latter time, in pencil, he inscribed "take him aback" as a possible substitution for "surprise."  However, he did not delete one or the other option, creating an uncompleted and oscillating revision. NN selects "take him aback." MEL prints "surprise" at this site.</note>,—Captain Vere advanced to meet him, thus unconsciously intercepting his view of Claggart <ref target="#ref_29374"><choice><orig>and and</orig><reg>and</reg></choice></ref><note xml:id="ref_29374">and] An uncompleted revision resulted in the doubling of "and" in MS.</note> interrupting the other's wonted <choice><orig>cerimonious</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_30399">ceremonious</ref><note xml:id="ref_30399">ceremonious] HM's manuscript misspelling "cerimonious" involves an undotted "i" for the second "e." NN prints the misspelling. Finding only one such archaic  variant in OED, MEL emends to the standard spelling.</note></reg></choice> salutation, said, "Nay. <choice><orig>tell</orig><reg>Tell</reg></choice> me how it is with yonder man," directing his attention to the prostrate one. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0549.tif" corresp="img_549"/>

</p><p>The Surgeon looked, and for all his self-command, somewhat started at the abrupt revelation. On Claggart's always pallid complexion, thick black blood was now oozing from nostril and ear. To the gazer's professional eye it was unmistakably no living man that he saw.

</p><p>"Is it so <choice><orig>then? (no quote in MS)</orig><reg>then?"</reg></choice> said Captain Vere intently watching him, "I thought <choice><orig>it.[quote]</orig><reg>it.</reg></choice> But verify it." Whereupon the customary tests confirmed the Surgeon's first <choice><orig>glance.</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_29380">glance,</ref><note xml:id="ref_29380">glance,] Drafting entirely in pencil, Melville ended his "Whereupon" clause with a period, but later deleted the first part of the sentence that had followed it, with the idea of linking the "Whereupon" clause with the deleted sentence's "who" clause.  However, Melville neglected to change his period to a comma. Regardless of punctuation, Melville's revision has created a dangling modifier. </note></reg></choice> who now looking up in <choice><orig>unfeined</orig><reg>unfeigned</reg></choice> concern, cast a look of intense <choice><orig>inquisitivness</orig><reg>inquisitiveness</reg></choice> upon his superior. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0551.tif" corresp="img_551"/> But Captain Vere, with one hand to his brow, was standing motionless. Suddenly, catching <choice><orig>the the</orig><reg>the</reg></choice> Surgeon's arm convulsively, he exclaimed, pointing down to the body–"It is the divine judgement on Ananias! <choice><orig> Look![no quote]</orig><reg>Look!"</reg></choice>

</p><p>Disturbed by the excited manner he had never before observed in the <choice><orig>"Indomitable" (no "'s" in MS)</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_29386">"<hi rend="italic">Indomitable</hi>'s"</ref><note xml:id="ref_29386">"Indomitable's"] In his pencil rough drafting, HM seems to have miswritten "Indomitable" for an intended possessive "Indomitable's." But "Indomitable" as an adjective—in this case the Surgeon's ironic descriptor for his otherwise unflappable, unexciteable, and "indomitable" captain—is a viable though remote option.</note></reg></choice> Captain, and as yet wholly ignorant of the affair, the prudent Surgeon nevertheless held his peace, only again looking an earnest interrogatory as to what it was that had resulted in such a tragedy. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0553.tif" corresp="img_553"/>

</p><p>But Captain Vere was now again motionless standing absorbed in thought. But again starting, he vehemently <choice><orig>exclaimed (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>exclaimed,</reg></choice> "Struck dead by an angel of God! Yet the angel must <choice><orig>hang! (no quote in MS)</orig><reg>hang!"</reg></choice>

</p><p>At these passionate interjections, mere incoherences to the listener as yet unapprised of the antecedents, the Surgeon was profoundly discomposed. <choice><orig>But,</orig><reg><ref target="#ref_29390">But</ref><note xml:id="ref_29390">But] MEL removes an inadvertently undeleted comma after "But."</note></reg></choice> now as <choice><orig>reccolecting</orig><reg>recollecting</reg></choice> himself, Captain Vere in less passionate tone briefly related the circumstances leading up to the event. <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0555.tif" corresp="img_555"/> <choice><orig>But (no quote in MS)</orig><reg>"But</reg></choice> come; we must despatch," he added. <choice><orig>Help (no quote in MS)</orig><reg>"Help</reg></choice> me to remove him (meaning the body) to yonder <choice><orig>compartment, (no quote in MS)</orig><reg>compartment,"</reg></choice> designating one opposite that where the foretopman remained immured. Anew disturbed by a request <ref target="#ref_29396"><choice><orig>that (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>that</reg></choice>,</ref><note xml:id="ref_29396">that,] MEL adds a comma to set off the adverbial phrase.</note> as implying a desire for secrecy, seemed unaccountably strange to him, there was nothing for the subordinate to do but comply.—

</p><p>"Go <choice><orig>now [quote] (no comma in MS)</orig><reg>now,</reg></choice>" said Captain Vere with something of his wonted manner—<choice><orig>Go (no quote in MS)</orig><reg>"Go</reg></choice> now. I shall presently call a drum-head court. Tell the lieutenants what has happened, and tell <choice><orig>Mr (no period in MS)</orig><reg>Mr.</reg></choice> Mordant," meaning the captain of marines, "and charge them  <pb facs="https://iip.textlab.org/?IIIF=mel/billybudd/modbm_ms_am_188_363_0557.tif" corresp="img_557"/> to keep the matter to themselves."</p></div></body>
		</text>
	</TEI>
